<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1013">
   <persName>
      <forename>Algernon</forename>
      <surname>Percy</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>4th Duke of Northumberland</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1792 - 1865</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Syon House, London, England (15 December 1792)</p>
      <p>Death: Alnwick, Northumberland (12 or 15 February 1865)</p>
      <p>Burial: The Percy chapel, Westminster Abbey, London</p>
      
      <p>Education: None formal, as time of war.</p>
      <p>Career: Joined navy (3 May 1805) age 12, served as midshipman in various frigates in the Mediterranean; made lieutenatn in 1811, commander 1814, acting captain of 'Caledonia' in 1815 when war ended. Never saw active service thereafter, but on reserve list promoted to rear admiral (1850), vice admiral (1857) and admiral (1862). Elevated to peerage as Baron Prudhoe (1816) because of father's wealth and position as one of the 'regent's set'. Took seat in the Lords but seldom spoke until after secceeded to the Dukedom in 1847. Travelled in Africa in 1820s and 1830s, and in 1834 both helped finance, and accompanied, Sir John Herschel's expedition to Capetown to observe the sourthern constellation and in 1847 met the costs of publication of Herschel's Cape observtions of double stars and nebulae. Also friend and patron of Edward William Lane, supporting his travels and suggesting his researches in Egypt of his Arabic lexicon, published in 1863 and dedicated to him by Lane. The importance of his contributions as patron of science and learning weas recognised by his being elected to the Royal society, the Society of Antiquaries and the Royal Geographical Society.</p>
      <p>Honours: Baron 1816; KG 1853</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 09/04/1818</p>
      <p>Council: VP 1847-1848</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>Notes: DNB gives death date as 12 February 1865</p>
   </note>
</person>