<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA10433">
   <persName>
      <forename>Henry</forename>
      <surname>Blount</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1602 - 1682</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Tittenhanger, Hertfordshire, England, Europe (15 December 1602)</p>
      <p>Baptism: Ridge, Hertfordshire, England, Europe (22 December 1602)</p>
      <p>Death: Tittenhanger, Hertfordshire, England, Europe (9 October 1682)</p>
      <p>Burial: 11 October 1682</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Author</p>
      <p>Education: Free school at St Albans; Trinity College, Oxford (BA 1618); Gray's Inn (admitted 1620)</p>
      <p>Career: Travelled through Spain, France, and Italy (1629-1632); wrote 'A Voyage into the Levant' (1636) about his travels in the South Eastern Mediterranean; gentleman pensioner to Charles I (1639); took part in the battle of Edgehill for the Royalist cause (1642); appointed by Cromwell to serve on Hales commission for reformation of the criminal code (1652); appointed to the trade and navigation committee (1655); wrote foreword for Walter Rumsey's 'Organon salutis', the first English work on coffee (1657); Sheriff of Hertfordshire (1661)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1639</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 06/03/1661</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Proposed on 20 February 1661</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Hunter; ODNB; Aubrey; Evelyn's' diary</p>
      <p>Notes: While Blount was elected in 1661, he is not considered an Original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the second charter of the Society granted in 1663, or elected within the following two month period stipulated therein for the declaration of Fellows. The original Fellows are only those who were officially declared at the meetings of 20 May 1663 and 22 June 1663, so elections like Blount's that predated these meetings were no longer recognised. He was not elected after the second charter's admission period.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>landowner and author</term>
   </note>
</person>