<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA10434">
   <persName>
      <forename>Abraham</forename>
      <surname>Cowley</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1618 - 1667</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: London, England, Europe (1618)</p>
      <p>Death: Chertsey, Surrey, England, Europe (28 July 1667)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey, London, England, Europe (3 August 1667)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Poet</p>
      <p>Education: King's scholar at Westminster School; Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1639/40; MA 1642)</p>
      <p>Career: Started writing poetry as a child (1633); ejected from Cambridge and moved to Oxford (1643); started publishing variety of political satire (1643); followed Queen Henrietta Maria to France in Henry Jermyn's service (c1645); employed on missions and secret correspondence between royalist party members; returned to England (1654); arrested and released on bail after failed royalist uprising (1655); studied botany and medicine, and proceeded doctor of physic (1657)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 06/03/1661</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Contributed the ode 'To the Royal Society' for Thomas Sprat's 'History of the Royal Society' (1667)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>ODNB; DNB; Venn</p>
      <p>Notes: While Cowley was elected in 1661, he is not considered an Original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the second charter of the Society granted in 1663, or elected within the following two month period stipulated therein for the declaration of Fellows. The original Fellows are only those who were officially declared at the meetings of 20 May 1663 and 22 June 1663, so elections like Cowley's that predated these meetings were no longer recognised. He was not elected after the second charter's admission period.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>poet</term>
   </note>
</person>