<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA10435">
   <persName>
      <forename>Nicholas</forename>
      <surname>Crisp</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>1st baronet</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1599 - 1666</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: c1599</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (26 February 1666)</p>
      <p>Burial: Church of St Mildred, Bread Street, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Merchant; enslaver</p>
      <p>Career: Held substantial stocks in the East India Company and served multiple years on its governing body (1623-); was instrumental in developing a new monopoly trading company for produce and enslaved people between the Cape of Good Hope and Cape Blanco, the Guinea Company (1630s); appointed collectors of impositions in Western ports (1638); elected to short and long parliaments as MP for Winchelsea, though he was expelled in 1641 as a monopolist; invested in the parliamentary Sea Adventure to Ireland (1642); moved to Oxford during the Civil War (1643); fled to France (1646); selected member of the committee to meet Charles II at Breda (1660); was offered variety of grants and customs revenues after the Restoration</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1640</p>
      <p>Baronetcy 1665</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 18/03/1663</p>
      <p>Proposer: Daniel Colwall</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Proposed on 11 March 1663</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: ODNB</p>
      <p>Margaret Makepeace, ed., Trade on the Guinea Coast, 1657-1666: The Correspondence of the English East India Company (Madison, Wisc.: African Studies Program, 1991)</p>
      <p>Sainsbury, W N. 1860. 'America and West Indies: November 1637', in Calendar of State Papers Colonial, America and West Indies, vol. 1, 1574-1660 [https://www.british-history.ac.uk/cal-state-papers/colonial/america-west-indies/vol1/pp259-260; last accessed 10/03/2022]</p>
      <p>Notes: While Crisp was elected in 1661, he is not considered an Original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the second charter of the Society granted in 1663, or elected within the following two month period stipulated therein for the declaration of Fellows. The original Fellows are only those who were officially declared at the meetings of 20 May 1663 and 22 June 1663, so elections like Crisp's that predated these meetings were no longer recognised. He was not elected after the second charter's admission period.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>merchant and royalist</term>
   </note>
</person>