<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1108">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Gray</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date> - 1769</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Death: 17 July 1769</p>
      <p>Burial: Petersham, Richmond upon Thames, Greater London [formerly Surrey], England United Kingdom</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Mathematician; teacher; plantation and slave owner; merchant</p>
      <p>Research field: Mathematics; gunnery; botany; meteorology; astronomy</p>
      <p>Career: Taught mathematics at Marischal College (later part of University of Aberdeen); Navy Office (c 1731); collaborated with Andrew Reid on a four-part abridgment of the Royal Society’s Philosophical Transactions (1720-1732); went to Caratgena [Colombia] (c 1733), probably as a factor for the South Sea Company; whilst in Cartagena made scientific observations including astronomical and meteorological which he communicated to the Royal Society (c 1736-1739); worked with William Guthrie on a 12 vol. 'General History of the World, from the Creation to the Present Time' (1764-1767); Rector of Marischal College, University of Aberdeen (1765); owner of Gray's Inn Castle plantation, St George, Jamaica (1768-1769); left Univeristy of Aberdeen an endowment for two mathematics bursaries</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 16/03/1732</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; Wikipedia</p>
      <p>References: 'John Gray Rector of Marischal College', Legacies of British Slave-ownership database, http://wwwdepts-live.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/person/view/2146649623 [accessed 9th July 2020]</p>
      <p>Stearns, Raymond Phineas 'Colonial fellows of the Royal Society of London, 1661-1788' Notes Rec. R. Soc. Lond. 8 178–246, 1997, http://doi.org/10.1098/rsnr.1951.0017</p>
      <p>Finucane, A ''The Temptations of Trade: Britain, Spain, and the Struggle for Empire' (Pennsylvania), 2016</p>
   </note>
</person>