<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1226">
   <persName>
      <forename>James Hopwood</forename>
      <surname>Jeans</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1877 - 1946</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Birkdale, Southport, Lancashire, England (11 September 1877)</p>
      <p>Death: His home in Dorking, Surrey (16 September 1946)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics, astronomy</p>
      <p>Education;</p>
      <p>Merchant Taylors School 1890-1896; Trinity College Cambridge 1896-1900; Fellow of Trinity College Cambridge 1901; MA 1903;</p>
      <p>Career;</p>
      <p>1905-1909 Professor of Applied Mathematics at Princeton University USA; 1910-1912 Stokes lecturer in Applied Mathematics at Cambridge. President of the Royal Asronomical Society 1925-1927, President of the British Association for the Advancement of Science meeting at Aberdeen in 1934. Made Research Associate of Mt. Wilson Observatory in 1923. Held chair of astronomy of the Royal Institution from 1935 to his death in 1946. Awarded the Hopkins Prize of the Cambridge Philosophical Society 1921-1924, the gold medal of the Royal Astronomical Society in 1922, the Franklin Medal of the Franklin Institute in 1931, the Mukerjee Medal of the Indian Association for the Cultivation of Science in 1937, and the Calcutta Medal of the Indian Science Congress Association in 1938.</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1928; OM 1939</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 3/05/1906</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Royal Medal 1919</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1917</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1919-1929; VP 1938-1940</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society 1945-1948 vol 5 pp 573-589, plate, by E A Milne</p>
      <p>Notes: DSB gives a different birth place to that given above (taken from DNB): Ormskirk, Lancashire.</p>
      <p>References: R Singh and F Riess, 'The nobel laureate Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman FRS and his contacts with the British Scientific community in a social and political context' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 47-64</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Knight Physicist and Mathematician</term>
   </note>
</person>