<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1388">
   <persName>
      <forename>Francis</forename>
      <surname>Potter</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1594 -1678</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Mere vicarage, Wiltshire, England, Europe (29 May 1594)</p>
      <p>Death: April 1678</p>
      <p>Burial: Chancel in Kilmington, Wiltshire, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Practical mechanics</p>
      <p>Education: King's School, Worcester; Trinity College, Oxford (BA 1613; MA 1616; BD 1625)</p>
      <p>Career: Rector of Kilmington, Somerset (1626-1678); made sundials, quadrants and compasses; published 'An Interpretation of the Number 666' (1642)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 11/11/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for the Histories of Trades (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Presented papers on his inventions to the Royal Society (1663).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Foster; Aubrey; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Robert G Frank, Jr, 'John Aubrey, FRS, John Lydall, and Science at Commonwealth Oxford' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 193-217</p>
      <p>Notes: Potter was first elected on 18 March 1663, prior to the Society receiving its second Royal Charter, and was not officially re-elected FRS of the incorporated Royal Society until the date stated above (11 November 1663). Potter is therefore not considered an original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the 1663 charter or elected within the subsequent two months, the period allowed in the charter for the declaration of Fellows. Elections like Potter's that predated this were no longer recognised. The date of any subsequent re-election is given in this database as the official election date.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>clergyman, instrument maker, and experimentalist</term>
   </note>
</person>