<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1327">
   <persName>
      <forename>Henry</forename>
      <surname>Barkly</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1815 - 1898</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Highbury, London, Greater London, England, United Kingdom (24 February 1815)</p>
      <p>Death: Stapleton Park, Pontefract, Wakefield District, West Yorkshire, England United Kingdom (20 October 1898)</p>
      <p>Burial Place: Brompton Cemetery, London</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Politician; colonial administrator; plantation and slave owner</p>
      <p>Research field: Natural history; botany</p>
      <p>Education: Bruce Castle School, Tottenham, London</p>
      <p>Career: Worked for his father's company Davidson &amp; Barkly, a West India trading company (c 1832); family owned an estate in British Guiana [Guyana] which Barkly inherited (1836); went to Demerara [now part of Guyana]; travelled through British and Dutch Guiana; returned to England (1845); Conservative (Peelite) MP for Leominster (1845-1848); supporter of free trade; Governor of British Guiana (1849-1853); Governor of Jamaica (1853-1856); Governor of Victoria, Australia (1856-1863); Governor of Mauritius (1863-1870); Governor of Cape Colony and High Commisioner of South Africa (1871-1877); worked with the first elected Prime Minister of the Cape Colony, John Molteno; supported the local resistance against Carnarvon's attempt to force the region into a British ruled federation; Royal Commission on Colonial Defence (1879); made scientific collections and sent botanical specimens from places he visited; in retirement devoted himself to scientific pursuits and to committee work for the London Library.</p>
      <p>Memberships: FRGS (1870)</p>
      <p>Honours: KCB 1853; GCMG 1874</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 02/06/1864</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Wikipedia</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1905 vol 75 pp 23-25 signed by J D H</p>
      <p>References: Vanity Fair 09 July 1887</p>
      <p>A Cohen, 'Roland Trimen and the merope harem' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 205-218</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>'Henry Barkly', Legacies of British Slave-ownership database, http://wwwdepts-live.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/person/view/10612 [accessed 2nd July 2020].</p>
   </note>
</person>