<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1438">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles</forename>
      <surname>Scarburgh</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1615 - 1694</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: London, England, Europe (c. December 1615)</p>
      <p>Baptism: St Martin in the Fields, England, Europe (29 December 1615)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (26 February 1694)</p>
      <p>Burial: Cranford, Middlesex, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research field: anatomy</p>
      <p>Education: St Paul's School, London; Caius College, Cambridge (BA 1637; MA 1640); studied mathematics with Seth Ward (FRS 1663); Merton College, Oxford (DMed 1646); Incorporated at Cambridge (1660)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Caius (1642-1649); elected Anatomical Reader by the Barber Surgeons' Company (1649); assisted William Harvey in his work on the generation of animals (c.1645); Lumleian lecturer at College of Physicians (1656); Harveian orator (1662); Physician for the Tower of London (1663-?1685); Physician to Charles II, James II, William III and the Royal Household; MP for Camelford (1685-1687); Governor of Christ's Hospital (1673); amassed a fine library of mathematical books; published a guide to human dissection 'Syllabus musculorum' (1676); MP for Camelford (1685)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1669</p>
      <p>Memberships: FRCP (1650)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Date of ejection/withdrawal: 29 October 1666 (for non-payment of arrears)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; Foster; McDonnell; Henning; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London and Oxford' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 157-168</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'The Origins and Foundation of the Royal Society of London' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 1-37</p>
      <p>A C S, 'Notes on the Foundation and History of the Royal Society' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 32-36</p>
      <p>L Jardine, 'The 2003 Wilkins Lecture: Dr Wilkins's boy wonders' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 107-129</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Scarburgh's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 16 January 1661.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician and natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>