<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA1421">
   <persName>
      <forename>Archibald</forename>
      <surname>Barr</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1855 - 1931</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Glenfield House, Paisley (18 November 1855)</p>
      <p>Death: At his home Westerton of Mugdock, near Milngavie, near Glasgow (05 August 1931)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Engineering</p>
      <p>Education: Paisley Grammar School; apprentice at local engineering firm A F Craig, manufacturers of spinning and weaving machinery. Glasgow University for his BA (1878) DSc, LLD (Glasg, Birm)</p>
      <p>Career: Professor of Civil and Mechanical Engineering at Leeds, where he met William Stroud, Professor of Physics (1884-1889); with Stroud he designed a short-base range-finder for infantry use, which not taken up bu encouraged the Admiralty to invite them to submit a further design which was adopted by the Royal Navy in 1892. Set up company 'Barr and Stroud's Patents' to market their creations. Regius Professor of Civil Engineering at Glasgow, (1889-1913), succeeding his old mentor, Thomson. Raised money to build Glasgow's James Watt Engineering Building (1901). Influenced the orgainising of the new Faculty of Science in 1893 and campaigned successfully for a lectureship in Electrical Engineering, established n 1898. Barr and Stroud expanded into a large purpose-built factory at Anniesland to test ad assemble range-finders, and manufacure binoculars, gun-sights and submarine periscopes by British and European navies. Barr resigned his university chair at Galsgow in 1913, becoming emeritus professor, though he remained chirman of Barr and Stroud until his death.</p>
      <p>Helped form the Scottish Aeronautical Club in 1909, becoming its president, and was a promoter of Scotland's first aviation meeting at Lanark in 1919. Governor of the Royal Scottish National Institution for the care of those with learning difficulties.</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 3/05/1923</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society 1932-1935 vol l pp 31-36, plate, signed by J W F</p>
   </note>
</person>