<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2292">
   <persName>
      <forename>John Scott</forename>
      <surname>Haldane</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1860 - 1936</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Edinburgh, Scotland (03 May 1860)</p>
      <p>Death: Oxford (15 March 1936)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physiology</p>
      <p>Education: Career: John Scott Haldane was one of the greatest and most colourful of British scientists, acknowledged as the leading physiologist of the era at a time when physiology and much of medical science was coming into its own. The most successful serial self-experimenter in the history of science, Haldane crawled through the carnage of underground explosions, locked himself in sealed chambers, breathed in lethal cocktails of gases, sampled his own blood, burned and healed his own flesh, and experimented on his own children, in an obsessional push to understand the nature of human respiration. What is expired air? How can you make coalmines safer? What does carbon monoxide do to people? These are just some of the vital questions to which Haldane provided the answers, saving thousands of lives in the process. He also designed the first space-suit and invented the gas-mask, among many other innovations and contributions we still benefit from today.</p>
      <p>Honours: CH 1928</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 3/06/1897</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Royal Medal 1916; Copley Medal 1934</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society 1936-1938 vol 2 pp 115-139, plate, by C G Douglas</p>
      <p>References: W van der Kloot, 'April 1915: Five Future Nobel Prize-Winners Inaugurate Weapons Of Mass Destruction And The Academic-Industrial-Military Complex' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 149-160</p>
      <p>Notes: According to the DNB entry, he died at midnight 14-15 Mar 1936.</p>
   </note>
</person>