<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2442">
   <persName>
      <forename>Seth</forename>
      <surname>Ward</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1617 - 1689</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Buntingford, Hertfordshire, England, Europe (c. 1617)</p>
      <p>Baptism: St Mary's Church, Aspenden, Hertfordshire, England, Europe (5 April 1617)</p>
      <p>Death: Knightsbridge, London, England, Europe (6 January 1689)</p>
      <p>Burial: Salisbury Cathedral, Wiltshire, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Astronomy</p>
      <p>Education: Grammar School at Buntingford, Hertfordshire; Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge (BA 1637; MA 1640); Studied William Oughtred's mathematics with Charles Scarburgh (FRS 1663); Wadham College, Oxford (DD 1654)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Sidney (1640-1644) ejected; ordained priest (1641); mathematical lecturer at Cambridge University (1643); imprisoned in St John's College, Cambridge as a Royalist (1644); Published 'Certain Disquisitions and Considerations Representing to the Conscience the Unlawfulness of the ... Solemn League and Covenant' (c.1643); Tutor to the sons of Ralph Freeman at Aspenden Hall (c1644-1649); Chaplain to Lord Wenman (1649); Savilian Professor of Astronomy, Oxford (1649-1661); Produced study of the nature of comets (1653); Collaborative work with John Wilkins (FRS 1663) on 'Vindiciae academiarum' (1654); Published 'Astronomia geometrica' (1656); Chaplain to Dr. Ralph Brownrig (1656); President of Trinity College, Oxford (1659-1660); Rector of Garsington, Oxford (1660) ejected; Canon and Precentor of Exeter (1660-1662); Rector of St Lawrence Jewry, London (1661-1662); Rector of Uplowman, Devon (1661); Rector of St Breock, Cornwall (1662); Dean of Exeter (1662); Bishop of Exeter (1662-1667); Bishop of Salisbury (1667-1689); Chancellor of the Order of the Garter (1671-1689); benefactor of the Royal Society and Sidney Sussex College;</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: 1664, 1666-1678</p>
      <p>VP 1674-?</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster; Aubrey; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'The Origins and Foundation of the Royal Society of London' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 1-37</p>
      <p>C A Ronan, 'Laurence Rooke (1622-1662)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 113-118</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London and Oxford' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 157-168</p>
      <p>Albert Van Helden, 'Christopher Wren's De Corpore Saturni' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 213-229</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Ward's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 18 December 1661.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>astronomer and bishop of Exeter and Salisbury</term>
   </note>
</person>