<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2654">
   <persName>
      <forename>Constantine John</forename>
      <surname>Phipps</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>Baron Mulgrave</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1744 - 1792</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: May 1744</p>
      <p>Death: 10 October 1792 at Liege</p>
      
      <p>Education: Career: 1760, he entered the navy. Served at the reduction of Martinique and St Lucia; on 17 March 1762 promoted to Lieutenant and took part in the reduction of Havana. In 1768 he was elected Member of Parliament for Lincoln, and from 1777 to 1784 Member of Parliament for Huntingdon, as well as one of the lords of the Admiralty. In 1773 he commanded the 'Racehorse', which with the 'Carcass' was fitted out to attempt to discover a northern route to India, although the expedition only sailed to the north of Spitzbergen because the sea was absolutely blocked with ice. In 1784 he became Member of Parliament for Newark on Trent. In the same year he was appointed joint paymaster general of the forces, a Commissioner for the Affairs of India, and one of the lords of 'Trades and Plantations'. He was a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries, and instrumental in founding the 'Society for the Improvement of Naval Architecture'.</p>
      <p>Honours: Baron 1790</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 12/12/1771</p>
      <p>Council: VP 1778-1792</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>Journal Book meeting of 12 December 1771 records that ' The Honourable Constantine Phipps, Son to Lord Mulgrave of the Kingdom of Ireland, was proposed as a Member by Joseph Banks Esquire and being balloted for immediately according to the proviso in the Statute was chosen a Member of the Society, and having further paid his admission fee, and the sum of seventy six guineas in lieu of contributions, he also signed the obligation in the Charter Book and was admitted Fellow'.</p>
      <p>References: Averil M Lysaght, 'Joseph Banks at Skara Brae and Stennis, Orkney, 1772' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 221-234</p>
      <p>L B Glyn, 'Israel Lyons: a short but starry career. The life of an eighteenth-century Jewish botanist and astronomer' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 275-305</p>
   </note>
</person>