<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2630">
   <persName>
      <forename>Archibald Campbell</forename>
      <surname>Campbell</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>1st Baron Blythswood </roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1835 - 1908</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Florence, Italy (22 February 1835)</p>
      <p>Death: Blythswood House, Renfrewshire (08 July 1908)</p>
      <p>Buried at at Inchinann, near Glasgow (11 July 1908)</p>
      
      <p>Education: Educated privately for an Army career, LL.D Glasgow</p>
      <p>Career: Joined the 79th Highlanders at age 16, transferring to the Scots Guards, before retiring from the Army on the death of his father (1868). ADC to Queen Victoria, (1894); President of the Highland and Agricultural Society (1896-1897); Lord lieutenant and Convenor of Renfrewshire (1904-1908).</p>
      <p>Notable amateur scientist, went with his wife to Thebes to observe the Transit of Venus (1874), taking with him a small transit instrument, a 6-inch telescope and a 12-inch telescope, recording the time of first contact, and also observed a white halo, proving an atmosphere around Venus. From 1892-1905 the Blythswood Laboratory was used to experiment into many areas at the borders of physics, including the use of cathode rays, X-rays, spectroscopy and radioactivity. He designed a speed indicator, which was fitted to shiops int he Royal Navy, and carried out studies into the efficiency of aerial propellers some years before the Wright Brothers first powered flight in 1903.</p>
      <p>Member of Parliament for Renfrewshire (1873-1874), and for West Renfrewshire (1885-1892). Lord Lietenant for Renfrewshire (1904-1908). REceived an Honorary Doctorate of Law from the University of Glasgow (1888), and made a Freeman of the City.</p>
      <p>President, Philosophical Society of Glasgow (1898-1901) and gained it the right to use the prefix 'Royal'</p>
      <p>Freemason, member of Lodge St Mary, Coltness, No 31, Wishaw, Lanarkshire</p>
      <p>Honours: Bt 1880; 1st Baron Blythswood of Renfrewshire, 24 August 1892</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 2/05/1907</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>Library and Museum of Freemasonry, 'Freemasons and the Royal Society: Alphabetical List of Fellows who were Freemasons' 2010, page 15-16</p>
   </note>
</person>