<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2840">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Elford</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1749 - 1837</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Bickham House, near Plymouth (01 August 1749)</p>
      <p>Death: Totnes Priory, Devon (30 November 1837)</p>
      <p>Burial: Totnes parish church, Devon</p>
      
      <p>Career: Recorder, Plymouth; one of the founding fathers of the Plymouth Bank; MP, Plymouth (1796-1806); MP, Rye (1807-1808); joined South Devon Militia in 1786 and rose to rank of Lieutenant Colonel, South Devon Militia when he accompanied his regiment to Ireland 1798-99 during the Irish Rebellion. Was an artist of some renown, exhibited regularly at the Royal Academy after 1774-1837. Friend of two local artists - Joshua Reynolds and James Northcote, who painted both him and Lady Elford with her son. Friend of William Pitt the Younger. Chairman of the Plymouth Anti Slavery Committee, which first used the engraving by Deedle of Bristol of the Liverpool Slave Ship Brookes, showing 454Africans for their 1788 Anti Slavery pamphlet, the first use of the image following Clarkson's survey and later taken up and used by the London Committee. . Recorder for Plymouth 1797-1833; presented Freedom of the Ciy of Plymouth to Admiral Nelson in 1800; Recorder for Totnes 1832-1834. Was involved with the Plymouth and Dartmoor Railway linking Princetown to the quays at Plymouth's Sutton Pool.</p>
      <p>In 1825 the Plymouth Bank failed, he had to sell his estate at Bickham, moved to live with his daughter adn son-in-law at The Priory, Totnes, where he died in 1837.</p>
      <p>Honours: Bt 1800</p>
      <p>Memberships: FLS (1813)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 29/04/1790</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
   </note>
</person>