<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2861">
   <persName>
      <forename>Oliver</forename>
      <surname>Heaviside</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1850 - 1925</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 55 King Street, Camden Town, London, England (18 May 1850)</p>
      <p>Death: Hornefield, Lower Warberry, Torquay, Devon (03 February 1925)</p>
      <p>Burial: Paignton cemetery, Devon</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics, electrical engineering</p>
      <p>Career: Had Scarlet Fever when young, leaving him partially deaf. Still became a good telegraph operator. Worked for Great Northern Telephone Company, Newcastle; suffered from deafness and was forced to retire (1874); studied electricity, especially Maxwell's Equations for three years, and telephony. Adapted comlex numbers for use in electric circuits, as well as defeloped techniques for applying Laplace Transforms for the solution of differential equations. Co-invented vector analysis calculus. Formulated the 'operator' method for use in linear differential equations, replacing the differential operator (d/dx) by a new variable (p) transforming a differential equation into an algebraic eqiation, which is much easier to solve. This simple solution to an algebraic equation can then be transformed back into a differential equation solution by using 'tables of conversion' which are already worked out. In 1902 he prdicted a 'layer' of the earth's atmosphere could refract radio waves (now called the ionosphere). His prediction exlained how Marconi had famously managed to send the first ever radio signal across the Atlantic Ocean in 1901. This lionized layer in our atmosphere was called the 'Heaviside Layer' for many years. Its existence and predicted abililty to refract certain high frequencies was finally proved in 1924.</p>
      <p>Awarded the first Faraday Medal, a bronze medal established in 1922 to commemmorate the 50th Anniversary of the first Ordinary Meeting of the Society of Telegraph Engineers (now the Institution of Engineering and Technology).</p>
      <p>Honours: Hon MIEE</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 4/06/1891</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc Series A 1926 vol 110 pp xiv-xv signed by A R</p>
   </note>
</person>