<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA2912">
   <persName>
      <forename>Samuel</forename>
      <surname>Ferris</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1757 - 1831</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Warminster, Wiltshire, England (25 March 1757)</p>
      <p>Baptism: St Denys, Warminster, Wiltshire</p>
      <p>Death: Exmouth, Devon 18 September 1831</p>
      <p>Burial: Littleham, Exmouth</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Physician</p>
      <p>Education: MD (1784, Edinburgh); LCP (1785)</p>
      <p>Career: Apprenticed to Samuel Martin of the Upholder's Company (1 May 1771); made a freeman of the Upholder's Company (1 June 1778); apprenticed to a Surgeon-apothecary, Timothy Healey, surgeon of Berkhampstead, Hertfordshire (1779-1780); came to London and attended lectures of William Hunter; completed medical studies in Edinburgh; President, Royal Medical Society of Edinburgh (1784); became Licentiate of College of Physicians (1785); practised in Missenden possibly with Benjamin Bates; then returned to London; left London due to worsening asthma and practised medicine in Beaconsfield, Buckinghamshire; became a magistrate of the county of Buckinghamshire</p>
      <p>Memberships: FSA (December 1790)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 30/03/1797</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1830-1831 No 7 p 84</p>
      <p>Notes: Index to BR gives '[Bates]' after his forename, indicating that this was perhaps a middle name; however it does not appear in BR itself, the obituary in Proceedings, or in Munk. The name Samuel Bates Ferris was used in his Times death notice ( (23 September 1831) but not in his baptismal record or on his gravestone.</p>
      <p>Mentioned in poem describing Exmouth Ball held at New Rooms Beacon Hill, 10 July 1818 - "There was grave Dr Ferris (to learning no stranger)"</p>
      <p>Information on Date of Birth and burial place,career, addresses, use of name Bates, mention in poem and relationships from David Ferriss</p>
   </note>
</person>