<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3049">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Paterson</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1755 - 1810</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Montrose, Scotland, United Kingdom (17 August 1755)</p>
      <p>Death: On board the ship HMS 'Dromedary' (21 June 1810)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Soldier; colonial administrator</p>
      <p>Research field: Botany</p>
      <p>Educations: Trained in horticulture at Syon in London</p>
      <p>Career: Entered the army; went on expeditions in South Africa (1777-1779); gazetted to the 98th Regiment and sent to India; chosen to command a company of the New South Wales Corps to protect convict settlement at Botany Bay, Australia (went there 1791); served in command on Norfolk Island (November 1791-March 1793), whilst there he collected botanical, geological and insect specimens and sent them to Joseph Banks PRS; Lieutenant Governor of New South Wales (1794, 1806-1808); in 1795, Paterson gave an order that resulted in the massacre of a number of men, women and children of the Bediagal tribe in retaliation for the killing of two settlers; led an expedition to the Hunter Region (1801); in 1804 led a settlement expedition to Port Dalrymple in the north of Van Diemen's Land and became Commandent of the colony (1804-1808) where he again collected specimens for Banks; administered government at Sydney as acting Lieutenant Governor after deposition of William Bligh FRS (1809); Paterson River and Mountain, New South Wales, and Paterson Creek, Tasmania, named after him, died on the passage home to England, off Cape Horn on HMS 'Dromedary'</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 10/05/1798</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Wikipedia</p>
      <p>References: Connor, John 'The Australian frontier wars, 1788-1838' , (Sydney) 2005</p>
      <p>Smith, N. 'William Paterson: amateur colonial botanist, 1755–1810’, in Australian Garden History, 17 (1), 2005, pp. 8–10.</p>
   </note>
</person>