<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3050">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Houstoun</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c 1695 - 1733</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Houston, Scotland (c 1695)</p>
      <p>Death: Jamaica, West Indies (14 August 1733)</p>
      <p>Buried: Kingston, Jamaica (14 August 1733)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Botany; medicine</p>
      <p>Education: Began a degree in medicine at St Andrew's University (1719) which he never completed; carried out experiments on animal respiration; MD (1729, Leyden)</p>
      <p>Career: While in the Netherlands became interested in the use of newly discovered plants for medicinal purposes; employed as a ship's surgeon for the South Sea Company; travelled to Central America and to the West Indies, collected specimens many of which were unknown in Europe at the time. Visited Jamaica, Cuba, Venezuela and Vera Cruz; sent home seeds to Philip Miller, head gardener of Chelsea; Cinchoneaceae Houstonia was named after him. Returned to London in 1731, where he was introduced to Sir Hans Sloane by Miller. Commissioned by Sloane to undertake another journey to collect specimens, this time financed by the Trustees for the Province of Georgia in America, who wanted Houston to stock the garden they had planned for Savannah, Georgia. Travelled first to Madeira islands to gather grape plants, then to the Caribbean. Expedition never completed as he died from the heat of Jamaica in 1733, shortly after arriving there. Houstoun's specimens, manuscripts and drawings were eventually returned and can be found in the Natural History Museum.</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 18/01/1733</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>Authority: Altname from DNB</p>
      <p>Notes: No portrait of him known to exist</p>
   </note>
</person>