<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3178">
   <persName>
      <forename>George</forename>
      <surname>Hibbert</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1757 - 1837</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Manchester, Lancashire, England, United Kingdom (1757)</p>
      <p>Death: Munden House, near Watford, Hertfordshire (08 October 1837)</p>
      <p>Burial: Aldenham, Hertfordshire</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Merchant; politician; plantation and slave owner</p>
      <p>Research field: Natural history; botany</p>
      <p>Education: Reverend Booth’s academy at Woolten Hall</p>
      <p>Career: Cotton manufacturer in Manchester; junior partner in G. W. S. Hibbert &amp; Co. a West India merchant house, London (from 1780), ultimately becoming head of the firm (1790s); Chairman of the West India Dock Company; Alderman of the City of London for the Bridge Within ward (1798-1803); Whig MP for Seaford (1806-1812); instrumental in the establishment of the Jamaican Botanical Gardens at St. Thomas-in-the-East (1806); Proslavery lobbyist; Agent for Jamaica (1812-1831) in which capacity he acted as a political lobbyist in Westminster for the planter-controlled Jamaican House of Assembly; Chairman of the West India Committee; founding President, London Institution (1805); edited Caxton's translation of Ovid, Six Books of Metamorphoses (1819); edited the anonymous 'Narrative of a Journey from Santiago de Chile to Buenos Ayres' (1824); a founder of the National Institution for the Preservation of Life from Shipwreck, later RNLI (1824); book and art collector</p>
      <p>Memberships: Freemason's (1796-1806); Brooks's (1810); FSA (1812); Roxburgh Club (1816); FLS</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 30/05/1811</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; UCL LBS; https://www.georgehibbert.com/index.html [accessed 23rd June 2020];</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1838 No 35 pp 93-94</p>
      <p>References: Hibbert Steele, Nick, ''The Jamaican Diaries of Robert Hibbert 1772-1780: Detailing a merchant family's involvement in and defence of the colonial slave trade based economy' (Australia) 2020</p>
      <p>'George Hibbert', Legacies of British Slave-ownership database, http://wwwdepts-live.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/person/view/16791 [accessed 23rd June 2020]</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>merchant</term>
   </note>
</person>