<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3352">
   <persName>
      <forename>George</forename>
      <surname>Ent</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1604 - 1689</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Sandwich, Kent, England, Europe (06 November 1604)</p>
      <p>Death: St Giles-in-the-Fields, London, England, Europe (13 October 1689)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Lawrence Jewry, Guildhall, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Medicine</p>
      <p>Education: Educated in Wallachia [or Walcheren] and at Rotterdam under James Beckman; admitted to Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge (admitted 1624; BA 1627, MA 1631); Padua (MD 28 April 1636); incorporated at Oxford (9 November 1638)</p>
      <p>Career: Published 'Apologia pro circulatione sanguinis' (1641); Goulstonian lecturer (1642); Published 'De generatione' (1651), edited from Harvey manuscript; Censor at RCP (1645-1649; 1651; 1653-1657); Registrar (1655-1670); Elect (1657-1689); Consiliarus (1667-1669); Anatomical studies appear in Walter Charleton's 'Onomasticon zoicum' (1677); Published 'Antidiatrive, sive, Animadversiones in Malachiae Turstoni, M.D.' (1679)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1665</p>
      <p>Memberships: Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians (President 1670-1675, 1682, 1684)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 22/04/1663</p>
      <p>Council: 1662-63; 1666-69</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Anatomical Committee (1664)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn</p>
      <p>References: A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'A Roman correspondence: George Ent and Cassiano dal Pozzo, 1637-55' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 5-23</p>
      <p>Letters from Thomas Stanley of Clumberlow Green, Herts., mentioning Sir George Ent in NR December 1958. Vol. 5, no.12 pp.544-5</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London and Oxford' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 157-168</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Ent's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously mentioned as a member on 8 May 1661.</p>
      <p>Appears to have withdrawn from the Society in 1677, according to index to BR, although Hunter says that he resigned in 1675.</p>
      <p>Venn gives father's name as John, DNB as Josias.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician</term>
   </note>
</person>