<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3322">
   <persName>
      <forename>George</forename>
      <surname>Villiers</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>2nd Duke of Buckingham</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1628 - 1687</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Wallingford House, Westminster, London, England, Europe (30 January 1628)</p>
      <p>Death: Kirkby Moorside, Yorkshire, England, Europe (16 April 1687)</p>
      <p>Burial: St George's chapel in Westminster Abbey, London, England, Europe (7 June 1687)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Politician; statesman; writer</p>
      <p>Research field: chemistry; alchemy</p>
      <p>Education: Christ Church, Oxford; Trinity College, Cambridge, MA (fil nob 1642)</p>
      <p>Career: Joined Royalist Army (1642); proscribed and sentenced to death (1648); fled to Holland (1648); with Charles II in Scotland (1650); fought at Worcester (1651); returned to Holland (1651); returned to England (1657); imprisoned in the Tower of London (1658-1659); set up the Vauxhall glassworks factory at Lambeth, the productions of which were praised by John Evelyn FRS (1660); gentleman of the bedchamber (1661); Lord Lieutenant of the West Riding of Yorkshire (1661-1667, recommisioned later in 1667); Privy Councillor (1662-1667); one of the 'Cabal', the cabinet signatories to a treaty with France (1667-1672); played a leading role in the impeachement of former Lord Chancellor Clarendon (1667) shareholder in the Royal African Company; Committee for Foreign affairs (1668); purchased position as Master of the Horse for £20,000 (1668-1674); fought an infamous duel with the Earl of Shrewsbury whose wife was Buckingham's mistress, Shrewsbury later died of his wounds (1668); High Steward of Oxford (1669); Ambassador to Paris (1670-1672); Chancellor of Cambridge University (1671-1674); attached to the embassy to The Hague (June 1672); Keeper of Enfield Chace (1672-1675); Lieutenant General of the Forces (1673); Lord of the Admiralty (1673-1674); dismissed from all offices (1674); imprisoned in the Tower of London for seeking the dissolution of parliament (1677) released after a month thanks to the influence of Nell Gwyn, the King's mistress and other courtiers; lived in retirement in Yorkshire; author of restoration plays, notably 'The Chances' (1667) adpated from John Fletcher's comedy and the popular satire 'The Rehersal' (1671), he also wrote poetry and satirical prose and was famed as a wit</p>
      <p>Honours: KG 1649</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Date of ejection/withdrawal: 22/07/1685 (due to non-payment of arrears)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; Foster; GEC; Davies; Wikipedia; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: F. T. Melton, ‘A rake refinanced: the fortune of George Villiers, 2nd Duke of Buckingham, 1628–85’, Huntington Library Quarterly, 51 (1988), 297–318</p>
      <p>Mark Govier, 'The Royal Society, Slavery and the Island of Jamaica: 1660-1700' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 203-217</p>
      <p>Davies, K. G. 'The Royal African Company' (London) 1999</p>
      <p>Pettigrew, William A. 'Freedom's debt : the Royal African Company and the politics of the Atlantic slave trade, 1672-1752.' (North Carolina) 2013</p>
      <p>AssocMaterial: Brian Fairfax's life of Buckingham, BL, Harleian MS 6862</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Villier's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 5 June 1661.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>politician and wit</term>
   </note>
</person>