<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3355">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Beale</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1608 - c 1683</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Yardley, Herefordshire, England, Europe (c1608)</p>
      <p>Baptism: Yarkhill, Herefordshire, England, Europe (17 April 1608)</p>
      <p>Death: c1683</p>
      <p>Burial: Yeovil, Somerset, England, Europe (16 April 1683)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research field: agriculture; horticulture; botany; forestry</p>
      <p>Education: Worcester Cathedral school (1618-1622); Eton College (1622-); King's College, Cambridge (BA 1632/3; MA 1636)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of King's (1632-40); travelled for some years while tutor and guardian to cousin Robert Pye and George Speke; Rector of Sock, Somerset (1638-1683); published 'A Treatise on Fruit Trees' (1653); member of the Herefordshire committee for ejecting scandalous ministers (1654); instrumental in establishment of Herefordshire Association of Ministers (1657-1658); published 'Observations on some parts of Bacon's natural history, as it concerns fruit trees, fruits and flowers' (1658); Rector of Yeovil, Somerset (1660-1683); Chaplain to Charles II (1665-1683); published 'Nurseries, Orchards, Profitable Gardens and Vineyards Encouraged' (1677)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 16/08/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments: Committee for Agriculture [Georgical] (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for the Histories of Trades (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Collecting all the Phenomena of Nature hitherto observed (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Correspondence (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Frequent correspondent on agricultural matters.</p>
      <p>Appointed Curator of Experiments regarding cider production (1663).</p>
      <p>Beale's paper 'Aphorisms concerning cider' (1662) prompted the formation of committee to consider the production elsewhere in England.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: P H Goodchild, ''No Phantasticall Utopia, but a Reall Place'. John Evelyn, John Beale and Backbury Hill, Herefordshire', in Garden History, 1991, vol. 19(2), pp.105-127</p>
      <p>Notes: DNB gives date of birth as 1603, Hunter gives 1608; Venn gives c1613.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Declared an honorary member from 07 January 1663 (Birch p172: "they had declared him, from that time, an honorary member of the society, and would receive him, upon his desire, a fellow of it."); re-elected 16 August 1663 [JB]. After the grant of the Second Royal Charter to the Royal Society in 1663 all existing Fellows had to be declared within two months or re-elected. As Beale was re-elected outside the two month window stipulated in the Charter he is not considered an Original Fellow of the Society. The date of election after the grant of the 1663 Charter is considered the official election date and is the one given in this database.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>clergyman and writer</term>
   </note>
</person>