<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3509">
   <persName>
      <forename>Francis Legatt</forename>
      <surname>Chantrey</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1781 - 1841</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Jordanthorpe, in the parish of Norton, Derbyshire, England (07 April 1781)</p>
      <p>Death: 25 November 1841</p>
      <p>Burial: Jordanthorpe, in the parish of Norton, Derbyshire, in a tomb contructed by himself</p>
      
      <p>Education: Royal Academy (after 1802)</p>
      <p>Career: Apprenticed to a carver and guilder, Robert Ramsey (1754-1828) Sheffield; drew portraits and landscape; apprenticeship cancelled (1802) and went to try his fortune, first in Dublin and Edinburgh and finally in London; obtained employment as as Assistant Wood carver, and at soame time devoted himself to portrait painting, bust sculpture, and modelling in clay. First commission was a marble bust for Sheffield parish church (1805); he exhibited pictures at the Royal Academy from 1804, but from 1807 onwards devoted hiself mainly to sculpture and Joseph Nollekens (1737-18230, the neoc,lassical sculpton, showed recognition of his merits. His first imaginative work in sculpture was the model of the head fo Satan, which was exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1808. Afterwards he executed for Greenwich Hospital four huge busts of Admirals Duncan, Howe, Vincent and Nelson, and led to his reputation spreading so quickly that his next bust, that of John Horne Tooke (1736-1812) the radical politician, procured him commisions to the Value of £2,000. visited Italy 91819). He died suddenly of heart failure; bequeathed money to the Royal Academy for the purchase of native works of art</p>
      <p>Freemason, initiated 5 April 1813, Lodge of Union No 218, subsequently No 166, London</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1835</p>
      <p>Memberships: ARA (1816); RA (1818)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 30/04/1818</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>References: W P Griffith and P J T Morris, 'Charles Hatchett FRS (1765 - 1847), chemist and discoverer of niobium' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 299 - 316</p>
      <p>The Library and Museum of Freemasonry, ;Freemasons and the Royal Society; Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were Freemasons' (2010), page 19</p>
   </note>
</person>