<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3559">
   <persName>
      <forename>David James</forename>
      <surname>Hamilton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1849 - 1909</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 06 March 1849</p>
      <p>Death: 19 February 1909</p>
      
      <p>Education: BM</p>
      <p>Career: Professor of Pathology, University of Aberdeen (by 1903)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 7/05/1908</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc Series B 1909 vol 81 pp i-v signed by J T C</p>
      <p>Notes: In the Printed List of Candidates 1906-1914 there are two Supplementary Certificates. The first with the following citation: Amongst later contributions bearing on the study of causation and prevention of certain communicable diseases, the following may be mentioned: - 'On Braxy' (Trans Highland and Agric Soc, 1902); 'The Relationship of Human Tuberculosis to that of Bovines' (ibid, 1903). The proposers are: C Niven; F R Japp; J W H Trail; C S Sherrington; D J Cunningham; [John Burdon Sanderson].</p>
      <p>The second has the following citation: In the year 1901, the Board of Agriculture appointed Prof Hamilton chairman of a Department Committee to investigate the disease known popularly as Louping-ill (chorea paralytica ovis) and Braxy (morbus subitarius ovis). The Report of the Committee was issused in June of the past year, 1906 and contains a fine exposition by Prof Hamilton of the Pathology of these and allied diseaes, showing them to be due to a class of pathogenic anaerobes previously almost unknown. A method of prevention has also been discovered by him which in practice has reduced the tremendous mortality from these diseases to a level commensurate with profitable sheep farming. The proposers are: J W H Trail; F R Japp; William Turner; C S Sherrington; J T Cash; J G McKendrick; James Dewar</p>
   </note>
</person>