<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3561">
   <persName>
      <forename>Hamilton</forename>
      <surname>Hartridge</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1886 - 1976</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 07 May 1886</p>
      <p>Death: 13 January 1976</p>
      
      <p>Education: Harrow School (1900-1905); King's College Cambridge (1905-1908). MA; MD; ScD</p>
      <p>Career: Problem solver at The Airship Construction Station (1915-1919); Fellow (1912-1926) and Senior Demonstrator of Physiology, and Lecturer on the Physiology of the Senses, King's College Cambridge (1919-1928) where he made his discoveries that bats use sound not vision to navigate; notable for his ingenious and fruitful experimentation - in mirror galvanometry, the resonance theory of hearing, spectroscopy (he invented the reversion spectroscope while working on the oxygen and carbon monoxide combining power of haemoglobin with F W Roughton), colorimetry, and microscopy, though the projection microscope, as well as an automatic rheotome, were designed to meet teaching and reserch problems during his period at Barts. Graduated in medicine from St George's Hospital (1914). Professor of Physiology, St. Bartholomew's Hospital Medical School (1927-1947); to this period belong his textbook revisions and rewritings, including the 7th edition of Bainbridge and Menzies's 'Principles of Physiology ' in 1929 and the special senses section of later editions of Starling's 'Principles of Human Physiology'. He had unusuakl powers of exposition and delivered popular lectures on the special senses to audiences at the British Association, in the Christmas Lectures at the Royal Institution, and as Gresham Professor of physics at Gresham College. 'Director, Vision Research Unit in Institute of Opthalmology (1947-1951); Emeritus Professor of Physiology in the University of London.</p>
      <p/>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 6/05/1926</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1977 vol 23 pp 193-211, plate, by W A H Rushton</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Physiologist and Inventor</term>
   </note>
</person>