<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3503">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Brouncker</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>2nd Viscount Brouncker</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1620 - 1684</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Newcastle Lyons, co. Dublin, Ireland, Europe (1620)</p>
      <p>Death: St James' Street, Westminster, London, England, Europe (5 April 1684)</p>
      <p>Burial: Chapel of St Katharine's Hospital, London, England, Europe (14 April 1684)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: mathematics</p>
      <p>Education: Oxford (MD 1646)</p>
      <p>Career: Published a translation of Descartes' 'Musicae compendium' (1653); MP for Westbury (1660); Chancellor to Catherine, Queen Consort (1662-1684); commissioned and designed a yacht for Charles II (1662); Commissioner of the Admirality (1664-1679); Assistant comptroller to the treasurer of the Admirality (1666-1679; 1681-1684); President of Gresham College (1664-1667); Lord of the Admiralty (1680-1683); Master of St Katharine's Hospital, London (1681-1684)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Founder Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 28/11/1660</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1663-1677</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee to consider of Mr Buckland's proposition to plant potatoes through all the parts of England (1662)</p>
      <p>Committee to examine [William] Ball's accounts from Midsumer until St Andrews Day (1663)</p>
      <p>Mechanical Committee (1664-65)</p>
      <p>Committee to consider a way of determining the measure of a degree on the earth (1669)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; GEC; Aubrey; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Jacqueline A Stedall, 'Catching Proteus: the collaborations of Wallis and Brouncker. I. Squaring the circle' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 293-316</p>
      <p>Jacqueline A Stedall, 'Catching Proteus: the collaborations of Wallis and Brouncker. II. Number problems' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 317-331</p>
      <p>D J Bryden, 'Magnetic Inclinatory Needles: Approved by the Royal Society?' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 17-31</p>
      <p>J F Scott and Sir Harold Hartley, 'William, Viscount Brouncker, PRS (1620-1684)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 147-157, plate</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>N J W Thrower, 'Samuel Pepys FRS (1633-1733) and The Royal Society' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 3-13</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>J Gribbin, 'The Fellowship', 2005, pp140-141</p>
      <p>Notes: Election date given as 22/04/1663 in index to BR, the same date given in R, where Brouncker appears as President and a member of Council named by Second Royal Charter. He was present at the foundation meeting on 28 Nov 1660, which has been entered as his date of election. Biographical info from GEC; Henning says he was son of 1st Viscount and his wife Anne, daughter of Sir John Dauntsey of Bishop's Lavington; married Katherine, daughter of Thomas Moore of Hawkchurch, Devon and had three sons and two daughters</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>mathematician</term>
   </note>
</person>