<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3675">
   <persName>
      <forename>Eugenius</forename>
      <surname>Bulgaris</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1716 - 1806</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Corfu (1716)</p>
      <p>Death: Monastery of Alexandr Nevskii, St Petersburg (1806)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Clergyman, Orthodox</p>
      <p>Research field: Aristotelian philosophy, mathematics, Newtonian physics and astronomy, classical literature, religious matters, politics</p>
      <p>Education: Ionian islands of Corfu and Zante; possibly Arta and Ioannina, Greece (before 1736); may have studied theology, philosophy and physical sciences and learned the Italian, French, Latin and Hebrew languages at the University of Padua, Italy (before 1742)</p>
      <p>Career: Ordained; taught in Greece (in Ioannina, Kozane and in Mount Athos); taught in Constantinople (Istanbul); tried to introduce a new philosophical and educational model, combining the teachings of the Christian Orthodox Church with recent developments in philosophy and natural philosophy; left the Greek speaking regions in order to settle abroad and leave behind his teaching career (the reasons for his departure were related to his desire to contact various foreign scholars and publish his works ) (1763); resident at Leipzig (1764-1771); at St. Petersburg, Russia, as a protege of Catherine II the Great (by June 1771); his relationship with the Empress promoted his career and enhanced relations between the Greek-speaking regions and the Orthodox Russian Empire; after the signing of the treatise of Kuchuk-Kainardji, Archbishop of Kherson and Slavjansk (Cherson and Slavenck), Southern Ukraine (1775-1779); translated a great number of books into Greek, some of which were used as 'textbooks' at the Greek schools.</p>
      <p>Memberships: Russian Academy of Sciences (honorary) (December 1776)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 3/04/1788</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>S.K. Batalden, 'Catherine II's Greek prelate: Eugenius Voulgaris in Russia, 1771 - 1806', (New York, 1982)</p>
      <p>Ch. Tzogas, 'Eugenius Voulgaris', Gregorios o Palamas, (1970), pp. 146 - 153</p>
      <p>B.N. Tatakes (ed.), 'Skouphos, Voulgaris, Theotokes', (Athens, 1953)</p>
      <p>E.D. Kolokotsas, 'Eugenius Voulgaris and his work', Athena, 30 (1919), pp. 177 - 208</p>
      <p>A.N. Goudas, 'Parallel Lives' (Athens, 1874), Volume II</p>
      <p>A.P. Vretos, 'Biographie de l'Archevêque Eugène Bulgari: rédigée sur des documentes authentiques', (Athens, 1860)</p>
      <p>P. Kalligas, 'The Life of Eugenius Voulgaris', Pandora, (1850/51), pp. 494 - 505 and 517 - 520</p>
      <p>G. Ainian, 'A collection of unpublished and some other published works of Eugenius Voulgaris', Volume I.</p>
      <p>G. Petrou, 'Eugenius Voulgaris (1716 - 1806) and the Royal Society of London', Neusis: Journal for the History and Philosophy of Science and Technology, 10 (Autumn 2001), pp. 181 - 198 [This article is written in Greek but an English translation by G. Petrou is held by the library of Royal Society of London.]</p>
   </note>
</person>