<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA3757">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles Piazzi</forename>
      <surname>Smyth</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1819 - 1900</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Naples, Italy (03 January 1819)</p>
      <p>Death: Clova, near Ripon (21 February 1900)</p>
      <p>Burial: Sharow churchyard, Ripon, Yorkshire</p>
      
      <p>Education: Research Field: Astronomy</p>
      <p>Career: Assistant in the Royal Observatory, Cape of Good Hope (1835-1845), cooperated with Sir Thomas Maclear in the extension of Lacaille's arc; produced oldest known calotypes of people and scenes in Southern Africa with the help of John Herschel; Astronomer Royal for Scotland and Regius Professor of Astronomy, University of Edinburgh (1845-1888), introduced time service for Edinburgh with time ball on the Nelson monument and later a time gun fired from Edinburgh Castle (1861); resigned Fellowship on 7 February 1874 on the Society denying him the reading of his paper on the interpretation of the design of the Great Pyramid, published "The Great Pyramid and the Royal Society"; Became obsessed with the metre - he believed the decimal system was foreign, French, and atheist. Claimed if the pyramids were measured very accurately, it was possible to tell that they were based on the British yard, given by God and built by the Hebrews. Led expeditions to Egypt to meausre them accurately to prove this. Use of the yard in the Pyramids proved there were common values between the founders of Egypt and the Anglo-Saxons, and so helped to justify the Conquest of Egypt in 1881-2.</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 11/06/1857</p>
      <p>Withdrew (1874)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
   </note>
</person>