<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA4534">
   <persName>
      <forename>Ralph</forename>
      <surname>Cudworth</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1617 - 1688</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Aller, Somerset, England, Europe (1617)</p>
      <p>Baptism: Aller, Somerset, England, Europe (13 July 1617)</p>
      <p>Death: Christ's College, Cambridge, England, Europe (26 June 1688)</p>
      <p>Burial: Christ's College chapel, Cambridge, England, Europe (27 June 1688)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Mechanical philosophy</p>
      <p>Education: Pupil of his step-father, Dr Stoughton; Emmanuel College, Cambridge (BA 1635; MA 1639; BD 1646; DD 1651)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Emmanuel (1639); published 'A Discourse Concerning the True Notion of the Lord's Supper' and 'The Union of Christ and the Church a Shadow' (1642); Master of Clare Hall, Cambridge (1646-1654); Regius Professor of Hebrew, University of Cambridge (1645-death); Incumbent of North Cadbury, Somerset (1650); Master of Christ's College, Cambridge (1654); Adviser to the scholars preparing the Polyglot Bible (1654-1657); Rector of Toft, Cambridgeshire (1656); Vicar of Great Wilbraham, Cambridgeshire (1656); Rector of Ashwell, Hertfordshire (1662); Prebendary of Gloucester (1678); published 'The true intellectual system of the universe, wherein all the reason and philosophy of atheism is confuted, and its impossibility demonstrated' (1678); one of the Cambridge Platonists</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 17/09/1662</p>
      <p>Proposer: John Wilkins (4 June 1662)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: DNB; DSB; Venn; Hunter; ODNB</p>
      <p>Notes: While Blount was elected in 1661, he is not considered an Original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the second charter of the Society granted in 1663, or elected within the following two month period stipulated therein for the declaration of Fellows. The original Fellows are only those who were officially declared at the meetings of 20 May 1663 and 22 June 1663, so elections like Blount's that predated these meetings were no longer recognised. He was not elected after the second charter's admission period.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>philosopher and theologian</term>
   </note>
</person>