<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA4968">
   <persName>
      <forename>William John</forename>
      <surname>Bankes</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1786 - 1855</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 11 December 1786</p>
      <p>Death: Venice, Venezia province, Veneto, Italy, Europe (15 April 1855)</p>
      <p>Burial: Wimborne Minster, Dorset England, United Kingdom</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Politician; archaeologist; explorer; collector</p>
      <p>Research field: Archaeology; Egyptology; antiquities</p>
      <p>Education: Westminster School (1795); Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1808, MA 1811)</p>
      <p>Career: Tory MP (for Truro 1810, for Cambridge University 1822- 1826, for Marlborough 1829-1832, for Dorset 1832-1835); lived a bohemian life with gypsies in Spain and Portugal (1812); travelled widely in the Middle East and Africa, especially Egypt, Nubia and the Nile collecting antiquities, accompanied by artists who documented ancient monuments and inscriptions (1812-1819); published account of his explorations as 'Travels in the East'; engaged Louis Linant de Bellefonds to search for the ancient city of Meroe (accomplished 1821-1822); contributed to deciphering the Rosetta Stone by suggesting that the texts on the stone might all say the same thing in different languages, and correctly supposed that a recurring cartouche represented a royal name; forced to flee England following his second arrest for having gay sex, which was illegal in the UK at the time and would likely have resulted in his execution (1841); living in France and later Italy continued to collect ancient and modern art and artefacts which he sent home to his house Kingston Lacy in Dorset; died in exile in Venice (1855)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 28/03/1822</p>
      <p>Ejected: 1842 following arrest for homosexual activity with a guardsman on a bench in St James's Park, London</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Patricia Usick, 'Adventures in Egypt and Nubia: The Travels of William John Bankes' (1786-1855); Wikipedia</p>
      <p>References: https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2020/jun/25/rosetta-stone-to-be-added-to-british-museum-lgbtq-tours</p>
      <p>Bankes of Kingston Lacy archive (ref: D/BKL), including the travel papers and correspondence of William John Bankes, c1800-1818, held at the Dorset History Centre</p>
      <p>Dorothy U. Seyler. 'The Obelisk and the Englishman: The Pioneering Discoveries of Egyptologist William Bankes' (New York), 2015.</p>
      <p>Notes: Ejected from the Royal Society 1842 following his arrest (Council Minutes, 10 March 1842).</p>
      <p>Election certificate ragged: small sections missing</p>
   </note>
</person>