<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5059">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Graunt</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1620 - 1674</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: The sign of the Seven Stars, Birchin Lane, London, England, Europe (24 April 1620)</p>
      <p>Death: Bolt Court, London, England, Europe (18 April 1674)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Dunstan-in-the-West, Fleet Street, London, England, Europe (22 April 1674)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Shopkeeper</p>
      <p>Research Field: Statistics, demography</p>
      <p>Education: Apprenticeship with haberdasher of small wares (1636)</p>
      <p>Career: Admitted freeman of Drapers' Company (1641); Author of 'Natural and Political Observations on the Bills of Mortality' (1662); Manager of the New River Company (1666); Member of the Common Council of the City of London; involved in actuarial work</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: On Council (1664-1666)</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for the Histories of Trades (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Worked and associated closely with William Petty (FRS 1660), in particular regarding statistical accounts.</p>
      <p>Brought in reports on the growth of carps and salmons (1663).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Aubrey; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: T. Sprat, History of the Royal Society 1667 (p 67)</p>
      <p>Peter Brimblecombe, 'Interest in Air Pollution Among Early Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 123-129</p>
      <p>D V Glass, 'John Graunt and his Natural and Political Observations' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 63-100</p>
      <p>Sir Irvine Masson and A J Youngson, 'Sir William Petty, FRS (1623-1687)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 79-90</p>
      <p>M Greenwood, 'The First Life Table' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 70-72</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Graunt's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 26 February 1662.</p>
      <p>Hunter has admission date 5 March 1662, which Journal Book states is the day of subscription.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>statistician</term>
   </note>
</person>