<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5184">
   <persName>
      <forename>George</forename>
      <surname>Cockburn</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1772 - 1853</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 22 April 1772</p>
      <p>Death: 19 August 1853</p>
      
      <p>Career: Entered the Royal Navy age 14, rose rapidly. By 1812 promoted Rear Admiral in charge of the Royal Navy in Spanisch waters but was then ordered to America. Played a large part in the War of 1812 as 2nd in command to Admiral Sir John Borlase Wqarren, until the end of March 1814, and then to Warren's successor, Admiral Sir Alecander Cochrane for eth eremainder of the war. his most important action was the capture and burning of Washington, 24 August 1814, as advisor to Major General Robert Ross. After Waterll, on his return to Europe, he commanded HMS 'Northumberland', conveying Napoleon to St Helena, where he remained for some months as Governor and the Emperor's gaoler. Later he was Commander in Chief, North america Station, and Admiral of the Fleet; also held the honorary title of Rear Admiral of the United Kingdom, and Major General of Marines, 1847-1853.</p>
      <p>Member of Parliament for Portsmouth (1818-1820); Weobley (1820-1828); Plynouth (1828-1832); and Ripon (1841-1847).</p>
      <p>Freemason, made 25 November 1811, in Somerset House Lodge No 2, subsequently Royal Somerset House and Inverness Lodge No 4 London</p>
      <p>Honours: KCB 1815; GCB 1818</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 21/12/1820</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>References: Library and Museum of Freemasonry, 'Freemasons and the Royal Society; Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were Freemasons' London, 2010, page 21-22</p>
   </note>
</person>