<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5336">
   <persName>
      <forename>Meghnad N</forename>
      <surname>Saha</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>?1893 - 1956</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Scoratali, Dacca district, India (now Bangladesh) (06 October 1893 or 06 October 1894)</p>
      <p>Death: New Delhi, India (16 February 1956)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Theoretical physics</p>
      <p>Education: DSc</p>
      <p>Career: Professor of Physics, University of Allahabad</p>
      <p>Wanted to set up a modern research laboratory in Kolkata (formerly Calcutta), but was not very successful. Moved to Allahabad University but returned in 1938. Became interested in nuclear physics; established Institute of Nuclear Physics which was later named after him as Saha Institute of Nuclear Pysics (1947). Took the first step to include nuclear physics in the higher studies of science. In order to develop and popularise science, he even went into politics and was elected Member of Parliament in 1951.</p>
      <p>Professor Meghnad Desai,</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 12/05/1927</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1959 vol 5 pp 217-236, plate, by D S Kothari</p>
      <p>R Singh and F Riess, 'The nobel laureate Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman FRS and his contacts with the British Scientific community in a social and political context' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 47-64</p>
      <p>R Singh 'India's Physics and Chemistry Nobel Prize nominators and nominees in colonial and international context' NR 2007 Vol 61 pp 333-346</p>
      <p>Notes: DSB gives death date as 06 October 1894</p>
   </note>
</person>