<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5680">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Freind</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1675 - 1728</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Croughton, near Brackley, Northamptonshire, England (1675)</p>
      <p>Death: London (26 July 1728)</p>
      <p>Burial: Hitcham, near Maidenhead, Buckinghamshire</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Physician, chemist</p>
      <p>Research Field: Chemistry, medicine</p>
      <p>Education: Westminster School; Christ Church, Oxford. BA (1698), MA (1701), BMed (1703), DMed (by diploma 1707)</p>
      <p>Career: First involvement with Royal Societycame with publication of an account of his dissection of a hydrocephalic child in 'Philosophical Transactions' (1699). Early renown based on his 'Emmenologia', a treatise on menstruation (1703). Friend of Voltaire. Lecturer on Chemistry at the Ashmolean Museum, Oxford (1704); Physician to the English forces in Spain accompnying the Earl of Peterborough (1705-1707); travelled to Italy, where he met Giorgio Baglivi (FRS 1698) and Giovanni Maria Lancisi (FRS 1706); Physician to the Duke of Ormonde in his campaign in Flanders (1712); practised in London (1713-death); MP for Launceston (1722-1724, 1725-1727); a Jacobite, he became involved in the plot of his friend, Francis Atterbury, and was imprisoned in the Tower of London on a charge of high treason (1723) but was released at the insistence of Richard Mead (FRS 1703) who is said to have refused to treat Sir Robert Walpole until he agreed to free Friend; Physician to George II when Prince of Wales (1724) and to Queen Caroline (1727); Governor of the Bridewell and Bethlehem Hospitals; died of a violent fever</p>
      <p>Memberships: FRCP (1716)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/03/1712</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; Thomas; Sedgwick</p>
      <p>Notes: Proposed by John Keill</p>
      <p>Freind's 'Opera Omnia Medica' contains a comprehensive background to Freind's life and times</p>
      <p>References: J S Rowlinson, 'John Freind: physician, chemist, Jacobite, and friend of Voltaire's' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 109-127</p>
   </note>
</person>