<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5616">
   <persName>
      <forename>Walter</forename>
      <surname>Pope</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1627 - 1714</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Fawsley, Northamptonshire, England, Europe (c.1627)</p>
      <p>Baptism: All Saints', Oxford, England, Europe (30 November 1628)</p>
      <p>Death: Bunhill Fields, London, England, Europe (c. June 1714)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Giles's, Cripplegate, London, England, Europe (25 June 1714)</p>
      
      <p>Education: Westminster School; Trinity College, Cambridge (admitted 1645); Wadham College, Oxford (BA 1649; MA 1651; MD 1661); Incorporated at Cambridge (1657)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Wadham (1651-1662); Sub-warden of Wadham (1658); travelled to France (1658-1659); Dean of Wadham (1660-1661); Professor of Astronomy at Gresham College, London (1661-1687); travelled abroad and spent two years in Italy (c.1664-1666); Registrar for the Diocese of Chester (1668-1714)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: On council in 1666-1667.</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Mechanical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Involved in observations of Jupiter's satellites with Christopher Wren (FRS 1663) (1661).</p>
      <p>Whilst in Italy, Pope was one of the Society's correspondents on matters of natural philosophy. Two papers on solar observations were published in the 'Philosophical Transactions'.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; Foster; ODNB</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Pope's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 22 May 1661.</p>
      <p>Approximate year of birth taken from Hunter, who also states that he was last in 1698 list.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>astronomer and writer</term>
   </note>
</person>