<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5638">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Molyneux</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1656 - 1698</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: His father's house in New Row, Dublin, Ireland (17 April 1656)</p>
      <p>Death: Dublin, Ireland (11 October 1698)</p>
      <p>Burial: Tomb of Sir William Ussher, north aisle of St Audoen's Church, Dublin, Ireland</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Astronomy, physics</p>
      <p>Education: Trinity College, Dublin BA, LLD (1693); Middle Temple (admitted 1675)</p>
      <p>Career: Published 'Six Metaphysical Meditations' (London, 1680), a translation of Descartes 'Meditationes' (1641); Joint Chief Engineer and Surveyor-General of the King's Buildings and Works in Ireland (1684-1688); founder of Dublin Philosophical Society officially constituted as The Dublin Society for the Improving of Naturall Knowledge, Mathematicks, and Mechanicks (1684); travelled in Holland, France and Germany (1685); designed a sundial-mounted telescope (1685) and published an account of it in Sciothericum Telescopium (Dublin, 1686); published Dioptrica Nova (London, 1692), the first optical treatise to be published in English; lived in Chester (1689-90); MP for City of Dublin and then Dublin University in the Irish Parliament (1690, 1692); originated the 'Molyneux Problem' proposed to John Locke (1693); published 'The Case of Ireland's Being Bound by Acts of Parliament in England Stated' (Dublin, 1698)</p>
      <p>Memberships: Dublin Philosophical Society (1683, Founder member)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 3/02/1686</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Irish Innovators</p>
      <p>References: K Theodore Hoppen, 'The Royal Society and Ireland: William Molyneux, FRS (1656-1698)' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 125-135, plate</p>
      <p>K Theodore Hoppen, 'The Royal Society and Ireland. II' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 78-99</p>
      <p>P Fontes da Costa, 'The Culture of Curiosity at The Royal Society in the first half of the eighteenth century', NR 2002 vo l56 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>W Hayes, 'Physics as well as poetry. Physicists of Ireland, edited by M McCartney and A Whitaker' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 245-246</p>
   </note>
</person>