<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5602">
   <persName>
      <forename>Edward Victor</forename>
      <surname>Appleton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1892 - 1965</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Bradford, Yorkshire, England ( 06 September 1892)</p>
      <p>Death: Edinburgh (21 April 1965)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Radio physics</p>
      <p>Education: Hanson Grammar School Bradford; BA in Natural Science at St Hon's College, Cambridge (1913-14); Won Wiltshire Prize (1913); Hutchinson Research Studentship (1914); MA; DSc</p>
      <p>Career: In the West Riding Regiment, transferring to the Royal Engineers (1914-1918); Returned to Cambridge, research on radio waves, and after 1919 to scientific problems in atmospheric physics. Assistant Demonstrator in Experimental Physics at the Cavendish Laboratory (1920: Sub Rector at Trinity College Cambridged (19220; Professor of Physics at London University (1924-1936; Secretary, Department of Scientific and Industrial Research (1939). Discoverer of the 'Appleton Layer' which plays an essential part in making radio communication possible between distant stations. Wheatstone Professor of Physics in the University of London; ex-Fellow of St John's College, Cambridge</p>
      <p>Vice Chancellor, University of Edinburgh (1949); President, British Association for the Advancement of Science (1953)</p>
      <p>Medals: Medal of Merit, highest civilian decoration from USA (1947); Officer of the French Legions of Honour (1947); awarded the Norwegian Cross of Freedom for his war work. Appointed by Pope to the Pontifical Academy fo Science (1948).</p>
      <p>Honours: KCB 1941; GBE 1946</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 12/05/1927</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Hughes Medal 1933; Royal Medal 1950; Nobel Prize (Physics) 1947 for his contribution to wards expoloring the ionosphere.</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1937</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB</p>
      <p>AssocMaterial: CSAC 82/6/81. Papers deposited in Edinburgh University Library</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1966 vol 12 pp 1-21, plate, by J A Ratcliffe</p>
      <p>References: Maurice V Wilkes, 'Sir Edward Appleton and Early Ionosphere Research' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 281-290, plate</p>
      <p>'Freemasons and the Royal Society: Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were Freemasons' 2010. Library and Museum of Freemasonry page 4</p>
   </note>
</person>