<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5673">
   <persName>
      <forename>Thomas</forename>
      <surname>Horsfield</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1773 - 1859</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: A farm near Bethlehem, Pennsylvania (12 May 1773)</p>
      <p>Death: 24 July 1859</p>
      <p>Buried: Moravian cemetery in Chelsea</p>
      
      <p>Physician and Naturalist</p>
      <p>Education: Schools in Bethlehem and Naszareth, Pennsylvania; University of Pennsylvania, where studied medicine. MD thesis illustrates his interest in botany, a study of the effects of the physiologically active poison ivy 'Rhus toxicodendron L.' and other members of the Anacardiaceae.Travelled to Java for first time in 1800, and captivated by its flora and fauna. Worked for East India Company in Java, including on the toxim from latex producing tree 'Antiaris toxocaria'. In 1803 attempted to analyse lava from eruption of Gunung Gunter. After 1811 when Java seized by the British, came into contact with Sir Stamford Raffles and in 1812 visited and prepared a map of Bankga Island for Raffles. In 1818 visited Sumatra with Sir Stamford and Lady Raffles. In 1820 appointed to East India Comapny's Museum in Leadenhall Street, London on Raffles recommendation. Worked with botanists J.J. Bennett (1801-1876) and Robert Brown (1773-1858) to produce his 'Plantae Javanicae' rariores (1838-1852). Remained at the India Museum until his death.</p>
      <p>MD</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 10/01/1828</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DAB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1859-1860 vol 10 pp xix-xxi</p>
      <p>Notes: 'Saml Carlisle' is Samuel Goodenough, Bishop of Carlisle</p>
      <p>New DNB (2004) gives place of birth as 42 West Market Street, Bethlehem, Pennsylvania</p>
   </note>
</person>