<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5785">
   <persName>
      <forename>Ellis</forename>
      <surname>Leighton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date> - 1685</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Death: St Andrew, Holborn, London, England, Europe (9 January 1685)</p>
      <p>Burial: Church of Horsted Keynes, Sussex, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Government official; soldier; barrister;</p>
      <p>Research field: Mechanics; engineering</p>
      <p>Education: Cambridge, LLD Lit. Reg. (1665); Middle Temple (admitted 1667)</p>
      <p>Career: Colonel in Royalist Army; arrested and imprisoned in Windsor Castle (1647); went into exile after execution of Charles I; returned to England and arrested again (1649); appointed Secretary for English affairs in Scotland by Charles II during his brief initial term as King of Scotland (1650-1651); fled to Rotterdam with the Duke of Buckingham after Charles II was defeated by Cromwell at the Battle of Worcester (1651); entered the employ of the Duke of York on the continent (1656); knighted in Brussels (1659); acted as a go-between for Royalists in exile and contacts in England; became Secretary of the Royal Adventurers into Africa after the Restoration, (1660); share in the secretaryship of the Prize Office (1664); KC, Admiralty Court (1665); counsel to the Navy Board (1667); called to the Bar (1670); sent to the French court to negotiate an alliance (1670); Secretary to John, Lord Berkeley, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland (1670-1672); KC, Ireland (1672); Recorder of Dublin (1672); accompanied Berkeley on his embassy to France (1675); conceived a project for a 'cart with iron axel-trees' which was viewed by John Evelyn FRS (1678); a warrant was issued for his arrest for taking bribes and committed to the Tower of London (1675-1676); returned to England from France to surrender himself (1677); rearrested (1678); released, probably on grounds of poor health; lived in Paris (1682); final move to London and death (1685)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1659</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 9/12/1663</p>
      <p>Proposers: Sir Robert Moray</p>
      <p>Date of ejection/withdrawal: 1677</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Mechanical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Proposed on 2 December 1663 and admitted 16 December 1663.</p>
      <p>Expelled for failing to pay his subscription.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; Hunter</p>
      <p>References: John Evelyn, Diary, ed. 1850–2, vol ii p35</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'The Royal Society and its Fellows, 1660-1700...' (1982)</p>
      <p>Mark Govier, 'The Royal Society, Slavery and the Island of Jamaica: 1660-1700' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 203-217.</p>
      <p>Notes: DNB gives Christian name as Elisha, but signed Charter Book as Ellis and also called Ellis in Shaw's "Knights".</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>courtier and government official</term>
   </note>
</person>