<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5891">
   <persName>
      <forename>John James</forename>
      <surname>Audubon</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1785 - 1851</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Les Cayes, Santo Domingo (26 April 1785)</p>
      <p>Death: 27 January 1851</p>
      <p>Buried in Trinity Cemetery at 155th Street and Broadway, New York City, USA</p>
      
      <p>Born in Haiti in 1785 to a sea captain and his mistress, he grew up in revolutionary France and came to America to avoid Napoleon's draft. By way of Philadelphia and Kentucky, Audubon settled in Louisiana in 1821. There he gave lessons to plantation belles and spent long days shooting birds and then painting them. He propped up dead birds with wires and meticulously recorded their colouring and conformation. He was self taught as an artist and naturalist. For his masterpiece 'Birds of America' Audubon portrayed his avian subjects in dramatic action and settings, as with the barred owl about to pounce on a curiously unsuspecting squirrel. In every case, Audubon observed the natural setings and created a scientific record still of value today.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>When he travelled to Europe in 1826 seeking a publisher, he was hailed as 'The American Woodsman'. The Royal Society in London elected him a Fellow, and he lectured on American wildlife to, among others, a young Charles Darwin, His success allowed him to purchase an estate in the Hudson River Valley in New York.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>His last project was the mammals of North America, left unfinished at his death in 1851.</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 18/03/1830</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DAB</p>
      <p>'Freemasons and the Royal Society: Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were also Masons' Library and Museum of Freemqasonry, 2010, page 5</p>
   </note>
</person>