<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA5919">
   <persName>
      <forename>Theodore</forename>
      <surname>Haak</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1605 - 1690</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Neuhausen, near Worms, Germany, Europe (25 July 1605)</p>
      <p>Death: Bartlett Buildings, Fetter Lane, London, England, Europe (5 May 1690)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Andrew's, Holborn, London, England, Europe (8 May 1690)</p>
      
      <p>Education: Gloucester Hall, Oxford (matriculated c.1629); University of Leiden (matriculated 1638)</p>
      <p>Career: Ordained deacon; procured benevolence money from several English dioceses for Germans during the Wars of Religion; translated 'Dutch annotations' on the Bible for the Westminster Assembly of Divines; acted as intelligence agent and translator for the Council of State</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Proposer: Viscount Brouncker (FRS 1661)</p>
      <p>Council 1678-1679</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for Correspondence (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Auditing the Treasurer's Accounts (1673)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Translated an Italian work on dyeing at the Society's request (1662).</p>
      <p>Researched and wrote about oysters (1662).</p>
      <p>Heavily involved in the Society's foreign correspondence until 1685.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; Shaw LD; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Marie Boas Hall, 'Frederick Slare, FRS (1648-1727)' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 23-41</p>
      <p>Christopher Hill, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London or Oxford?' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 144-156</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'The Origins and Foundation of the Royal Society of London' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 1-37</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'The Accompt of William Balle from 28 November 1660 to 11 September 1663' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 174-183</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>A C S, 'Notes on the Foundation and History of the Royal Society' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 32-36</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 1. 1731-1847' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 307-332</p>
      <p>J Heyman, 'The birth of the modern architect. On a grander scale: the outstanding career of Sir Christopher Wren, by L Jardine' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 243-244</p>
      <p>N Malcolm, 'An unpublished letter from Henry Oldenburg to Johann Heinrich Rahn' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 249 - 266</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Haak's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 4 December 1661.</p>
      <p>Possibly proposed by Dr Wilkins, 13 November 1661, as 'Mr Hawks' (JB). The burial register at St Andrew's gives burial date as 08 May 1690 (see book on Haak by P Barnet).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>translator and natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>