<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6090">
   <persName>
      <forename>John William</forename>
      <surname>Strutt</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>3rd Baron Rayleigh</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1842 - 1919</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Langford Grove, Maldon, Essex, England (12 November 1842)</p>
      <p>Death: Terling Place, Witham, Essex (30 June 1919)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics</p>
      <p>Education: Eton; at home; private school at Wimbledon; Harrow School (1857); private school with the Reverend George Townsend Waner who took pupils privately in Torquay (1857); Trinity College, Cambridge (1861). BA (1865, Senior Wrangler and 1st Smith's Prizeman)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge (1866-1871); managed his estate of Terling Place, before succeeding to the barony (1873) and passing the job to his brother (1876); Cavendish Professor of Physics, Cambridge succeeding James Clerk Maxwell (1879-1884); Professor of Natural Philosophy, Royal Institution, London (1887-1905); had a private laboratory at Terling Place, where his work on producing diffraction gratings by photgrpahic reduction of hand drawn rulings led to the production of the earliest known so-called Fresnel zone plates - an entry in his notebook in 1871 predates by four years a paper by Soret, previously thought to be the first report of this two dimensional lens, later to find application in Polaroid cameras and used for focusing synchroton radiation. Privy Councillor (1905); discovered argon</p>
      <p>President of a Government Committee on Explosives; Scientific Advisor to Trinity House; Lord Lieutenant of Essex (1892-1901); Chancellor of Cambridge University</p>
      <p>Honours: OM (1902)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 12/06/1873</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Rumford Medal 1914; Royal Medal 1882; Copley Medal 1899; Nobel Prize (Physics) 1904 for discovery of argon</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1902</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1885-1896; PRS 1905-1908</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc Series A 1920-1921 vol 98 pp i-l, plate, by Arthur Schuster</p>
      <p>References: Mary Nixon, 'The Raymond and Beverly Sackler Archive Resource at the Royal Society: A Work in Progress' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 183-186, plate</p>
      <p>A A Mills and R Hall, 'The Production of a Plane Surface. As Illustrated by Specula From Some Early Newtonian Telescopes' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>John R Levene, 'Nevil Maskelyne, FRS, and the Discovery of Night Myopia' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 100-108, plate</p>
      <p>Sir Harold Hartley, 'The Ramsay Centenary' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 71-80</p>
      <p>Derek J Price, 'The Cavendish Laboratory Archives' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 139-147</p>
      <p>Lord Rayleigh, OH: Nobel Laureate in Science [exhibition catalogue] Harrow School Old Speech Room Gallery 13th October -22nd November 1992</p>
      <p>R Singh and F Riess, 'The nobel laureate Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman FRS and his contacts with the British Scientific community in a social and political context' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 47-64</p>
      <p>' The Acoustical Experiments of Lord Rayleigh. Exhibition Guide and biographical sketch by Professor Edward A Davis' Whipple Museum of the History of Science. 2011 Part of the 'Local Heroes' initiative of the Royal Society as part of their 350th anniversary.</p>
   </note>
</person>