<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6100">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Woodward</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1665 - 1728</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Derbyshire, England (01 May 1665)</p>
      <p>Death: At his apartments in Gresham College, London (25 April 1728)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Geology; Botany, Antiquarianism</p>
      <p>Education: Apprenticed to a linen draper; pupil of Peter Barwick FCP; MD (Lambeth 1695); incorporated at Cambridge</p>
      <p>Career: Gresham Professor of Physic (1692-death); possibly the inspiration for the caricature of the 'virtuoso' in Judith Drake's 'An essay in defence of the female sex' (1696); Expelled from the Royal Society for insulting Sir Hans Sloane with the words "speak sense or English and we shall understand you. If you understood anatomy you would know better" (Council Minutes, 29 March 1710) whilst Sloane was reading a paper before the Society. Woodward refused to make the required apology (Council Minutes 24 May 1710) and was expelled from the Council and the Society; he brought an action against the Royal Society Council (Council Minutes, 17 June 1710) but lost. He was involved in a sword fight with Richard Mead (FRS 1703) in Gresham College (1719); died of a decline; benefactor to the University of Cambridge, his collection of fossils formed the nucleus of the Woodwardian Museum</p>
      <p>Memberships: FCP (1702/3)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 30/11/1693</p>
      <p>Proposers: Robert Hooke</p>
      <p>Council: 1696, 1698</p>
      <p>Expelled from the Society's Council 1710</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Ward; Hunter; Venn</p>
      <p>References: Hannah Smith, 'English 'feminist' writings and Judith Drake's 'An essay in defence of the female sex' (1696)' in Historical Journal 2001, 44, 3, pp 727-748</p>
      <p>Joseph M Levine, 'Dr Woodward's shield: history, science and satire in Augustan England', Berkeley, 1977</p>
      <p>W H G Armytage, 'The Royal Society and the Apothecaries' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 22-37</p>
      <p>Jean Jacquot, 'Sir Hans Sloane and French Men of Science' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 85-98</p>
      <p>G R de Beer, 'Sir Hans Sloane, FRS, 1660-1753' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 81-84</p>
      <p>P Fontes da Costa, 'The Culture of Curiosity at The Royal Society in the first half of the eighteenth century', NR 2002 vo l56 pp 147-166</p>
   </note>
</person>