<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6148">
   <persName>
      <forename>Abraham</forename>
      <surname>Hill</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1633 - 1721</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 18 April 1633</p>
      <p>Baptism: St Dionis Backchurch, London, England, United Kingdom, Europe (16 June 1635)</p>
      <p>Death: 5 February 1721</p>
      <p>Burial: The chancel of Sutton-at-Hone Church, Kent, England, United Kingdom, Europe (14 February 1721)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Merchant; administrator</p>
      <p>Research field: Antiquities; languages; natural philosophy</p>
      <p>Education: Taught himself several languages and natural and moral philosophy</p>
      <p>Career: Entered his father's merchant business and inherited a legacy on death of his parents (1660); purchased the lease of St John's or 'Sutton Manor' estate, Kent (1660) and introduced apples and pears to the estate, for making cider and perry; colleague and sometime scientific confidant of Robert Hooke FRS; Assistant to the Royal African Company (1683-1685, 1688-1690); Deputy Governor (1691-1692); Commissioner for Trade, Board of Trade (1696-1702); Comptroller to John Tillotson, Archbishop of Canterbury (1691-1694); collected coins and books; retired to his estate of St. John's in Sutton-at-Hone, Kent (1689)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Founder Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 28/11/1660 (Present at foundation meeting)</p>
      <p>Council: 1663-1666, 1672-1721; Treasurer 1663-1665, 1679-1700; VP 1715-1716</p>
      <p>Secretary 1673-1675</p>
      <p>Committees/Panels: Committee for the quicksilver experiment (1661); Committee to examine Birchensa's synopsis of music (1662); to review Mersenne on the tenacity of bodies (1662); for the making of statutes (1663); to consider experiments for the entertainment of Charles II (1664), for ordinary meetings (1676, 1680); for agriculture, histories of trade, correspondence, experiments on diving (1664, 1679); for the Repository (1666); for the inventory of the Society’s possessions (1676); for the prism experiment in the Newton-Linus dispute (1676); for publication (1676, 1682); for the purchase of property (1678-81, 1703); for the history of Barbados (1681); for verifying entries in the Society’s journal and other books (1682); for the publication of the History of Fishes (1685-86) (14); for Estruscan inscriptions (1700); of Visitors of the Royal Observatory at Greenwich (1710); for the Newton-Leibnitz controversy (1712); to draw up queries to be sent to Moscow (1713).</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Involved in acquiring the Arundel Library (1666 and 1678) and property around Chelsea College (1682) for the Society, and in investing Society funds in stock of the Royal African Company and East India Company (1682). Assisted Nehemiah Grew in describing the coins in the Royal Society Repository for his catalogue of the collection. In his capacity as Secretary acted as Royal Society nominee on patent for inventions (1665) including clocks for finding longitude at sea invented by Christian Huygens and Alexander Bruce, which the Society hoped to profit from. With Sir Hans Sloane, administered Sir Godfrey Copley's bequest of £100 in trust to the Royal Society (1709) which eventually resulted in the establishhment of the Copley Medal (1736).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Davies; Wikipedia</p>
      <p>References: H. G. Lyons, 'Two Hundred Years Ago: 1739' in NR vol 2 (1939) pp 34-42</p>
      <p>G. H. Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR vol 10 (1953) pp 101-130</p>
      <p>R. E. W. Maddison, 'Abraham Hill, FRS (1635-1722)' in NR v.15 (1960) pp.173-182, plate</p>
      <p>Mark Govier, 'The Royal Society, Slavery and the Island of Jamaica: 1660-1700' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 203-217 for information on association with trading companies</p>
      <p>J. Gribbin, 'The Fellowship: the story of a revolution', (London, 2005), pp 162-164</p>
      <p>C. Malcolmson, 'Studies of skin colour in the early Royal Society', (London, 2016), pp 82-86.</p>
      <p>AssocMaterial: Correspondence of Abraham Hill from various repositories is listed in the Early Modern Letters Online catalogue, http://emlo.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/forms/advanced?start=50&amp;people=hill,%20abraham&amp;start=0</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>merchant</term>
   </note>
</person>