<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6133">
   <persName>
      <forename>Edmund</forename>
      <surname>Waller</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1606 - 1687</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Stocks Place Manor House, Coleshill, Hertfordshire, England, Europe (3 March 1606)</p>
      <p>Baptism: Amersham, Buckinghamshire, England, Europe (9 March 1606)</p>
      <p>Death: St James's Street, Westminster, London, England, Europe (21 October 1687)</p>
      <p>Burial: Parish church of Beaconsfield, Buckinghamshire, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Politician</p>
      <p>Poet</p>
      <p>Education: Mr Dobson's School at High Wycombe; Eton College; King's College, Cambridge (matriculated 1621); Lincoln's Inn (admitted 1622)</p>
      <p>Career: MP for Ilchester (1624), for Chipping Wycombe (1626), for Amersham (1628, 1640), for St Ives (1640-1643), for Hastings (1660), and for Saltash (1685); conducted the impeachment of Sir Francis Crawley (1641); opposed the raising of troops by Parliament (1642); leader in 'Waller's plot' to seize London for Charles I; imprisoned in the Tower of London (1643-1644); sold his estate to save himself from hanging; in exile in Paris (1644-1651); pardoned and returned to England (1651); Commissioner for Trade (1655-1657, 1660-1668); Commissioner for Plantations (1660-1674) Commissioner for Corporations (1662-1663); Commissioner for Assessment for Buckinghamshire (1663-1674, 1679-1680), for Middlesex (1664-1669), and for Westminster (1673-1679); Commissioner for Accounts, Ireland (1668)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee of Agriculture [Georgical Committee]</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: While Waller was never fully expelled from the Society, his name was placed on multiple lists to collect years' worth of arrears.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; Aubrey; Henning; ODNB</p>
      <p>Note: The election date is Waller's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 16 January 1661.</p>
      <p>Some sources state his place of death as Hall Barn, Beaconsfield in Buckinghamshire.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>poet and politician</term>
   </note>
</person>