<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6321">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Smeaton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1724 - 1792</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Austhorpe, near Leeds, Yorkshire, England (08 June 1724)</p>
      <p>Death: Austhorpe, Yorkshire (28 October 1792)</p>
      <p>Burial: In the chancel of Whitkirk parish church, Yorkshire</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Engineer</p>
      <p>Research Field: Civil engineering</p>
      <p>Career: Employed in the office of his father, an attorney; went to London, gave up law, and entered the service of a scientific instrument maker; later started his own similar business; designed and built the Eddystone Lighthouse (1756-1759) Lord Macclesfield proposed Smeaton for the Royal Society's prestigious Copley Medal for his "Experimental inquiry concerning the powers of water and wind in the moving of Mills" (published in 'Philosophical Transactions' volume 51 1759-1760, pp 100-174) on 22 November 1759. Medal awarded, with 15 page laudatory speech recorded in Journal Book, on 30 November 1759.</p>
      <p>After a sound elementary education Smeaton was encouraged to follow a legal career and was employed in the office of his father, an attorney; then was sent to London for further training in the courts. His inclination to mechanical arts prevailed, and with his father's consent he gave up law and entered the service of a scientific instrument maker; then started his own similar business as a maker of scientific instruments, thereby providing scope for both his scientific interests and his mechanical ingenuity. In the 1750's he produced several technical innovations, including a novel pyrometer with which he studied the expansion of various materials. However, the pace of industrial and and commercial progress directed his attention to large scale engineering works. From 1756-1759 Smeaton was occupied with his best known achievement, the rebuilding of the Eddystone lighthouse, which confirmed his reputation as an engineer. He subsequently became a consultant in the more profitable structural engineering and river harbour works, and adopted the term 'civil engineer' to distinguish civilian consultants from the military engineers graduating from the Military Academy at Woolwich. He was elected Fellow of the Royal Society in 1753, and in 1759 he published a paper on water wheels and windmills, for which he received the Copley Medal of the Royal Society. He was a member of the Royal Society Club, an occasional guest at meetings of the Lunar Society, and a charter member of the first professional engineering society, the Society of Civil Engineers founded in 1771; after his death it became known as the Smeatonian Society. Its founding reflected the growing sense of professionalism among British civilian engineers during the eighteenth century.</p>
      <p/>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 15/03/1753</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1759</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Journal Book Original Volume XXIV, pp 399-414</p>
      <p>References: R L Hills, 'John Watt's Map of the Clyde' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 63-71</p>
      <p>A P Woolrich, 'The Printing of Smeaton's Reports' in NR 1980 vol 35 pp 131-133</p>
      <p>A W Skempton, 'The Publication of Smeaton's Reports' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 135-155, plate</p>
      <p>J R M Setchell, 'The Friendship of John Smeaton, FRS, with Henry Hindley, Instrument and Clockmaker of York and the Development of Equatorial Mounting Telescopes' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 79-86</p>
      <p>J R M Setchell, 'Further Information on the Telescopes of Hindley of York' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 189-192</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'The Club of the Royal College of Physicians, the Smeatonian Society of Civil Engineers and their Relationship to the Royal Society Club' in NR 1967 vol 22 pp 186-192</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'Priestley's Laboratory and Library and Other of his Effects' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 114-136</p>
      <p>J A D Ackroyd, 'Sir George Cayley, the father of aeronautics. Part 2. Cayley's aeroplanes' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 333-348</p>
      <p>J Corden, 'Web of Science History' project in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 383-388</p>
      <p>See; http://www.timeout.com/london/music/features/76/Kaiser_Chiefs-10_things.html&gt;http://www.timeout.com/london/music/features/76/Kaiser_Chiefs-10_things.html [Ricky Wilson, one of the 'KaiserChiefs' pop group went to Leeds Grammar School and namechecks another ex-pupil in the song "I predict a riot" with the line 'would never have happenede to Smeaton'. John Smeaton (1724-1792) is the father of civil engineering'.]</p>
      <p>A N Rollinson 'Engineering and technology of Industrial water Power at Castleford Mills from the seventeenth century to the twentieth century.' N&amp;R Vol 70 Issue 1 March 2016, pp45-63</p>
      <p/>
   </note>
</person>