<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6304">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Gauden</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1605 - 1662</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Mayland, Essex, England, Europe ( 1605)</p>
      <p>Death: 22 September 1662</p>
      <p>Burial: Worcester Cathedral, Worcester, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Education: School at Bury St Edmunds, Suffolk; St John's College, Cambridge: BA (1623), MA (1626). Wadham College, Oxford: BD (1635), DD (1641)</p>
      <p>Career: Tutor at Oxford to his brothers-in-law, the sons of Sir William Russell, and others; Vicar of Chippenham (1640-1642); Chaplain to Robert Rich, Earl of Warwick; Rector of Brightwell, Berkshire; Dean of Bocking, Essex (1641); conformed to Presbyterianism under the Commonwealth but published in support of the Church of England; Preacher to the Temple (1660); Chaplain to the King (1660); Bishop of Exeter (1660-1662); expected to become Bishop of Winchester but was made Bishop of Worcester (1662); died of a violent attack of the stone and strangury</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 18/12/1661</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: DNB; Venn; Foster; Hunter; ODNB</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is a possible election date into the Society. Gauden died prior to the grant of the second charter in April 1663. He is therefore not considered an original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the second charter of the Society granted in 1663, or elected within the following two month period stipulated therein for the declaration of Fellows. I.e the original Fellows are only those who were officially declared at the meetings of 20 May 1663 and 22 June 1663, elections like Gauden's that predated these meetings were no longer recognised.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>bishop of Worcester</term>
   </note>
</person>