<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6502">
   <persName>
      <forename>David</forename>
      <surname>Rittenhouse</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1732 - 1796</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Paper Mill Run, near Germantown, Pennsylvania (08 April 1732)</p>
      <p>Death: Philadephia, Pennsylvania, USA (26 June 1796)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Scientific instrument maker</p>
      <p>Research Field: Technology, astronomy, natural philosophy</p>
      <p>Career: Established himself as a clock and mathematical instrument maker in Norriston (1751); took up astronomy (1768); moved to Philadelphia (1770) and studied the electrical properties of the electric eel and surveyed the levels of the lands between the Suquehama and Delaware Rivers; constructed cannon of iron and of brass; elected Member of the Assembly from Philadelphia (1776); elected State Treasurer (1777-1789); Professor of Astronomy, University of Pennsylvania (1779-1782); Secretary of the American Philosophical Society (1771), Vice President (1786) and President (1790-1796)</p>
      <p>First experiment in the New World to make crosshairs with spider silk for his astronomical instruments. Described his experience to Reverend John Ewing (1732-1802) the first provost of the University of Pennsylvania, in a letter read before the members of the American Philosophical Society and then published in 1786 in the Society's 'Transactions'. "I have lately with no small dificulty placed the thread of a spider in some of my instruments, it has a beautiful effect, it is not one tenth the size of a silkworm, and is rounder and more evenly of a thickness".</p>
      <p>Memberships: American Philosophical Society (1768)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 16/04/1795</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DAB; DSB</p>
      <p>References: Frank R Freemon, 'American Colonial Scientists Who Published in the Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 191-206</p>
      <p>Notes: Bulloch's Roll has birth place as Roxburgh, PA</p>
   </note>
</person>