<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6536">
   <persName>
      <forename>Henry Bartle Edward</forename>
      <surname>Frere</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1815 - 1884</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Clydach, Monmouthshire, Wales, United Kingdom (29 March 1815)</p>
      <p>Death: Wimbledon, London, Greater London, England, United Kingdom (29 May 1884)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Paul's Cathedral, London</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Colonial administrator</p>
      <p>Research field: Natural history; religion</p>
      <p>Education: Haileybury College; East India Company College</p>
      <p>Career: Joined the Bombay Civil Service (1834); Assistant Collector, Poona; Private Secretary to Sir George Arthur, Governor of Bombay (1842); Commissioner at Scinde (1850-1859); Governor of Bombay (1862-1867); Member of Council of the Secretary of State for India (1866-1877); Privy Councillor (1873); received the Freedom of the City of London (1874); accompanied the Prince of Wales on his tour in India (1875); Governor of Cape Colony and High Commission for South Africa (1877); as Governor implemented a set of policies which attempted to impose a British confederation on the region and led to the overthrow of the Cape's first elected government in 1878 and a string of regional wars, culminating in theAnglo-Zulu war (1879), Basotho Gun War (1880) and the First Boer War (1880-1881); recalled to England to face charges of misconduct (1880) charged with having acted recklessly, and censured by Parliament; Mount Bartle Frere (1622m), the highest mountain in Queensland, Australia, is named after him; The botanist, N. A. Dalzell (1864) named the plant genus Frerea in his honour "not only as a mark of esteem and respect, but also because he always has been the enlightened encourager and promoter of scientific researches in India, and is himself a close observer of nature."</p>
      <p>Honours: KCB 1859; GCSI 1867; Bt 1876; GCB 1876</p>
      <p>Memberships: Royal Asiatic Society (President 1872); Royal Society of South Africa (founder and President, 1877)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 03/05/1877</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB</p>
      <p>References: Vanity Fair 20 September 1873</p>
      <p>Notes: Boase gives birth date as 29 March 1815; BR gives 15 March 1815</p>
   </note>
</person>