<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6626">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles</forename>
      <surname>Babbage</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1791 - 1871</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Teignmouth, Devon, England (26 December 1791)</p>
      <p>Death: London (18 October 1871)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Mathematician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Mathematics, computer logic, computer technology</p>
      <p>Education: Holmwood School, Ponder's End (with Frederick Marryat (FRS 1819)); entered Trinity College, Cambridge (1811), but graduated from Peterhouse, Cambridge. BA (1814), MA (1817)</p>
      <p>Career: Lucasian Professor of Mathematics, Cambridge (1828-1839); developed calculating machine using his own money and government grants; involved in actuarial work</p>
      <p>Memberships: Statistical Society (Founder Fellow 1834); FRAS</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 14/03/1816</p>
      <p>Council:</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>References: Alex D D Craik, 'James Ivory, FRS, mathematician: "the most unlucky person that ever existed"' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 223-247</p>
      <p>Maurice V Wilkes, 'The Ubiquitous Mr Babbage', review of Charles Babbage, Passages From the Life of a Philosopher, ed. M Campbell-Kelly, in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 341-342</p>
      <p>Richard Sorrenson, 'Towards a History of the Royal Society in the Eighteenth Century' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 29-46</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Herschel, Peacock, Babbage and the Development of the Cambridge Curriculum' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 205-219</p>
      <p>Peter J Turvey, 'Sir John Herschel and the Abandonment of Charles Babbage's Difference Engine No. 1' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 165-176</p>
      <p>Lise Wilkinson, 'Three Drawings of Fellows by William Brockedon, FRS' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 183-187, plate</p>
      <p>Roy M MacLeod, 'Of Medals and Men: A Reward System in Victorian Science 1826-1914' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 81-105</p>
      <p>L Pearce Williams, 'The Royal Society and the Founding of the British Association for the Advancement of Science' in NR 1961 vol 16 pp 221-233</p>
      <p>L F Gilbert, 'The Election to the Presidency of the Royal Society in 1820' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 256-279</p>
      <p>J A D Ackroyd, 'Sir George Cayley, the father of aeronautics, Part 1. The invention of the aeroplane' NR 2002 vol 56 pp 167-181</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'A Roman tercentenary' by A Cook in NR 2002 vol 56 p273</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Charles Babbage and his world' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 353-365</p>
      <p>K K Schwarz, 'Faraday and Babbage' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 367-381</p>
      <p>F C Moon, 'Robert Willis and Franz Reuleaux: pioneers in the theory of machines' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 209-230</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Lucasian Professors. From Newton to Hawking: a history of Cambridge University's Lucasian professors of mathematics, ed K C Knox and R Noakes' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 312-313</p>
      <p>Notes: Date of birth incorrect in DNB, DSB and Boase. Photograph of election certificate, RS Box 3; negative RS Box N101</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Mathematician</term>
   </note>
</person>