<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6761">
   <persName>
      <forename>Henry</forename>
      <surname>Power</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1623 - 1668</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Annesley, Nottinghamshire, England, Europe (c1623)</p>
      <p>Death: New Hall near Elland, Halifax, Yorkshire, England, Europe (December 1668)</p>
      <p>Burial: Church of All Saints, Wakefield, Yorkshire, England, Europe (23 December 1668)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Microscopy; physics; medicine</p>
      <p>Education: Mr Higginson's School at Halifax, Yorkshire; Christ's College, Cambridge (BA 1644; MA 1648; MD 1655)</p>
      <p>Career: Practised at Halifax; correspondent of Sir Thomas Browne; conducted experiments with Richard Towneley, some reports of which later became part of 'Experimental Philosophy' (1664); transferred medical practice to Wakefield (1664); wrote but did not publish 'Historia physico-anatomica' (mid 1660s)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 1/07/1663</p>
      <p>Proposer: John Wilkins</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Correspondent with William Croone (FRS 1663) regarding his experimental researches and meteorological observations.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Hunter; ODNB</p>
      <p>Notes: Venn gives place of birth as Annesley, Notts</p>
      <p>JT Hughes 'Henry Power (1626-1668) of New Hall, Elland and experiments on barometric pressure'. in Transactions of the Halifax Antiquarian Society, ns10 (2002), pp14-26</p>
      <p>JT Hughes 'Dr Henry Power (1626-1668): The Medical Practice of a Halifax Physician' in Transactions of the Halifax Antiquarian Society, vol 11 (2003), pp 56-67 - gives date of birth as 1626. "On entering Christ's College, Henry was 15, and his birthplace was given as Annesley, Notts" see also Cambridge records, Peile, 1910 p 477.</p>
      <p>Notes: Originally elected 26 February 1662 [JB]; also elected and admitted 1 July 1663 [JB], also 'Dr Henry Power was again proposed ... and was presently elected, having been formerly chosen Already by the first Charter' 25 May 1664 [JB]. Power is therefore not considered an original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the second charter of the Society granted in 1663, or elected within the following two month period stipulated therein for the declaration of Fellows. I.e the original Fellows are only those who were officially declared at the meetings of 20 May 1663 and 22 June 1663, elections like Powers's that predated these meetings were no longer recognised. The date of any subsequent re-election is given in this database as the official election date.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher and physician</term>
   </note>
</person>