<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6857">
   <persName>
      <forename>James</forename>
      <surname>Petiver</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1663 - 1718</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Hillmorton, near Rugby, Warwickshire, England, Europe (1663)</p>
      <p>Death: Aldersgate Street, London, England, Europe (2 April 1718)</p>
      <p>Burial: Chancel of St Botolph's Church, Aldersgate Street, London, England, Europe (10 April 1718)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Apothecary</p>
      <p>Research Field: Botany; entomology</p>
      <p>Education: Rugby School; apprenticed to Charles Feltham, apothecary to St Bartholomew's Hospital, London; University of Leyden (1711)</p>
      <p>Career: Practised in London; corresponded with John Ray (FRS 1667) and many other naturalists; made a collection of several thousand plants; Apothecary to the Charterhouse (1700-1718); helped initiate 'The Monthly Miscellany; or, Memoirs for the Curious' (1707); Demonstrator of Plants to the Society of Apothecaries (1709); purchased Dr Hermann's museum in Leyden for Sir Hans Sloane (FRS 1685) (1711); Sloane purchased his collections of specimens, books and manuscripts after his death and they are now in the British Museum</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 27/11/1695</p>
      <p>Council: 1702-1709 (with intermittent breaks); 1716-1717</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Presented findings as well as correspondence on natural history to the Society (1690s)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Innes Smith</p>
      <p>References: Frank N Egerton, 'Richard Bradley's Relationship with Sir Hans Sloane' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 59-77</p>
      <p>W H G Armytage, 'The Royal Society and the Apothecaries' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 22-37</p>
      <p>P Fontes da Costa, 'The Culture of Curiosity at The Royal Society in the first half of the eighteenth century', NR 2002 vo l56 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>J H Appleby, 'The founding of St Petersburg in the context of the Royal Society's relationship with Russia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 273-284</p>
      <p>N Ibanez, J M Monserrat, I Soriano and J M Camarasa, 'Plant material exchanged between James Petiver (ca.1663-1718) and Joan Salvador I Riera (1683-1725). I. The Balearic plants conserved in the BC-Salvador', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 241-248</p>
      <p>Jarvis, C E and Richard Coulton. 2020. 'A Chronology of the Life of James Petiver (ca 1663-1718), in Notes and Records, vol. 74, pp.183-187 [DOI: 10.1098/rsnr.2020.0010; last accessed: 23/02/2022]</p>
      <p>Delbourgo, J. 2017. 'Collecting the World: The Life and Curiosity of Hans Sloane' (Allen Lane)</p>
      <p>Notes: There is some discrepancy within sources as to Petiver's year of birth. Hunter, as well as Jarvis and Coulton, have 1663, while ODNB estimates 1665.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>botanist and entomologist</term>
   </note>
</person>