<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA6942">
   <persName>
      <forename>Erasmus</forename>
      <surname>Darwin</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1731 - 1802</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Elston Hall, Nottinghamshire, England (12 December 1731)</p>
      <p>Death: Breadsall Priory, Derbyshire (18 April 1802)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Physician</p>
      <p>Poet</p>
      <p>Research Field: Medicine, scientific poetry, botany, technology</p>
      <p>Education: Chesterfield School (1741-1750); St John's College, Cambridge; Edinburgh Medical School. MB (1755); MD (Edinburgh)</p>
      <p>Career: First medical practice in Nottingham, moved to Lichfield, Staffordshire; member of the Lunar Society; many inventions, including a vertical-axis windmill, used in Josiah Wedgwood's (FRS 1783) factory; moved to Radbourne Hall with his second wife, because she disliked Lichfield.</p>
      <p>Freemason, member, Lodge St David No 36, Edinburgh</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 9/04/1761</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn</p>
      <p>References: Robert E Schofield, 'The Lunar Society of Birmingham; A Bicentenary Appraisal' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 144-161</p>
      <p>Nora Barlow, 'Erasmus Darwin, FRS (1731-1802)' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 85-98, plate</p>
      <p>John Thomas, 'Josiah Wedgwood's Portrait Medallions of Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 45-53, plate</p>
      <p>D G King-Hele, 'Erasmus Darwin, Man of Ideas and Inventor of Words' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 149-180, plate</p>
      <p>D G King-Hele, 'Shelley and Science' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 253-265</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'Portraits of Dr Erasmus Darwin, FRS, by Joseph Wright, James Rawlinson and William Coffee' in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 69-84, plate</p>
      <p>Desmond King-Hele, 'Erasmus Darwin's Life at Lichfield: Fresh Evidence' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 231-243</p>
      <p>Desmond King-Hele, 'The 1997 Wilkins Lecture: Erasmus Darwin, the Lunaticks and Evolution' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 153-180, plate</p>
      <p>Gordon C Cook, 'Mary Darwin's Illness' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 59-63</p>
      <p>Linde Katritzky, 'Coleridge's Links with Leading Men of Science' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 261-276</p>
      <p>'Erratum' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 381-382</p>
      <p>Gordon C Cook and Desmond King-Hele, 'Doctor Erasmus Darwin's Death in 1802' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 261-265</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Portland Vase: Sir William Hamilton, Josiah Wedgwood and the Darwins' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 237-259, plate</p>
      <p>Neil Chambers, 'Letters From the President: the Correspondence of Sir Joseph Banks' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 27-57</p>
      <p>Paul Elliott, 'Abraham Bennet, FRS (1749-1799): A Provincial Electrician in Eighteenth-Century England' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 59-78</p>
      <p>Desmond King-Hele, 'Erasmus Darwin's improved design for steering carriages - and cars' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 41-62, plate</p>
      <p>L B Glyn, 'Israel Lyons: a short but starry career. The life of an eighteenth-century Jewish botanist and astronomer' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 275-305</p>
      <p>J Browne, 'Darwin on Darwin. Charles Darwin's The Life of Erasmus Darwin, ed D King-Hele' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 346 - 348</p>
      <p>D King-Hele, 'Makers of the future. The Lunar Men: the friends who made the future, by J Uglow' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 348 - 350</p>
      <p>The Library and Museum of Freemasonry 'Freemasons and the Royal Society; Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were Freemasons' 2010, page 26</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician, botanist and poet</term>
   </note>
</person>