<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7297">
   <persName>
      <forename>Bertram</forename>
      <surname>Hopkinson</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1874 - 1918</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Birmingham (11 January 1874 )</p>
      <p>Death: 26 August 1918 (Buried at St Giles Cemetery Cambridge after a military funeral on 30 August 1918)</p>
      
      <p>Experimental Physicist</p>
      <p>Education: St. Paul's, London; Trinity College, Cambridge 1893-6 (MA Mathematics).</p>
      <p>King's College London and/or King's College London Hospital</p>
      <p>B.Sc (1894) Experimental Physics</p>
      <p>Career: Appointed professor of mechanism and applied mechanics in Cambridge, in charge of the department of mechanical ~science (later engineering). His work was in metal stress, alloys, magnetism, explosion in gases and the internal combustion engine.</p>
      <p>Royal Air Force Flying Corps, November 1915</p>
      <p>Tribute from Sir Alfred Ewing, Principal of Edinburgh University, to The Times, 12 September 1918 to the scientific work of the late Colonel Bertram Hopkinson, C.M.G., F.R.S.. He says :- “It is indeed a tragedy in this regard that he should have been taken at the very summit of his powers, and at the moment when they were so fully engaged in serving the nation’s urgent need. His genius for applied science was hereditary. He had the same faculty as gave his father an honoured place in the history of electrical engineering, the same rare combination of mastery of theory and scientific method with appreciation of practical requirements and possibilities. It was this that enabled him to be conspicuously successful as Professor of Applied Mechanics at Cambridge: and it was this that made the value of his war work almost unique. It chanced that his own researches before the war, and those of students working under him in the Cambridge laboratory, formed in some degree a preparation for what was to come. They dealt with the processes and results of explosions, with the action of internal-combustion engines, and with the fatigue of materials under incipient overstrain. They were of high interest in themselves and in their bearing on matters of engineering practice. But to Hopkinson they were more: one may say they constituted and apprenticeship for the great work of his life, which was the work of the past four years. Of what he has accomplished in these years, for the Admiralty, and especially for the Air Force, it is not now permissible to speak. This, however, may be said, that the war gave him such an opportunity as he had never had before, and into it he threw all his inventiveness, all his initiative, his untiring energy, his power of organisation, his unrivalled capacity for getting the best out of himself and out of others. No worker rejoiced more in his work, nor accepted its call with more absolute self-renunciation. He was amazingly aloof from any consideration of personal advantage or personal convenience. The pressure of exacting claims on his attention was continuous, but it seemed never able to ruffle his serenity nor impair the soundness of his judgment. Many will mourn him as a genial and trusted friend, but only those who know something of his recent activities can have any idea of the magnitude of the nation’s loss.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Honours: CMG 1918</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 5/05/1910</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc Series A 1918-1919 vol 95 pp xxvi-xxvi, plate, signed by J A E</p>
      <p>The Times, 12 September 1918, by Sir Alfred Ewing</p>
      <p>References: T M Charlton, 'Professor Bertram Hopkinson, CMG, MA, BSc, FRS (1874-1918)' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 101-109</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Online sources;</p>
      <p>http://kingscollections.org/warmemorials/kings-college/memorials/hopkinson-bertram</p>
   </note>
</person>