<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7289">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Winde</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1642 - 1722</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Bergen-op-Zoom, Holland, Europe (c. 1642)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Great Britain, Europe (April 1722)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Martin-in-the-Fields, Westminster, London, England, Great Britain, Europe (28 April 1722)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Architect</p>
      <p>Soldier</p>
      <p>Career: Ensign with English troops at Bergen-op-Zoom (1658); returned to England (1660); Gentleman Usher to Elizabeth, sister of Charles I (1661); Cornet in the King's Troop of the Royal Regiment of Horse (1667); assisted in the fortification of Gravesend Reach against the Dutch Navy (1667); sent to Jersey as Captain of a troop of horse (1678); made a map of the island which he presented to Charles II (1679); fought at Sedgemoor (1685); disappointed at his lack of promotion, he abandoned his military career (1688) and possibly trained under Sir Balthazar Gerbier; employed under first Earl of Craven as an architect for Hampstead Marshall in Berkshire (c.1662-1688); practised as an architect</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Proposer: John Wilkins (4 June 1662)</p>
      <p>Date of ejection/withdrawal: 22 July 1685 (due to lack of payment)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; ODNB</p>
      <p>Howard Colvin (1995) 'A Biographical Dictionary of British Architects, 1600-1840'</p>
      <p>References: Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Winde's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 17 September 1662 and admitted into the Society on 5 November 1662..</p>
      <p>There are some discrepancies across sources as to Winde's year of birth. Colvin says that his father went to Bergen-op-Zoom in 1647 and if Winde was born there he was a very young ensign. ODNB says 1642; VIAF says 1649. The latter would have made him approximately ten years old when he started to establish a military career, according to ODNB.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>architect and soldier</term>
   </note>
</person>