<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7472">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Wallis</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1616 - 1703</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Ashford, Kent, England, Europe (3 December 1616)</p>
      <p>Death: Oxford, England, Europe (8 November 1703)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Mary's Church, Oxford, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Mathematician</p>
      <p>Research Field: mathematics</p>
      <p>Education: School at Ashford; James Mouat's School at Ley Green, near Tenterden, Kent; Felsted School (for 2 years); Emmanuel College, Cambridge (BA 1637); MA 1640); Incorporated at Oxford (1649; DD 1654); Incorporated from Oxford (1656)</p>
      <p>Career: Ordained (1640); Chaplain to Sir Richard Darley (1640-1642) and to Mary, Baroness Vere (1642-1644); employed by Parliament to decipher intercepted dispatches (1642-1645); Fellow of Queens' College, Cambridge (1644-1645); Secretary to the Westminster Assembly (1644); Rector of St Gabriel's, Fenchurch Street, London (1645-1647); Minister of St Martin's, Ironmonger Lane, London (1647); Savilian Professor of Geometry at Oxford (1649-1703); Keeper of the Archives at Oxford (1654-1703); published 'Arithmetica Infinitorum' (1656); one of twelve Presbyterian representatives at the Savoy Conference (1661); Justice of the Peace; Decipherer to William III; opposed the adoption of the Gregorian Calendar (1692);</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for Collecting all the Phaenomena of Nature hitherto observed, and all Experiments made and recorded</p>
      <p>Committee to consider a way of determining the measure of a degree on the earth (1669)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Frequent correspondence with secretary Henry Oldenburg</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster</p>
      <p>References: Margaret Deacon, 'Founders of Marine Science in Britain: the Work of the Early Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 28-50</p>
      <p>J F Scott, 'The Reverend John Wallis, FRS (1616-1703)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 57-67, plate</p>
      <p>J F Scott and Sir Harold Hartley, 'William, Viscount Brouncker, PRS (1620-1684)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 147-157</p>
      <p>J E McGuire and P M Rattansi, 'Newton and the "Pipes of Pan"' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 108-143</p>
      <p>H E Bell, 'The Savilian Professors' Houses and Halley's Observatory at Oxford' in NR 1961 vol 16 pp 179-186</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'The Origins and Foundation of the Royal Society of London' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 1-37</p>
      <p>Derek T Whiteside, 'Wren the Mathematician' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 107-111</p>
      <p>Christoph J Scriba, 'A Tentative Index of the Correspondence of John Wallis, FRS' in NR 1967 vol 22 pp 58-93</p>
      <p>C S S, 'The Society's Library' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 21-27</p>
      <p>A C S, 'Notes on the Foundation and History of the Royal Society' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 32-36</p>
      <p>Jacqueline A Stedall, 'Catching Proteus: the collaborations of Wallis and Brouncker. I. Squaring the circle' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 293-316</p>
      <p>Jacqueline A Stedall, 'Catching Proteus: the collaborations of Wallis and Brouncker. II. Number problems' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 317-331</p>
      <p>Katherine Hill, 'Neither Ancient nor Modern: Wallis and Barrow on the Composition of Continua. Part One: Mathematical Styles and the Composition of Continua' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 165-178, plate</p>
      <p>Katherine Hill, 'Neither Ancient nor Modern: Wallis and Barrow on the Composition of Continua. Part Two: The Seventeenth-Century Context: The Struggle Between Ancient and Modern' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 13-22</p>
      <p>Brebis Bleaney, 'The Physical Sciences in Oxford, 1918-1939 and Earlier' in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 247-261</p>
      <p>G J Whitrow, 'Newton's Role in the History of Mathematics' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 71-92</p>
      <p>J R Philip, 'An Innumerate President of the Royal Society?' in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 1-10</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London and Oxford' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 157-168</p>
      <p>Christoph J Scriba, 'The Autobiography of John Wallis, FRS' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 17-46</p>
      <p>Christopher Hill, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London or Oxford?' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 144-156</p>
      <p>G L'E Turner, 'Henry Baker, FRS: Founder of the Bakerian Lecture' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 53-79</p>
      <p>A Cook, '1703 and other anniversaries' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 1-2</p>
      <p>J Gray, 'Harriot Restored. &lt;i&gt;The greate invention of algebra: Thomas Harriot's treatise on equations&lt;/i&gt;, by Jacqueline A Stedall' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 101-102</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Wallis' re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 6 March 1661.</p>
      <p>Old Style calendar puts Wallis' date of birth as 23 November 1616 and his date of death as 28 October 1703.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>mathematician and cryptographer</term>
   </note>
</person>