<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7731">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles</forename>
      <surname>Howard</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1630 - 1713</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 13 September 1630</p>
      <p>Death: 31 March 1713</p>
      <p>Burial: Dorking church, Surrey, England, United Kingdom, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Research field: Agriculture</p>
      <p>Arboriculture</p>
      <p>Botany</p>
      <p>Career: Travelled in France and the Netherlands (1640s-1650s); landscaped the garden at Deepdene (1652-); applied for a patent for new method of tanning in 'Brief Directions how to Tanne Leather According to a New Invention' (1660); applied for a patent for a new way of processing flax (1678); engaged in lengthy lawsuits with his brother and nephew, the 6th and 7th Dukes of Norfolk), over the barony of Greystoke (1677-1685)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Proposers: Colonel Samuel Tuke (24 December 1662)</p>
      <p>Council: On Council (1663-1664)</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee to consider Mr Buckland's proposition to plant potatoes through all parts of England (1662)</p>
      <p>Committee to consider propagating Cyder-Fruit all over England (1663)</p>
      <p>Chemical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Agricultural [Georgical] Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for the Histories of Trades (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Contributed and wrote about sulphorous vapours (1662).</p>
      <p>Wrote papers on the cultivation, drying, and selling of saffron (1663).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB (MP)</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Howard's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 24 December 1662 and admitted into the Society on 31 December 1662.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>landowner and natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>