<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7894">
   <persName>
      <forename>Joseph</forename>
      <surname>Larmor</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1857 - 1942</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Magheragall, County Antrim, Ulster (11 July 1857)</p>
      <p>Death: Holywood, County Down, Ulster (19 May 1942)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Theoretical physics</p>
      <p>Education: Royal Belfast Academical Insitution</p>
      <p>Queens's University Belfast, BA, MA;</p>
      <p>St John's College Cambridge for mathemtical Tripos. Graduated 1880 as Senior Wrangler (top First Class student) and first Smith's Prizeman.</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of St John's College, Cambridge; University and College Lecturer in Mathematics; Senior Wrangler, 1880; Professor of Natural Philosophy Queen's College, Galway 1880-1885; Lecturer, St John's College Cambridge 1885; Lucasian Professor of Mathematics, Cambridge 1903-1932; Fellow of the Royal University of Ireland; Examiner in Mathematics at the University of London</p>
      <p>Member of London Mathematical Society from 1884, Council Member 1887-1912; Vice President 1890, Treasurer 1892-1914, President 1914; awarded the De Morgan Medal 1914</p>
      <p>Honorary degrees from Dublin, Oxford, Belfast, Glasgow, Aberdeen, Birmingham, St. Andrews, Durham and Cambridge Universities.</p>
      <p>Member of Royal Irish Academy, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and Accademia dei Lincei</p>
      <p>MP for University of Cambridge 1911-1922</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1909</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 2/06/1892</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Royal Medal 1915; Copley Medal 1921</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1909</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1901-1912; VP 1912-1914</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society 1942-1944 vol 4 pp 197-207, plate, by A S Eddington</p>
      <p>References: Andrew Warwick, 'Frequency, Theorem and Formula: Remembering Joseph Larmor in Electromagnetic Theory' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 49-60, plate</p>
      <p>Maurice V Wilkes, 'Sir Edward Appleton and Early Ionosphere Research' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 281-290</p>
      <p>G D Birkhoff, 'Sir Joseph Larmor and modern mathematical physics' in Scienc (NS) 97 (1943), pp77-79</p>
      <p>JZ Buchwald, 'The abandonment of Maxwellian electrodynamics; Joseph Larmor's theory of the electron' Part I in Arch. Internat. Hist. Sci. 31 (106) (1981), 135-180, and (107)(1981) 373-438</p>
      <p>E Cunningham, 'Sir Joseph Larmor' in Journal of the London Math. Soc. 18(1943), 57-64</p>
      <p>E Cunningham, 'Sir Joseph Larmor' in Proc.Phys. Soc. London 55 (1943), 248-249</p>
      <p>A Warwick, 'On the role of the FitzGerald-Lorentz contraction hypothesis in the development of Joseph Larmor's electronic theory of matter' in Archive for History of Exact Science 43(1)(1991), 29-91</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>W Hayes, 'Physics as well as poetry. Physicists of Ireland, edited by M McCartney and A Whitaker' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 245-246</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Physicist</term>
   </note>
</person>