<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7854">
   <persName>
      <forename>Edward</forename>
      <surname>Troughton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1753 - 1835</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: In the parish of Corney, Cumberland, England (October 1753)</p>
      <p>Death: London (12 June 1835)</p>
      <p>Burial: Kensal Green cemetery, London</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Scientific instrument maker</p>
      <p>Research Field: Mathematics, optics, physics</p>
      <p>Career: Apprenticed to his elder brother, John, a mechanician in London, and later was his partner; after John's death, Edward took into partnership William Simms (FRS 1852); invented a new method of graduating arcs of circles (1778); was colour blind</p>
      <p>First English maker of mathematics instruments to apply spider silk in surveying and astronomical instruments, though other English makers followed his lead. Troughton made a micrometer for Sir John Frederick William Herschel's seven foot equatorial instrument he used for the observations made between 1821 and 1823 of the apparent distances and positions of 380 double and triple stars. In 1824 on their five foot focus equatorial telescope John Herschel and Sir Edwin South used a Troughton micrometer and measured position angles to the remarkable degree of accuracy of 1" of arc.</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 15/03/1810</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1809</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1834-1835 No 22 p 355</p>
      <p>References: Brian J Ford, 'Shining Through the Centuries: John Ray's Life and Legacy. A Report of the Meeting "John Ray and his Successors"' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 5-22</p>
      <p>Allan Chapman, 'Pre-Eminently Precise', review of Anita McConnell, Instrument Makers to the World. A History of Cooke, Troughton, and Simms and Eleanor Mennim, Transit Circle. The Story of William Simms, 1793-1860 in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 168-170</p>
      <p>Charles H Cotter, 'The Mariner's Sextant and the Royal Society' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 23-36</p>
      <p>A W Skempton and Joyce Brown, 'John and Edward Troughton, Mathematical Instrument Makers' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 233-262, plate</p>
      <p>M Croarken, 'Astronomical labourers: Maskelyne's assistants at the Royal Observatory, Greenwich, 1765 - 1811' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 285 - 298</p>
   </note>
</person>