<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7960">
   <persName>
      <forename>Isaac</forename>
      <surname>Barrow</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1630 - 1677</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: London, England, Europe (October 1630)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (4 May 1677)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey, London, England, Europe (7 May 1677)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Geometry</p>
      <p>Optics</p>
      <p>Education: Charterhouse School; Felsted School; Peterhouse, Cambridge (1643); Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1648/9), MA (1652), DD (1666)</p>
      <p>Career: Tutor to William Fairfax (3rd Viscount Fairfax of Emley); Fellow of Trinity (1649); incorporated at Oxford (1653); published compact editions of Euclid's 'Elements' (1656) and 'Data' (1657); travelled abroad (1655-1659); received Anglican ordination (1659); Fellow of Eton College (1660); Regius Professor of Greek at Cambridge (1660-1663); Professor of Geometry, Gresham College, London (1662-1663); Lucasian Professor of Mathematics at Cambridge (1663-1669); Prebendary of Salisbury (1671); Chaplain to Charles II; Master of Trinity College, Cambridge (1673-1677); Vice-Chancellor of Cambridge (1675-1676)</p>
      <p>Honours: Trinity College, Cambridge (BD honoris causa 1661)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: R E W Maddison, 'Abraham Hill, FRS (1635-1722)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 173-182</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'Cambridge: Newton's legacy' in NR 2001 vol 55 pp 205-226</p>
      <p>Katherine Hill, 'Neither Ancient nor Modern: Wallis and Barrow on the Composition of Continua. Part One: Mathematical Styles and the Composition of Continua' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 165-178, plate</p>
      <p>Katherine Hill, 'Neither Ancient nor Modern: Wallis and Barrow on the Composition of Continua. Part Two: The Seventeenth-Century Context: The Struggle Between Ancient and Modern' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 13-22</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Personality of Isaac Newton' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 1-56, plate</p>
      <p>Stuart Hollingdale, review of Mordechai Feingold, ed, Before Newton: the Life and Times of Isaac Barrow in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 277-279</p>
      <p>G J Whitrow, 'Newton's Role in the History of Mathematics' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 71-92</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Lucasian Professors. From Newton to Hawking: a history of Cambridge University's Lucasian professors of mathematics, ed K C Knox and R Noakes' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 312-313</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Barrow's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 17 September 1662 and admitted into the Society on 29 October 1662.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>mathematician and theologian</term>
   </note>
</person>