<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7953">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles Thomson Rees</forename>
      <surname>Wilson</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1869 - 1959</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Glencorse, Midlothian, Scotland (14 February 1869)</p>
      <p>Death: Carlops, Peeblesshire (15 November 1959)</p>
      <p>Burial: Carlops, Peeblesshire, Scotland</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Atmospheric and atomic physics</p>
      <p>Education: Greenheyes Collegiate School Manchester; BSc (Owens College, Manchester); gained an entrance scholarship to Sidney Sussex College Cambridge,(1888) and graduated 1892. MA (Cantab); BSc (Vict)</p>
      <p>Career: Appointed James Clerk Maxwell Scholar at the Cavendish Laboratory (1895) and published his first work on the cloud chamber; develops his work on behaviours of ions as condensation nuclei (1893-1898); appointed by Meteorological Research Council to conduct research on atmospheric electricity (from 1899); Fellow, Sidney Sussex College (1900); appointed Reader in Electrical Meteorology (1918); published his two landmark illustrated papers on the tracks of electrons (1923); Jacksonian Professor of Natural Philosophy, Cambridge (1925-1934)</p>
      <p>Awarded Honorary LL.D. from University of Aberdeen (1924)</p>
      <p>Honours: CH 1937</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 14/06/1900</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Hughes Medal 1911; Royal Medal 1922; Copley Medal 1935; Nobel Prize (Physics) 1927 with Arthur Holly Compton (1892-1962) for his work on the Wilson cloud chamber, which made the paths of electically charged particles visible by condensation of vapour.</p>
      <p>Council: VP 1928-1929</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1960 vol 6 pp 269-295, plate, by P M S Blackett</p>
      <p>References: P I Dee and T W Wormell, 'An Index to C T R Wilson's Laboratory Records and Notebooks in the Library of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 54-66</p>
      <p>C T R Wilson, 'Reminiscences of My Early Years' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 163-173, plate</p>
      <p>Wilfried Schroder and Karl-Heinrich Wiederkehr, 'Johann Kiessling, the Krakatoa event and the development of atmospheric optics after 1883' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp249-258</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Physicist</term>
   </note>
</person>