<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA7902">
   <persName>
      <forename>Bernard Siegfried</forename>
      <surname>Albinus</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1697 - 1770</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Frankfurt (24 February 1697)</p>
      <p>Death: Leyden (09 September 1770)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Anatomist</p>
      <p>Education: His real name was Bernhard Siegfried Weiss, which means “white” in German, the Latin version of which is “albus”, from where derives his Latinized name “Albinus</p>
      <p>He received his first instructions from his father, and from the celebrated professors at Leyden, Rau, Bidloo, and Boerhaave; and in 1713 visited France, where he formed an acquaintance with Winslow and Senac, and afterwards corresponded with them on, his favourite science, anatomy. But he had scarce spent a year there when he was invited by the curators of the university of Leyden, to be lecturer in anatomy and surgery, | in place of Rau. With this request, so flattering to a young man, he resolved to comply, although contrary to his then views and inclination, and on his arrival was created doctor in medicine without any examination. Soon after, upon the death of his father, he was appointed to succeed him as professor of anatomy, and on his admission, Nov. 9, 1721, he read a paper, “De vera via ad fabricae humani corporis cognitionem ducente,” which was heard with universal approbation.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Albinus moved to Leyden (Leiden) when he was only five years old, excelling at his studies and entering the University of Leyden at 12. He later moved to Paris, France to continue his studies on anatomy and surgery. He received his medical degree in 1719.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>He began work at the University of Leyden as a Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, where he continued working until his death in 1770. He is considered one the most well-known anatomists of the 18th century.</p>
      <p>Bernhard Siegfried Albinus</p>
      <p>Because of his work with his colleague Herman Boerhaave (1668-1738), Albinus came in contact with Jan Wandelaar (1690-1759) an artist and engraver. It was this collaboration and the art of Jan Wandelaar which have made Albinus’ books and illustration famous. Albinus was criticized for the luscious, detailed, and sometimes strange backgrounds of his anatomical images, yet he defended Jan Wandelaar and his artistic expression. Albinus and Jan Wandelaar were dedicated to the faithful reproduction of anatomy in their publications, developing a grid system to reduce errors in production and printing.</p>
      <p>During his tenure, Albinus was twice appointed Rector of the University and President of the College of Surgeons of Leyden. During this time, he became aware of the discovery of the copper plates created by Eustachius’ and lost for over a hundred years. In 1744 he published the plates in the book “Explanation of the Anatomical Tables of Eustachius “with his comments, stressing the fact that these images were better than those of Vesalius, published in 1543. This is no surprise, as Vesalius’ images were woodcuts, done before the technique of printing with copper plates became popular.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Although not well-known, Albinus’ name is eponymically attached to the risorius and scalenus minimus muscles. His famous publications include “Historia muscolorum hominis” in 1734), “Icones ossium foetus humani” in 1737, “Tabulae sceleti et musculorum corporis humani” in 1749, etc.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>This very eminent anatomist died Sept, 9, 1770, at Leyden, where he had filled the professor’s chair nearly fifty years.</p>
      <p/>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 23/02/1764</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
   </note>
</person>