<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8085">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Pell</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1611 - 1685</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Southwick, Sussex, England, Europe, (1 March 1611)</p>
      <p>Death: Dyot Street, London, England, Europe (12 December 1685)</p>
      <p>Burial: Rector's vault of St Giles-in-the-Fields, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Mathematics</p>
      <p>Education: Mr John Jefferies School at Steyning, Sussex; Trinity College, Cambridge (admitted 1624; BA (1628), MA (1630)); Incorporated at Oxford (1631); DD (Lambeth 1663)</p>
      <p>Career: Assistant Master at Collyer's School in Horsham and teacher at Chichester Academy in Sussex (1630-1638); Published 'An Idea of Mathematics' (1638); Professor of Mathematics at 'Gymnasium Illustre' in Amsterdam (1643); Professor of Philosophy and Mathematics at Breda (1646); Published 'A Refutation of Longomontanus' Pretended Quadrature of the Circle' (1646/7); Returned to England (1652); Cromwell's Envoy and then Resident at Zurich (1654-1658); Editor on Rahn's 'Teutsche Algebra' (1659); Ordained deacon and priest (1661); Rector of Fobbing, Essex (1661-1685); Vicar of Laindon and Basildon, Essex (1663-1685); Chaplain to Gilbert Sheldon, Archbishop of Canterbury (FRS 1665); Published 'A Table of Ten Thousand Square Numbers' (1672); Imprisoned for debt twice and given asylum at the Royal College of Physicians by Daniel Whistler (FRS 1663)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: On Council (c. 1676)</p>
      <p>Committee appointments included: Committee on mechanical and optical inventions (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee on reporting and conducting experiments on natural phenomena (1664)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster; Aubrey; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Noel Malcolm, 'The publications of John Pell, FRS (1611-1685): some new light and some old confusions' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 275-292</p>
      <p>Linda Levy Peck, 'Uncovering the Arundel Library at the Royal Society: Changing Meanings of Science and the Fate of the Norfolk Donation' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 3-24</p>
      <p>D J Bryden, 'Magnetic Inclinatory Needles: Approved by the Royal Society?' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 17-31</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'In this issue' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 245 - 247</p>
      <p>N Malcolm, 'An unpublished letter from Henry Oldenburg to Johann Heinrich Rahn' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 249 - 266</p>
      <p>S. Lawrence FIMA, 'Historical Notes: Pell's Contribution to Mathematics', 12 October 2018</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Pell's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously mentioned as a member on 24 December 1662.</p>
      <p>Index to BR offers alternative election date 13 August 1662.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>mathematician</term>
   </note>
</person>