<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8060">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Herschel</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1738 - 1822</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Hanover, Germany (15 November 1738)</p>
      <p>Death: Observatory House, Slough, Buckinghamshire (25 August 1822)</p>
      <p>Burial: Under the tower, Church of St Laurence, Upton, Buckinghamshire</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Astronomy</p>
      <p>Education: Hon LLD (1786, Edinburgh)</p>
      <p>Career: Oboist in the Hanoverian Foot Guards (from age 14); left Regiment and went to England (1757); music copyist, London; Director of Public Concerts, Leeds (1762); gave private music lessons; Organist for the new town organ, Halifax, but resigned shortly after (1766); Organist, Octagon Chapel, Bath (1766); began making astronomical obervations (1777); discovered the planet Uranus (13 March 1781); also discovered two of Uranus' moons, Titania and Oberon, and two of Saturn's moons; uniquely appointed King's Astronomer by George III; discovered infra-red heat; window commemorating him in Upton Church (unveiled 24 February 2001)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1816</p>
      <p>Memberships: Bath Philosophical Society (1779); FRAS (President 1821)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 6/12/1781</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1781</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>References: John Thomas, 'Josiah Wedgwood's Portrait Medallions of Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 45-53, plate</p>
      <p>John R Levene, 'Nevil Maskelyne, FRS, and the Discovery of Night Myopia' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 100-108</p>
      <p>Averil M Lysaght, 'Joseph Banks at Skara Brae and Stennis, Orkney, 1772' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 221-234</p>
      <p>Sir Bernard Lovell, 'Herschel's Work on the Structure of the Universe' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 57-75</p>
      <p>R V Jones, 'Through Music to the Stars. William Herschel, 1738-1822' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 37-56, plate</p>
      <p>Mari Williams, 'James Bradley and the Eighteenth Century "Gap" in Attempts to Measure Annual Stellar Parallax' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 83-100</p>
      <p>A A Mills and R Hall, 'The Production of a Plane Surface. As Illustrated by Specula From Some Early Newtonian Telescopes' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>Margaret Bullard, 'My Small Newtonian Sweeper - Where is it Now?' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 139-148</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Charles Babbage and his world' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 353-365</p>
      <p>W P Griffith and P J T Morris, 'Charles Hatchett FRS (1765 - 1847), chemist and discoverer of niobium' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 299 - 316</p>
      <p>M Bailey Ogilvie, 'In her place. Pandora's breeches: women, science and power in the enlightenment, by P Fara' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 314-315</p>
      <p>A Chapman, 'Sir William and Miss Caroline Herschel. 'The Herschel partnership, as viewed by Caroline' and 'Caroline Herschel's autobiographies' by M Hoskin' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 91-92</p>
      <p>Emily Winterburn, 'Philomaths, Herschel, and the Myth of Self-taught Man' in NR 2014, vol 68, no. 3, pp 207-225</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>astronomer</term>
   </note>
</person>