<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8022">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Vaughan</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>3rd Earl of Carbery</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1639 - 1713</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Baptism: St Dunstan's in the West, London, England, Europe (18 July 1639)</p>
      <p>Death: Chelsea, Middlesex, England, Europe (16 January 1713)</p>
      <p>Burial: St John the Baptist's chapel, Westminster Abbey, London, England, Europe (28 January 1713)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Politician; colonial governor</p>
      <p>Research field: Mathematics</p>
      <p>Education: Educated at home as a pupil of Jeremy Taylor DD and William Wyatt; Christ Church, Oxford (matriculated 1656); Inner Temple (admitted 1658)</p>
      <p>Career: Whig politician and supporter of Charles II; Commissioner for Militia, Carmarthenshire (1660); Deputy Lieutenant of Carmarthenshire (1660-1687?), and for South Wales (1685-1687?); Commissioner for Assessment for Carmarthenshire (1660-1680), and for Carmarthen (1663-1680); Gentleman of the Privy Chamber (1661-1674?); Member of the Council in the Marches of Wales (1661-1689); MP for Carmarthen (1661-1679); in Parliament, he defended Charles II's interests; aided in the impeachment of former Lord Chancellor the Earl of Clarendon (1667);MP for Carmarthenshire (1679-1681, 1685-1687), Colonel of a regiment of foot (1673-1674); Governor of Jamaica (1675-1678); charged with the supression of piracy, making piracy a capital offence (1677); facilitated the Royal African Company's slave trading into Jamaica; accused of selling his servants into slavery; friend and patron of John Dryden (FRS 1663); Lord of the Admiralty (1683-1684, 1689-1690); Governor of Milford Haven (1686-death); Custos Rotulorum for Carmarthenshire and Cardiganshire (1686-death); Vice-Admiral of South Wales (1689-death); built Gough House, Chelsea (c.1704).</p>
      <p>Honours: KB 1661</p>
      <p>Memberships: Kit-Cat Club</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 21/01/1685</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1686-1689; Council 1685, 1689</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Whilst in Jamaica (1675-1678), Vaughan corresponded with Henry Oldenburg (FRS 1663), Secretary of the Royal Society, and sent samples of production.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; ODNB; GEC; Hunter; Foster; Henning</p>
      <p>References: Anon., 'The history and state of Jamaica under Lord Vaughan', (manuscript, c.1678) National Library of Jamaica, available via the World Digital Library (Library of Congress/UNESCO, 2009-) https://www.wdl.org/en/item/7781/</p>
      <p>Frank Cundall, 'The governors of Jamaica in the seventeenth century' (London, 1936)</p>
      <p>Mark Govier, 'The Royal Society, Slavery and the Island of Jamaica: 1660-1700' in NR 1999 v.53 pp.203-217, plate.</p>
      <p>Notes: Vaughan was first elected on 20 March 1661, prior to the Society receiving its Royal Charter, and was not officially re-elected FRS of the incorporated Royal Society until the date stated above (21 January 1685). Vaughan is therefore not considered an original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the 1663 charter or elected within the subsequent two months, the period allowed in the charter for the declaration of Fellows. Elections such as Vaughan's, predating this, were no longer recognised. The date of any subsequent re-election is given in this database as the official election date.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>politician and colonial governor</term>
   </note>
</person>