<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8074">
   <persName>
      <forename>Christopher</forename>
      <surname>Merrett</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>? 1614 - 1695</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Winchcombe, Gloucestershire, England, Europe (16 February 1614)</p>
      <p>Death: Hatton Garden, London, England, Europe (19 August 1695)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Andrew's Church, Holborn, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: natural history; botany; glassmaking</p>
      <p>Education: Gloucester Hall, Oxford (matriculated 1632; BMed 1636, DMed 1643); Oriel College, Oxford (BA 1635)</p>
      <p>Career: Practised in London (1640-); Goulstonian lecturer at the Royal College of Physicians (1654); Keeper of library and museum at RCP (1654-1665); compiled first catalogue for the College (1660); Translated and expanded Antonio Neri's 'L'arte vertraria' [The Art of Glass] (1662); produced a new catalogue of British fauna, flora, and fossils (1667); published 'A Short View of the Frauds and Abuses Committed by Apothecaries' (1669)</p>
      <p>Memberships: FRCP (1651-1681)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: Sworn in Anniversary Day 1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for Agriculture (1664)</p>
      <p>Chairman of committee on history of trades</p>
      <p>Committee to extract [John] Evelyn's papers (1662)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Involved in botanical and natural history experiments (e.g. ingesting plants brought back by an emissary employed to collect specimens)</p>
      <p>Collated lists of chirurgical instruments for operations intended by the Society on dead bodies.</p>
      <p>Date of ejection/withdrawal: 22 July 1685 (due to non-payment)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; ODNB</p>
      <p>Authority: OtherFormsOfName from DNB</p>
      <p>References: Albert J Koinm, 'Christopher Merret's use of experiment' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 23-32</p>
      <p>Kathleen H Ochs, 'The Royal Society of London's History of Trades Programme: An Early Episode in Applied Science' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 129-158</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London and Oxford' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 157-168</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>W H G Armytage, 'The Royal Society and the Apothecaries' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 22-37</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>A C S, 'Notes on the Foundation and History of the Royal Society' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 32-36</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Merrett's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously mentioned as a member on 2 January 1661.</p>
      <p>Hunter gives birth date as 1615; 1614 possibly Old Style.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician and writer on natural philosophy</term>
   </note>
</person>