<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8032">
   <persName>
      <forename>Thomas</forename>
      <surname>Willis</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1621 - 1675</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Great Bedwyn, Wiltshire, England, Europe (27 January 1621)</p>
      <p>Baptism: St Mary the Virgin, Great Bedwyn, Wiltshire, England, Europe (14 February 1621)</p>
      <p>Death: St Martin's Lane, London, England, Europe (11 November 1675)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Medicine; anatomy</p>
      <p>Education: Edward Sylvester's School at Oxford; Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1639; MA 1642; BMed 1646; DMed 1660)</p>
      <p>Career: Assisted Mrs Iles, wife of one of the Canons of Christ Church, in making medicines; licensed to practice medicine (1646); practised in Oxford, opposite Merton College; Sedleian Professor of Natural Philosophy, University of Oxford (1660-1675); practised in London (1666-1675); discovered saccharine diabetes</p>
      <p>Memberships: Honorary Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians (1664)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 18/11/1663</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Correspondent to Henry Oldenburg (1667)</p>
      <p>Asked to contribute to the building of a Society College (1668)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; Aubrey; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Marie Boas Hall, 'Dispenser of Restoration Medicine', review of J Trevor Hughes, Thomas Willis 1621-1675: His Life and Work in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 141-142</p>
      <p>D R Oldroyd, 'Some "Philosophicall Scribbles" Attributed to Robert Hooke' in NR 1980 vol 35 pp 17-32</p>
      <p>Robert G Frank, Jr, 'John Aubrey, FRS, John Lydall, and Science at Commonwealth Oxford' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 193-217</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London and Oxford' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 157-168</p>
      <p>L G Wilson, 'William Croone's Theory of Muscular Contraction' in NR 1961 vol 16 pp 158-178</p>
      <p>Sir Charles Symonds, 'Thomas Willis, FRS (1621-1675)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 91-97, plate</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>L Jardine, 'The 2003 Wilkins Lecture: Dr Wilkins's boy wonders' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 107-129</p>
      <p>Notes: Admitted 13 November 1661 (JB).</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Willis was first elected on 13 November 1661 (JBO), prior to the Society receiving its Royal Charter and was not officially re-elected FRS of the incorporated Royal Society until the date stated above (18 November 1663) at which time the JBO states: 'Dr Willis was chosen, having been forgot to be chosen again, at the time, when, upon the Renewall of the Charter, the Councill, according to the power granted them therein, did receive and admitt in to the Society, such persons, as had been Election Date Fellows afore, upon the first Charter'. Willis is therefore not considered an original Fellow of the Royal Society, a classification reserved for those named in the 1663 charter or elected within the subsequent two months, the period allowed in the charter for the declaration of Fellows. Elections like Willis's that predated this were no longer recognised and had to be reconfirmed. The date of any subsequent re-election is given in this database as the official election date.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician and natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>