<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8006">
   <persName>
      <forename>Chandrasekhara Venkata</forename>
      <surname>Raman</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1888 - 1970</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Tiruchirapalli, Madras, India (07 November 1888)</p>
      <p>Death: Bangalore, India (21 November 1970)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics, physical theory, physiology of vision</p>
      <p>Education: Presidency College, Madras graduating with English and Physics as his subjects; attended Chennai University for BA first class (1904); MA with physics as main subject passed first class (1907); carried out research in college laboratory on the diffraction of light.</p>
      <p>Career: Deputy Accountant General in Calcutta; first research paper published in 'Proceedings of the Royal Society', and received his first international award, The Woodburn Reserch Medal. Invited to teach at Calcutta University by the Chancellor, Justice Sir Ashutosh Mukherjee. Awarded Doctorate (1921) Same year made first trip abroad. On his return sea voyage, he became interested in the blue waters of the ocean. His research on the scattering oflight led to the discovery of the effect known as the 'Raman Effect'. Director of Indian Institute of Science in Bangalore (1932-1970)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1929</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 15/05/1924</p>
      <p>Resigned as Fellow, resignation accepted 6 April 1968</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Hughes Medal 1930; Nobel Prize (Physics) 1930</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1971 vol 17 pp 565-592, plate, by S Bhagavantam</p>
      <p>References: J C D Brand, 'The Discovery of the Raman Effect' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 1-23, plate</p>
      <p>Gerhard Herzberg, 'A Leader of Indian Science', review of G Venkataraman, Journey Into Light: Life and Science of C V Raman in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 109-113</p>
      <p>S Ramaseshan, 'Dorothy Hodgkin and the Indian Connection' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 115-127</p>
      <p>D C V Mallik, 'The Raman effect and Krishnan's diary' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 67-83</p>
      <p>Rajinder Singh and Falk Riess, 'The 1930 Nobel Prize for Physics: a close decision?' in NR 2001 vol 55 pp 267-283</p>
      <p>S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra, 'C V Raman; A Pictorial Biography' 1988, Indian Academy of Sciences</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>R Singh and F Riess, 'The nobel laureate Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman FRS and his contacts with the British Scientific community in a social and political context' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 47-64</p>
      <p>R Singh 'India's Physics and Chemistry Nobel Prize nominators and nominees in colonial and international context' NR 2007 Vol 61 pp 333-346</p>
      <p>Notes: Resigned April 1968. See Kameshwar C. Wali, Chandra: a Biography of S. Chandrasekhar, p. 253. See also Council Minutes, 4 April 1968, item 20</p>
   </note>
</person>