<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8054">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Finch</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1626 - 1682</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: London, England, Europe (1626)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (18 November 1682)</p>
      <p>Burial: Christ's College chapel, Cambridge, England, Europe (in the same vault as Sir Thomas Baines FRS 1663) (November 1682)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research field: anatomy</p>
      <p>Education: Eton College; Mr Sylvester's School at Oxford; Christ's College, Cambridge (admitted 1645); Inner Temple (admitted 1644); Balliol College, Oxford (BA 1647); Incorporated at Cambridge (1647); MA (Cambridge 1649); Padua (MD 1660); Incorporated at Cambridge (1660)</p>
      <p>Career: English Consul at Padua and Syndic of the University; Professor of Anatomy at Pisa (1659-1665); Returned to England (1661); Minister to the Grand Duke of Tuscany (1665); Ambassador to Ottoman court in Constantinople (1672-1681); went on special mission to Adrianople (1675)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1661</p>
      <p>Memberships: Extra Fellow RCP (1661)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Mechanical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Nominated for the Committee to improve the English language (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Whilst in Italy and Turkey, Finch acted as the Royal Society correspondent in these areas.</p>
      <p>Tasked with enquiries into poisons while in Italy (1664).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Venn; Foster; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: R E W Maddison, 'The Accompt of William Balle from 28 November 1660 to 11 September 1663' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 174-183</p>
      <p>T L Underwood, 'Quakers and the Royal Society of London in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 133-150</p>
      <p>W E Knowles Middleton, 'Some Italian Visitors to the Early Royal Society' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 157-173</p>
      <p>Susana Gomez Lopez, 'The Royal Society and Post-Galilean Science in Italy' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 35-44</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Finch's election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician and diplomat</term>
   </note>
</person>