<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8001">
   <persName>
      <forename>Henry</forename>
      <surname>Oldenburg</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c1619 - 1677</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Free and imperial city of Bremen (c.1619)</p>
      <p>Death: Pall Mall, London, England, Europe (5 September 1677)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Mary the Virgin, Bexley, England, Europe (7 September 1677)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Administrator</p>
      <p>Publisher</p>
      <p>Translator</p>
      <p>Education: Paedegogium Bremen (-1633); Gymnasium illustre in Bremen (MTh 1639); Oxford (entered 1656)</p>
      <p>Career: Tutor to variety of both royalist and parliamentary men across Europe and England (1641-1653); Envoy to England to negotiate recognition of Bremen's neutrality (1653); Tutor to the Honywood family in Kent (1654-1655); Tutor to Henry, son of Barnabas O'Brien, 6th Earl of Thomond, and Richard Jones (FRS 1663), son of Robert Boyle's sister, Catherine, Lady Ranelagh (1656); accompanied Jones to France and Germany (1657-1660); acted as publisher to Robert Boyle; published 'Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society' (1665-1677); imprisoned in the Tower of London on suspicion that his extensive foreign correspondence was political, rather than scientific (20 June 1667-26 August 1667); worked as a translator (1670)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 22/04/1663</p>
      <p>Council: Secretary 1663-1677</p>
      <p>Editor of 'Philosophical Transactions' 1665-1677</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee to consider of Mr Buckland's proposition to plant potatoes through all the parts of England (1662)</p>
      <p>Committee for Correspondence (c.1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Agriculture [Georgics] (c.1664)</p>
      <p>Mechanical Committee (c.1664)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Shaw LD</p>
      <p>Notes: Hall and Hall give birth date between 1617 and 1620; Hunter, and DSB, give 1618; DNB and index to BR give c 1615. Hunter gives a possible election date as 26 December 1660. A note in index to BR says 'Hooke's diary for death date'. Possible death dates of 5 or 17 September 1677 (earlier from DSB). DSB gives place of death as London. It seems that Oldenburg's wife died on 17 September 1677.</p>
      <p>References: H W Robinson, 'Gleanings from the Library - I. A Note on the Early Minutes' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 92-95</p>
      <p>C S S, 'The Society's Library' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 21-27</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'Henry Oldenburg, FRS (c. 1615-1677)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 183-197, plate</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'What Happened to the Latin Edition of Boyle's History of Cold?' in NR 1962 vol 17 pp 32-35</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'Some Hitherto Unknown Facts about the Private Career of Henry Oldenburg' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 94-103</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>Christopher Hill, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society - London or Oxford?' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 144-156</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'Further Notes on Henry Oldenburg' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 33-42</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society's Role in the Diffusion of Information in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 173-192</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'A "College" for the Royal Society: The Abortive Plan of 1667-1668' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 159-186</p>
      <p>Kathleen H Ochs, 'The Royal Society of London's History of Trades Programme: An Early Episode in Applied Science' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 129-158</p>
      <p>Charles A Rivington, 'Early Printers to the Royal Society 1663-1708' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 1-27</p>
      <p>Laurel Brodsley, Sir Charles Frank and John W Steeds, 'Prince Rupert's Drops' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 1-26</p>
      <p>P B Wood, 'Hevelius's Business: An Unpublished Letter from Henry Oldenburg to the Earl of Tweeddale' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 25-29</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'Additions and Corrections to The Correspondence of Henry Oldenburg' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 143-150</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'The 350th Anniversary of the Birth of G W Leibniz, FRS' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 153-163</p>
      <p>Susana Gomez Lopez, 'The Royal Society and Post-Galilean Science in Italy' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 35-44</p>
      <p>Iordan Avramov, 'An Apprenticeship in Scientific Communication: the Early Correspondence of Henry Oldenburg (1656-63)' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 187-201, plate</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Our Foreign Correspondence' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 179-182</p>
      <p>Marta Cavazza, 'The Institute of Science of Bologna and the Royal Society in the eighteenth century' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 3-25, plate</p>
      <p>R Lewis, 'The publication of John Wilkins's Essay (1668): some contextual considerations' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp133-146</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 1. 1731-1847' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 307-332</p>
      <p>S Mandelbrote, 'From Bremen to Pall Mall. Henry Oldenburg. Shaping The Royal Society, by M B Hall' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 389-390</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>H Gest, 'The Discovery of Microorganisms by Robert Hooke and Antoni von Leeuwenhoek, Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 187-201</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'In this issue' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 245 - 247</p>
      <p>N Malcolm, 'An unpublished letter from Henry Oldenburg to Johann Heinrich Rahn' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 249 - 266</p>
      <p>J Gribbin, 'The Fellowship', 2005, pp154-157</p>
      <p>A M Roos ''Magic Coins' and Magic Squares': the discovery of astrological sigils in the Oldenburg Letters.' in NR 2008 vol 62 pp 271-288</p>
      <p>Ana Maria Alfonso-Goldfarb, Marcia Helena Mendes Ferraz, Piyo M Rattansi, 'Seventeenth Century "Treasure" found in Royal Society Archives: the 'LUDUS HELMONTII and the stone disease' in NR 2014, vol 68. no 3, pp 227-243</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Oldenburg's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 26 December 1660.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>scientific correspondent</term>
   </note>
</person>