<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8062">
   <persName>
      <forename>Christian</forename>
      <surname>Huygens</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1629 -  1695</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: The Hague, Netherlands, Europe (14 April 1629)</p>
      <p>Death: The Hague, Netherlands, Europe (8 July 1695)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics; mathematics; astronomy; optics</p>
      <p>Education: Taught by his father; University of Leyden (1645-1647); Collegium Arausiacum [College of Orange] at Breda (1647-1649); University of Angers (LLD, 1655)</p>
      <p>Career: Travelled to Denmark in group of diplomats (1649); published 'Cyclometriae' (1651); published 'De Circuli Magnitudine' (1654); discovered the first moon of Saturn (1655); published 'De Ratiociniis in Ludo Aleae' on probability (1656); discovered the shape of the rings of Saturn (1656); patented first pendulum clock (1656) and continued to build them to determine longitude at sea; published 'Systema Saturnium' (1659) regarding the rings of Saturn; published 'Horologium Oscillatorium sive de motu pendulorum' (1673) on the theory of pendulum motion; travelled to London (1661); found error in Descartes' law on impact and worked on the collision of elastic bodies (1668); worked with Académie Royale des Sciences (1666-); published his work on the wave theory of light, 'Traité de la lumiere' (1678); travelled back to England (1689); started work on one of the earliest discussions of extraterrestrial life, 'Cosmotheoros' (1698)</p>
      <p>Memberships: Académie Royale des Sciences (1665; first foreigner to become a member)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 22/06/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Mechanical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Astronomical and Optical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Frequent correspondent to European natural philosophers.</p>
      <p>Regularly reported on and produced experiments on a wide variety of topics.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB; Biographie Universelle</p>
      <p>Authority: Name from Hunter; altname from Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>References: D T Whiteside, 'The Prehistory of the Principia from 1664 to 1686' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 11-61</p>
      <p>H A M Snelders, 'Christiaan Huygens and Newton's Theory of Gravitation' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 209-222</p>
      <p>J H Leopold, 'Clockmaking in Britain and the Netherlands' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 155-165</p>
      <p>A R Hall, 'The Leeuwenhoek Lecture, 1988. Antoni van Leeuwenhoek 1632-1723' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 249-273</p>
      <p>D S Landes, 'The Wilkins Lecture, 1988. Hand and Mind in Time Measurement: the Contributions of Art and Science' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 57-69</p>
      <p>A R Hall, 'Chairman's Remarks' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 97-98</p>
      <p>A E Shapiro, 'Huygens' Traite de la Lumiere and Newton's Opticks: Pursuing and Eschewing Hypotheses' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 223-247</p>
      <p>E A Fellmann, 'The Principia and Continental Mathematicians' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 13-34</p>
      <p>Laurel Brodsley, Sir Charles Frank and John W Steeds, 'Prince Rupert's Drops' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 1-26</p>
      <p>A A Mills and R Hall, 'The Production of a Plane Surface. As Illustrated by Specula From Some Early Newtonian Telescopes' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>Simon Schaffer, 'Halley's Atheism and the End of the World' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 17-40</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society's Role in the Diffusion of Information in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 173-192</p>
      <p>Albert Van Helden, 'Christopher Wren's De Corpore Saturni' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 213-229</p>
      <p>E Faure-Fremiet, 'Les Origines de l'Academie des Sciences de Paris' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 20-31</p>
      <p>J E McGuire and P M Rattansi, 'Newton and the "Pipes of Pan"' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 108-143</p>
      <p>J A Lohne, 'Isaac Newton: the Rise of a Scientist 1661-1671' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 125-139</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'Henry Oldenburg, FRS (c 1615-1677)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 183-197</p>
      <p>Angus Armitage, 'William Ball, FRS (1627-1690)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 167-172</p>
      <p>H W Robinson, 'Gleanings from the Library - I. A Note on the Early Minutes' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 92-95</p>
      <p>S Mandelbrote, 'From Bremen to Pall Mall. Henry Oldenburg. Shaping The Royal Society, by M B Hall' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 389-390</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Gases and liquids. How fluids unmix: discoveries by the school of Van der Waals and Kamerlingh Onnes, by J L Sengers' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 255-256</p>
      <p>H Gest, 'The Discovery of Microorganisms by Robert Hooke and Antoni von Leeuwenhoek, Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 187-201</p>
      <p>S Van Damme, 'The Dutch Galileo? The Greatness of Huygens' Science. 'Huygens The man begind the principle' by C D Andriesse translated by Sally Miedema', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 219-220</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Huygens' election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows.</p>
      <p>Various possible death dates: DSB gives 08 Jul 1695, index to BR gives 08 June 1695, BR gives 08 Jul 1693, Hunter gives 1695.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>