<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8116">
   <persName>
      <forename>Joseph</forename>
      <surname>Banks</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1744 - 1820</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Argyle Street, London, England (13 February 1744)</p>
      <p>Death: His house at Spring Grove, Isleworth (19 June 1820)</p>
      <p>Burial Place: Parish church, Isleworth</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Botany</p>
      <p>Education: By private tutor then Harrow School; Eton School; entered Christ Church College, Oxford in 1760 where his interest in botany prompted him to procure a teacher in this field for the students. Matriculated as gentleman commoner from Christ Church, Oxford (1760) but left without taking a degree. DCL (1771, Oxon)</p>
      <p>Career: Made a botanical expedition collecting plants and other specimens with his Etonian friend Lieutenant Constantine Phipps RN to Labrador and Newfoundland (1766); took part in Captain James Cook's first great expedition to view the Transit of Venus and subsequent circumnavigation of the world in HMS Endeavour. Voyaged to Iceland (1772).</p>
      <p>Sailed with Cook's expedition in the "Endeavour", with Daniel Solander (FRS 1764) as one of his assistants (1768-1771) to explore the unchartered lands of the South Pacific, circumnavigating the globe visiting South America, Tahiti, New Zealand, Australia and Java; in New Zealand (1769-1770), collecting specimens including vines, fruit trees, melberry trees for silk worms; Banks and Solander visited the Hebrides and Iceland together (1772); Privy Councillor (1797). His collections and library passed to the then British Museum after his death.</p>
      <p>Memberships: Freemason, member, 1767, Old Horn Lodge No 2 at Fleece Tavern, Tothill Street, London, later Royal Somerset House and Inverness Lodge No 4(1766)</p>
      <p>Honours: Bt 1781; KCB 1795</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 01/05/1766</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1778-1820</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>References: Gudrun Richardson, 'A Norfolk Network within the Royal Society' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 27-39, plate</p>
      <p>Marta Cavazza, 'The Institute of Science of Bologna and the Royal Society in the eighteenth century' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 3-25, plate</p>
      <p>Sir John Craig, 'The Royal Society and the Royal Mint' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 156-167</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer and Max H Hey, 'The First Ascent of Mont Blanc' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 236-255</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'A Note on the Origin of the Society's Conversaziones' in NR 1958 vol 13 pp 61-63</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison and Raymond E Maddison, 'Spring Grove, the Country House of Sir Joseph Banks, Bart., PRS' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 91-99</p>
      <p>L F Gilbert, 'The Election to the Presidency of the Royal Society in 1820' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 256-279</p>
      <p>John Thomas, 'Josiah Wedgwood's Portrait Medallions of Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 45-53, plate</p>
      <p>G R de Beer, 'The Relations between Fellows of the Royal Society and French Men of Science when France and Britain were at War' in NR 1952 vol 9 pp 244-299, plate</p>
      <p>A D Atkinson, 'Dr Johnson and the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 131-138</p>
      <p>David E Allen, 'Man of the World', review of R E R Banks et al, eds, Sir Joseph Banks: A Global Perspective in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 336-337, plate</p>
      <p>Garry J Tee, 'Relics of Davy and Faraday in New Zealand' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 93-102</p>
      <p>Harold B Carter, 'The Royal Society and the Voyage of HMS Endeavour 1768-71' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 245-260</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Enlightening of Science', review of John Gascoigne, Joseph Banks and the English Enlightenment: Useful Knowledge and Polite Culture in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 258-260, plate</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Portland Vase: Sir William Hamilton, Josiah Wedgwood and the Darwins' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 237-259, plate</p>
      <p>Neil Chambers, 'Letters From the President: the Correspondence of Sir Joseph Banks' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 27-57, plate</p>
      <p>Patricia Fara, 'The Royal Society's Portrait of Joseph Banks' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 199-210, plate</p>
      <p>Sarah Meer, 'Servant of the State, Promoter of Empire', review of John Gascoigne, Science in the Service of Empire: Joseph Banks, the British State and the Uses of Science in the Age of Revolution in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 372-373</p>
      <p>M Yakup Bektas and Maurice Crosland, 'The Copley Medal: the Establishment of a Reward System in the Royal Society, 1731-1839' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 43-76</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, review of Marie Boas Hall, All Scientists Now: the Royal Society in the Nineteenth Century in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 133-134</p>
      <p>David E Allen, 'Banks in Full Flower', essay review in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 119-124</p>
      <p>A W Skempton, 'The Publication of Smeaton's Reports' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 135-155</p>
      <p>Averil Lysaght, 'A Letter From Sydney Parkinson in Batavia to Dr John Fothergill' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 79-81</p>
      <p>Averil M Lysaght, 'Joseph Banks at Skara Brae and Stennis, Orkney, 1772' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 221-234</p>
      <p>Averil M Lysaght, 'Some Early Letters from Joseph Banks (1743-1820) to William Phelp Perrin (1742-1820)' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 91-99</p>
      <p>Egon H Kodicek and Frank G Young, 'Captain Cook and Scurvy' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 43-63</p>
      <p>G N Cantor, 'Thomas Young's Lectures at the Royal Institution' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 87-112</p>
      <p>Garland Cannon, 'Sir William Jones, Sir Joseph Banks, and the Royal Society' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 205-230</p>
      <p>Maurice Crosland, 'Explicit Qualifications as a Criterion for Membership of the Royal Society: A Historical Review' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 167-187</p>
      <p>Sir Raphael Cilento, 'Sir Joseph Banks, FRS, and the Naming of the Kangaroo' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 157-161</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'Edmond Halley and the Clubs of the Royal Society' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 195-205</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'The Thursday's Club Called the Club of the Royal Philosophers, and its Relation to the Royal Society Club' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 73-80</p>
      <p>Trevor H Levere, 'Dr Thomas Beddoes and the Establishment of His Pneumatic Institution: A Tale of Three Presidents' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 41-49</p>
      <p>Trevor H Levere, 'Friendship and Influence: Martinus van Marum, FRS' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 113-120</p>
      <p>William T Stearn, 'A Royal Society Appointment with Venus in 1769: the Voyage of Cook and Banks in the Endeavour in 1768-1771 and its Botanical Results' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 64-90</p>
      <p>Patricia Fara, 'Letters from a scientific emperor', review of Neil Chambers, 'The letters of Sir Joseph Banks: a selection 1768 - 1829' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 264-265</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'A Roman tercentenary' by A Cook in NR 2002 vol 56 p273</p>
      <p>L B Glyn, 'Israel Lyons: a short but starry career. The life of an eighteenth-century Jewish botanist and astronomer' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 275-305</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 1. 1731-1847' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 307-332</p>
      <p>K K Schwarz, 'Faraday and Babbage' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp367-381</p>
      <p>J Corden, 'Web of Science History' project in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 383-388</p>
      <p>N G Coley, 'George Pearson MD, FRS (1751-1828): 'The greatest chemist in England'? in NR 2003 vol 57 pp</p>
      <p>161-175</p>
      <p>W P Griffith and P J T Morris, 'Charles Hatchett FRS (1765 - 1847), chemist and discoverer of niobium' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 299 - 316</p>
      <p>D Carr Agnew, 'Robert Fitzroy and the myth of 'Marsden Square': Transatlantic rivalries in early marine meteorology' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 21-46</p>
      <p>T Fulford, D Lee and P J Kitson, 'Sir Joseph Banks and his networks' in 'Literatue, Science and Exploration in the Romantic Era: Bodies of Knowledge' (CUP), 2004</p>
      <p>M Crosland, 'Relationships between the Royal Society and the Academie des Sciences in the late eighteenth century' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 25-34</p>
      <p>S G Perceval 'Journal of an Excursion to Eastbury adn Bristol etc in May and June 1767' in Proceedings of the Bristol Naturalists Society, NS 9 (1899) page 6 et seq.</p>
      <p>N A Chambers 'The So ciety of Arts and Joseph Banks: a first step in London's learned society' NR 2007 vol 61 pp313-326</p>
      <p>'Freemasons and the Royal Society: Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were Masons' Library and Museum of Freemasonry, 2010, page 7</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Deposited papers: Cambridge University Library, Department of Manuscripts and University Arvhives - 2 journals in a volume of 94 folios, entitled 'Journal of an Excursion to Eastbury and Bristol etc in May and June 1767' and 'Journal of an excursion to Wales etc 1767-8' Ref. MS.Add.6294. Volume sold at Sotheby's in 1886. Bought from the original purchaser, John W Ford of Enfiled in 1887 by Spencer George Perceval and presented to CUL in 1921.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>naturalist</term>
   </note>
</person>