<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8174">
   <persName>
      <forename>John Douglas</forename>
      <surname>Cockcroft</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1897 - 1967</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Todmorden, Yorkshire, England (27 May 1897)</p>
      <p>Death: Cambridge, Cambridgeshire (18 September 1967)</p>
      <p>Buried: St Giles' cemetery, now Ascension Cemetery, Cambridge</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics, electrical engineering</p>
      <p>Education: Career;</p>
      <p>A Signaller in First Wordl War. Apprenticed with Metropolitan Vickers, while he attained a Manster of Science in Technology, before going to St John's College in Cambridge where he took the mathematics tripos in 1924. At the Cavendish Laboratory under Sir Ernest Rutherford, with E T S Watson developed the high voltage particle accelerator machine which brought him fame. Assisted witht he development of radar in the Second World War. From 1943 involved with the development of the atomic bomb, and went to Canada to direct a British, Canadian and French team. After the war became Director of Harwell, Britain's peacetime atomic energy research programme. First reactor for producing nuclear energy for the national grid opened at Calder Hall in 1953.</p>
      <p>Honours: CBE 1944; Kt 1948; KCB 1953; OM 1957</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 7/05/1936</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Hughes Medal 1938; Royal Medal 1954; Nobel Prize (Physics) 1951</p>
      <p>Lectures: Rutherford 1952</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1968 vol 14 pp 139-188, plate, by M L E Oliphant and Penney</p>
      <p>References: Robert Spence, 'Address at the Service of Memorial and Thanksgiving for Sir John Cockcroft, OM, KCB, FRS at Westminster Abbey on 17 October 1967' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 31-32</p>
      <p>J B Adams, 'Four Generations of Nuclear Physicists' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 75-94</p>
      <p>Sir Harrie Massey, 'Nuclear Physics Today and in Rutherford's Day' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 25-44</p>
      <p>W E Burcham, 'The Cavendish High-Voltage Laboratory 1935-39' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 121-134</p>
      <p>F R N Nabarro, 'A scientist of the Commonwealth. Schonland, scientist and soldier, by B Austin' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 396-398</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'The war time work of Hinshelwood and his colleagues' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 161-175</p>
      <p>Notes: Appears in DSB under Cockroft, also in R. Source for death date BM 18, p145 and DSB. Index to BR gives 17 Sep 1967.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Knight Physicist</term>
   </note>
</person>