<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8137">
   <persName>
      <forename>Robert</forename>
      <surname>Boyle</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1627 - 1691</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Lismore Castle, Munster, Ireland, Europe (25 January 1627)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (30 December 1691)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Martin-in-the-Fields, Westminster, London, England, Europe (7 January 1692)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: natural philosophy; physics; chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: Eton College (1635-1638)</p>
      <p>Career: Travelled to Geneva with his tutor Marcombes, and his brother Francis (1638-1640), and to Italy (1641-1642); returned to Geneva; moved back to London (1644), then to the manor of Stallbridge, Dorset (1645); worked on 'Aretology' (1645-46); took part in the 'Invisible College' (1646-47); set up a laboratory at Stalbridge (1649); published 'Some Considerations Touching the Style of the Holy Scriptures' (1661); visited his Irish estates (1652-1653), where with the help of Sir William Petty FRS he engaged in anatomical dissection; published 'Certain Physiological Essays' (1661); 'The Sceptical Chymist' (1661); while at Oxford wrote the bulk of 'Some Considerations Touching the Usefulness of Experimental Natural Philosophy (1663, 1671); member of the Council of Foreign Plantations (1661-1664); Governor of the Corporation for the Spread of the Gospel in new England (1662-1689); governor of the New England Company; paid for the translation of the Bible into Arabic and several other languages (1685-1686); Director of the Honorable East India Company</p>
      <p>Honours: Doctor of Physic (Oxford, 1665)</p>
      <p>Lectures: Boyle Lectures</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Founder Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 28/11/1660</p>
      <p>Council: 1660 and declined Presidency of the Royal Society (1680)</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee to consider of Mr Buckland's proposition to plant potatoes through all the parts of England (1662)</p>
      <p>Committee for Agriculture (c. 1664)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; Aubrey</p>
      <p>References: W H G Armytage, 'The Royal Society and the Apothecaries' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 22-37</p>
      <p>Sir Irvine Masson and A J Youngson, 'Sir William Petty, FRS (1623-1687)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 79-90</p>
      <p>Robert Birley, 'Robert Boyle's Head Master at Eton' in NR 1958 vol 13 pp 104-114</p>
      <p>Robert Birley, 'Robert Boyle at Eton' in NR 1959 vol 14 p 191</p>
      <p>Richard A Hunter and Ida Macalpine, 'William Harvey and Robert Boyle' in NR 1958 vol 13 pp 115-127</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'A Guide to the Archives of the Royal Society and to other Manuscripts in its Possession' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 21-39</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'Studies in the Life of Robert Boyle, FRS. Part V. Boyle's Operator: Ambrose Godfrey Hanckwitz, FRS' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 159-188</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'Studies in the Life of Robert Boyle, FRS. Part IV. Robert Boyle and Some of his Foreign Visitors' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 38-53</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'Studies in the Life of Robert Boyle, FRS. Part III. The Charitable Disposal of Robert Boyle's Residuary Estate' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 15-27</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'A Tentative Index of the Correspondence of the Honourable Robert Boyle, FRS' in NR 1958 vol 13 pp 128-201</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'Henry Oldenburg, FRS (c. 1615-1677)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 183-197</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'Studies in the Life of Robert Boyle, FRS. Part VII. The Grand Tour' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 51-77</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'Studies in the Life of Robert Boyle, FRS. Part VI. The Stalbridge Period, 1645-1655, and the Invisible College' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 104-124</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'What Happened to the Latin Edition of Boyle's History of Cold?' in NR 1962 vol 17 pp 32-35</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'Henry Miles, FRS (1698-1763) and Thomas Birch, FRS (1705-66)' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 39-44</p>
      <p>Margaret Deacon, 'Founders of Marine Science in Britain: the Work of the Early Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 28-50</p>
      <p>L M Payne, Leonard G Wilson and Sir Harold Hartley, 'William Croone, FRS (1633-1684)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 211-219</p>
      <p>Kenneth Dewhurst, 'Locke's Contribution to Boyle's Researches on the Air and on Human Blood' in NR 1962 vol 17 pp 198-206</p>
      <p>John F Fulton, 'The Honourable Robert Boyle, FRS (1627-1692)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 119-135, plate</p>
      <p>J A Lohne, 'Isaac Newton: the Rise of a Scientist 1661-1671' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 125-139</p>
      <p>H A Feisenberger, 'The Libraries of Newton, Hooke and Boyle' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 42-55</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'The Origins and Foundation of the Royal Society of London' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 1-37</p>
      <p>A D Atkinson, 'The Royal Society and English Vocabulary' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 40-43</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'Some Hitherto Unknown Facts about the Private Career of Henry Oldenburg</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and Marie Boas Hall, 'Further Notes on Henry Oldenburg' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 33-42</p>
      <p>C S S, 'The Society's Library' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 21-27</p>
      <p>A C S, 'Notes on the Foundation and History of the Royal Society' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 32-36</p>
      <p>John Hedley Brooke, 'Wise men nowadays think otherwise': John Ray, natural theology and the meanings of anthropocentrism' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 199-213</p>
      <p>Marco Beretta, 'At the source of Western science: the organization of experimentalism at the Accadmeia del Cimento (1657-1667)' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 131-151</p>
      <p>Quentin Bone, 'Favourite or Outsider?', review of George Bartle, An Old Radical and his Brood and Joyce Youings, ed, Sir John Bowring, 1792-1872: Aspects of his Life and Career in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 142-144, plate</p>
      <p>Colin A Russell, 'The Secret Alchemist', review of L M Principe, The Aspiring Adept: Robert Boyle and his Alchemical Quest in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 371-372</p>
      <p>Guy Meynell, 'Locke, Boyle and Peter Stahl' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 185-192</p>
      <p>Iordan Avramov, 'An Apprenticeship in Scientific Communication: the Early Correspondence of Henry Oldenburg (1656-63)' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 187-201</p>
      <p>Lawrence M Principe, 'Newly Discovered Boyle Documents in the Royal Society Archive: Alchemical Tracts and his Student Notebook' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 57-70</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'Boyle Anatomized', review of Michael Hunter, ed, Robert Boyle by Himself and his Friends with a Fragment of William Wotton's Lost "Life of Boyle" in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 334-335, plate</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Ladies in the Scientific Revolution' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 1-12</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'Frederick Slare, FRS (1648-1727)' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 23-41</p>
      <p>Simon Schaffer, 'The Glorious Revolution and Medicine in Britain and the Netherlands' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 167-190</p>
      <p>Stephen F Mason, 'A Theosophical Boyle?', review of Michael Hunter, ed, Robert Boyle Reconsidered in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 317-319, plate</p>
      <p>Kathleen H Ochs, 'The Royal Society of London's History of Trades Programme: An Early Episode in Applied Science' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 129-158</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'Boyle's Method of Work: Promoting His Corpuscular Philosophy' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 111-143</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>P M Rattansi, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 129-143</p>
      <p>Penelope M Gouk, 'Acoustics in the Early Royal Society 1660-1680' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 155-175</p>
      <p>Robert G Frank, Jr, 'John Aubrey, FRS, John Lydall, and Science at Commonwealth Oxford' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 193-217</p>
      <p>W E Knowles Middleton, 'Some Italian Visitors to the Early Royal Society' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 157-173</p>
      <p>R Lewis, 'The publication of John Wilkins's Essay (1668): some contextual considerations' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp133-146</p>
      <p>S Mandelbrote, 'From Bremen to Pall Mall. Henry Oldenburg. Shaping The Royal Society, by M B Hall' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 389-390</p>
      <p>A Cook, '1703 and other anniversaries' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 1-2</p>
      <p>N J W Thrower, 'Samuel Pepys FRS (1633-1733) and The Royal Society' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 3-13</p>
      <p>W Hayes, 'Physics as well as poetry. Physicists of Ireland, edited by M McCartney and A Whitaker' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 245-246</p>
      <p>J H Appleby, 'The founding of St Petersburg in the context of the Royal Society's relationship with Russia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 273-284</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>L Jardine, 'The 2003 Wilkins Lecture: Dr Wilkins's boy wonders' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 107-129</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Displacing Phlogiston. Robert Siegfried, From elements to atoms: a history of chemical composition' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 242-243</p>
      <p>M Hunter, 'Report. Robert Boyle for the 21st Century' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 87-90</p>
      <p>J Gribbin, 'The Fellowship', 2005, pp141-147</p>
      <p>A M Roos 'Hunting Robert Boyle: Michael Hunter and Boyle's life and letters ' - Essay review of 'Boyle: etween God and science' 2009, Yale University Press. In NR 2011 vol 65 pp 311-315</p>
      <p>D T Burns ' Previously unrecorded Dutch citations and versions of some of the scientific publications of Robert Boyle FRS' NR 2011 vol 65 pp 295-300</p>
      <p>Notes: See also: http://www.bbk.ac.uk/boyle</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher and chemist</term>
   </note>
</person>