<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8167">
   <persName>
      <forename>Walter</forename>
      <surname>Charleton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1620 - 1707</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Parsonage House, Shepton Mallett, Somerset, England, Europe (2 February 1620)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (24 April 1707)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Natural philosophy; medicine; chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: Educated by his father; Magdalen Hall, Oxford (matriculated 1635; MD 1643)</p>
      <p>Career: Physician-in-ordinary to Charles I and Charles II; occasional assistant to senior Royal Physician Sir Theodore Turquet de Mayerne; practised in London (1650-1691); published 'A Ternary of Paradoxes', 'Deliramenta catarrhi', and 'Spiritus gorgonicus' (1650); published his work 'Physiologia Epicuro-Gassendo-Charltoniana; or, A fabrick of science natural upon the hypothesis of atoms, founded by Epicurus, repaired by Petrus Gassendus, augmented by Walter Charleton' (1654); appointed physician-in-ordinary to exiled Charles II; Harveian orator (1680; 1705); retired to Nantwich, Cheshire (1692); returned to London and was appointed College of Physician's Harveian librarian (1706)</p>
      <p>Memberships: Royal College of Physicians (Honorary Fellow 1664; Fellow 1676-1677; President 1689-1691)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Anatomical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Collecting all the Phenomena of Nature hitherto observed (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Proposed on 23 January 1661</p>
      <p>Involved in thermal and poison-related experiments and observations (1661).</p>
      <p>Interested in echoes and sonic phenomena, in particular in relation to the whispering gallery at Gloucester Cathedral (1662).</p>
      <p>Wrote a paper on the fulmination of Gold and on the velocity of sounds (1662).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Munk's Roll; Foster; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Robert Kargon, 'Walter Charleton, Robert Boyle, and the Acceptance of Epicurean Atomism in England', in Isis, 1964, vol 55(2), pp 184-192</p>
      <p>Horne, R. A, 'Review of Physiologia. Epicuro-Gassendo-Charltoniana: Or a Fabrick of Science Natural, upon the Hypothesis of Atoms, Founded by Epicurus, Repaired by Petrus Gessendus, Augmented by Walter Charleton, by W. Charleton', in Isis, 1967, vol 58(2), pp 270–271</p>
      <p>P M Rattansi, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 129-143</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>Penelope M Gouk, 'Acoustics in the Early Royal Society 1660-1680' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 155-175</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Charleton's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 15 May 1661.</p>
      <p>Name spelt 'Charleton' in DNB, DSB and by Michael Hunter. Alternative birth and death dates (13 Feb, 6 May) provided by DSB. Birth date given as 1619 in Munk.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician and natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>