<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8196">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles Robert</forename>
      <surname>Darwin</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1809 - 1882</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 'The Mount', Shrewsbury, Shropshire, England (09 or 12 February 1809)</p>
      <p>Death: Down, Kent (19 April 1882)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Natural history, geology, evolution</p>
      <p>Education: School at Shrewbury; Edinburgh University (medicine); Christ's College, Cambridge. BA (1831); MA</p>
      <p>Career: Naturalist to HMS Beagle (1831-1836), including visit to New Zealand (1835); published "The origin of species" (1859) and other works</p>
      <p>Memberships: Hon RSNZ (1871)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 24/01/1839</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1864; Royal Medal 1853</p>
      <p>Council: VP 1854-1856</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1888 vol 44 pp i-xxv signed by T H H</p>
      <p>References: W B Turrill, 'Joseph Dalton Hooker, FRS (1817-1911)' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 109-120</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer, 'Mendel, Darwin, and Fisher: Addendum' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 64-71</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer, 'Mendel, Darwin, and Fisher (1865-1965)' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 192-226</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer, ed, 'Some Unpublished Letters of Charles Darwin' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 12-66, plate</p>
      <p>Sir Edward Salisbury, 'Epilogue' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 139-141</p>
      <p>Sir Edward Bailey, 'Charles Lyell, FRS (1797-1875)' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 121-138</p>
      <p>Nora Barlow, 'Erasmus Darwin, FRS (1731-1802)' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 85-98</p>
      <p>John Thomas, 'Josiah Wedgwood's Portrait Medallions of Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 45-53, plate</p>
      <p>H J Habakkuk, 'Thomas Robert Malthus, FRS (1766-1834)' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 99-108</p>
      <p>Fred Somkin, 'The Contributions of Sir John Lubbock, FRS to the Origin of Species: Some Annotations to Darwin' in NR 1962 vol 17 pp 183-191</p>
      <p>C F A Pantin, 'Alfred Russel Wallace, FRS, and His Essays of 1858 and 1855' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 67-84</p>
      <p>J W Haas, 'The Reverend Dr William Henry Dallinger, FRS (1839-1909)' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 53-65</p>
      <p>John Hedley Brooke, 'Wise men nowadays think otherwise': John Ray, natural theology and the meanings of anthropocentrism' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 199-213</p>
      <p>Gregory Estes, K Thalia Grant and Peter R Grant, 'Darwin in the Galapagos: his footsteps through the Archipelago' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 343-368</p>
      <p>Alan Grafen, 'Darwin in 1862', review of The Correspondence of Charles Darwin, volume 10, 1862, ed. Frederick Burkhardt et al., in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 175-176</p>
      <p>Brian J Ford, 'Shining Through the Centuries: John Ray's Life and Legacy. A Report of the Meeting "John Ray and his Successors"' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 5-22</p>
      <p>D A B Young, 'Darwin's Illness and Systemic Lupus Erythematosus' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 77-86, plate</p>
      <p>David C Watt, 'Lionel Penrose, FRS (1898-1972) and Eugenics: Part One' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 137-151</p>
      <p>Desmond King-Hele, 'The 1997 Wilkins Lecture: Erasmus Darwin, the Lunaticks and Evolution' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 153-180</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Personality of Isaac Newton' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 1-56</p>
      <p>Richard D Keynes, 'Darwin's Bulldog', review of Adrian Desmond, Huxley: The Devil's Disciple in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 345-347</p>
      <p>Richard D Keynes, 'From the Beagle to Down House', review of Charles Darwin's Letters. A Selection 1825-1859, ed. Frederick Burkhardt, in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 149-150</p>
      <p>Richard D Keynes, 'The Evolution of a Theory', review of Janet Browne, Charles Darwin Voyaging in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 129-136, plate</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Portland Vase: Sir William Hamilton, Josiah Wedgwood and the Darwins' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 237-259, plate</p>
      <p>Joan Mason, 'Women in Science: Breaking Out of the Circle', essay review in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 177-182</p>
      <p>John Postgate, 'Evolution in Perspective', review of Peter J Bowler, Charles Darwin - the Man and his Influence in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 320-321</p>
      <p>John Postgate, review of Adrian Desmond and James Moore, Darwin in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 327-328</p>
      <p>Krishna R Dronamraju, 'On Some Aspects of the Life and Work of John Burdon Sanderson Haldane, FRS, in India' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 211-237</p>
      <p>Peter J Bowler, 'Charles Darwin: Imprimature!', essay review in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 125-131</p>
      <p>Peter J Bowler, 'The Species Theory Evolves', review of Frederick Burkhardt and Sydney Smith, eds, The Correspondence of Charles Darwin. Vols 4, 5, 6 in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 262-265</p>
      <p>A E Gunther, 'J E Gray, Charles Darwin, and the Cirripedes, 1846-1851' in NR 1979-80 vol 34 pp 53-63</p>
      <p>A E Gunther, 'The Darwin Letters at Shrewsbury School' in NR 1975-6 vol 30 pp 25-43</p>
      <p>James R Moore, 'On the Education of Darwin's Sons: The Correspondence Between Charles Darwin and the Reverend G V Reed, 1857-1864' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 51-70</p>
      <p>L Harrison Matthews, 'Samuel Stutchbury and Darwin's Cirripedes' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 261-266</p>
      <p>M J Bartholomew, 'The Award of the Copley Medal to Charles Darwin' in NR 1975-6 vol 30 pp 209-218</p>
      <p>R B Freeman, 'Darwin's Negro Bird-Stuffer' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 83-86</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer, ed., 'The Darwin Letters at Shrewsbury School' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 68-85</p>
      <p>William Mills, 'Darwin and the Iceberg Theory' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 109-127</p>
      <p>Vanity Fair 30 September 1871</p>
      <p>A Cohen, 'Roland Trimen and the merope harem' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 205-218</p>
      <p>Graeme Gooday, 'A Victorian scientist and engineer', review of Gillian Cookson and Colin Hempstead, 'Fleeming Jenkin and the birth of electrical engineering' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 265-266</p>
      <p>Patricia Fara, 'Darwin's origin of inspiration', review of Edna Healey, 'Emma Darwin: the inspirational wife of a genius' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 267-268</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 1. 1731-1847' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 307-332</p>
      <p>J Corden, 'Web of Science History' project in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 383-388</p>
      <p>N J W Thrower, 'Samuel Pepys FRS (1633-1733) and The Royal Society' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 3-13</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>S Conway Morris, 'When the penny dropped. Charles Darwin: the power of place' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 250-251</p>
      <p>J Browne, 'Darwin on Darwin. Charles Darwin's The Life of Erasmus Darwin, ed D King-Hele' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 346 - 348</p>
      <p>D Carr Agnew, 'Robert Fitzroy and the myth of 'Marsden Square': Transatlantic rivalries in early marine meteorology' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 21-46</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'From Darwin and Wallace to the discovery of Invar' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 121-123</p>
      <p>M Bulmer, 'The theory of natural selection of Alfred Russel Wallace FRS' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 125-136</p>
      <p>J van Wyhe, 'The complete work of Charles Darwin online' in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 87-91</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'The Palace of Westminster frescoes, Kelvin's secretary and the Calcutta School of Tropical Medicine', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 135-137</p>
      <p>K Moore, 'An unpublished letter by Charles Darwin in the Royal Society's archives', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 193-197</p>
      <p>F Orrego and C Quintana, 'Darwin's illness: a final diagnosis' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 23-29</p>
      <p>J van Wyhe and A Basman, 'The launch and reception of Darwin online' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 63-65</p>
      <p>J van Wyhe, 'Mind the gap: did Darwin avoid publishing his theory for many years?' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 177-205</p>
      <p>B Lightman 'The many lives of Charles Darwin: early biographies and the definitive evolutionist' NR, 2010, vol 64, pp339-358</p>
      <p>J Ollerton, G Chancellor and J van Wyhe 'John Tweedie and Chrles Darwin in Buenos Ares' in NR 2012 vol 66, number 2, pages 111-206;</p>
      <p>Charles H Smith, 'Wallace, Darwin and Ternate 1858', in NR 2014 vol 68 no 2, pp 165-170</p>
      <p>B Jenkins 'Henry Cheek and transformism: new light on Charles Darwin's Edinburgh background' in Notes adn Records, vol 69, Issue 2, 20 June 2015</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Notes: DSB gives birth date as 09 February 1809</p>
      <p>Online resources: The complete work of Darwin online: http://darwin-online.org.uk</p>
      <p>Darwin correspondence project: http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Naturalist</term>
   </note>
</person>