<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8178">
   <persName>
      <forename>Daniel</forename>
      <surname>Colwall</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date> - 1690</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Death: Liberty of the Tower of London (November 1690)</p>
      
      <p>Career: Governor and benefactor of Christ's Hospital; established the royal mathematical school within Christ's Hospital (1676); paid for the engravings in Nehemiah Grew's 'Musaeum regalis societatis' (1681);</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: Treasurer 1666-1679; VP 1682-1688</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for examining and auditing the accounts of the Treasurer (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for the Histories of Trades (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Correspondence (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for taking care of the Royal Society (1676)</p>
      <p>Committee for Agriculture [Georgical Committee] (1669)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: As benefactor in 1665-66, presented £100 to pay for the collection of rarities, belonging to Mr Hubbard [Robert Hubert]. This formed the first part of the Society's museum.</p>
      <p>As Treasurer, he was instructed to collect members to pay their subscription, in particular in 1667 and 1673.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Kathleen H Ochs, 'The Royal Society of London's History of Trades Programme: An Early Episode in Applied Science' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 129-158</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>H G Lyons, 'The Society's Finances, part I: 1662-1830' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 73-87</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Colwall's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 16 January 1661.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>merchant and philanthropist</term>
   </note>
</person>