<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8189">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Croone</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1633 - 1684</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: London, England, Europe (15 September 1633)</p>
      <p>Death: London, England, Europe (12 October 1684)</p>
      <p>Burial: St Mildred's Church in the Poultry, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Physiology</p>
      <p>Education: Merchant Taylors School, London (1642); Emmanuel College, Cambridge, BA (1650/1), MA (1654); MD (Lit. Reg. 1663); Incorporated at Oxford (1654);</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Emmanuel (1651); Professor of Rhetoric, Gresham College, London (1659-1670); Gray's Inn (admitted 1670); candidate for College of Physicians (1660), Fellow (1675), and censor (1679); published 'De ratione motus musculorum' (London 1664); appointed by Barber-Surgeons' Company anatomy lecturer on muscles (1670-1684); maintained active experimental interests, and developed a lucrative medical practice in London in his later years, with a particular interest in respiration, muscular motion, and generation; noted for his experiment on establishing the importance of air in respiration by an experiment at the Royal Society, when he choked chicken until it appeared dead and then revived it by blowing air into its lungs through a glass pipe inserted down its throat (1664)</p>
      <p>Memberships: FRCP (1675)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: Appointed 'Register' 28/11/1660; 1664, 1666, 1668, 1670, 1672, 1675-1676, 1678-1681, 1683</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee to 'view Mersennnus concerning the tenacity of [bodies]' (25 June 1662)</p>
      <p>Committee on the Histories of Trades (30 March 1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for 'taking care of the repository of the Royal Society' (3 February 1676)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster; Hunter; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Kathleen H Ochs, 'The Royal Society of London's History of Trades Programme: An Early Episode in Applied Science' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 129-158</p>
      <p>L G Wilson, 'William Croone's Theory of Muscular Contraction' in NR 1961 vol 16 pp 158-178</p>
      <p>L M Payne, Leonard G Wilson and Sir Harold Hartley, 'William Croone, FRS (1633-1684)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 211-219, plate</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>J Gribbin, 'The Fellowship', 2005, pp172-174</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Croone's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously named as 'register' at the initial meeting on 28 November 1660, although he was not present.</p>
      <p>Name spelt 'Croune' in Birch and DNB, 'Croone or Crowne' in Venn.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician</term>
   </note>
</person>