<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8132">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles</forename>
      <surname>Blagden</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1748 - 1820</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Wotton-under-Edge, Gloucestershire, England (17 April 1748)</p>
      <p>Death: The house of his friend Berthollet (a renowned chemist), at Arcueil, near Paris, France (26 March 1820)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physical chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: MD (1768, Edinburgh)</p>
      <p>Career: Medical Officer in the Army (until 1814); Secretary of the Royal Society (1784-1797); friend of Sir Joseph Banks</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt c 1793</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 25/06/1772</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1788</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1784-1797</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>References: Neil Chambers, 'Letters From the President: the Correspondence of Sir Joseph Banks' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 27-57</p>
      <p>Ernest Heberden, 'Correspondence of William Heberden, FRS With the Reverend Stephen Hales and Sir Charles Blagden' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 179-189</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer and Max H Hey, 'The First Ascent of Mont Blanc' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 236-255</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'A Guide to the Archives of the Royal Society and to other Manuscripts in its Possession' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 21-39</p>
      <p>G. R. De Beer, ‘The diary of Sir Charles Blagden’, NR vol 8 1950–51pp 65–89</p>
      <p>G R de Beer, 'The Relations between Fellows of the Royal Society and French Men of Science when France and Britain were at War' in NR 1952 vol 9 pp 244-299</p>
      <p>A D Atkinson, 'Dr Johnson and the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 131-138</p>
      <p>L B Glyn, 'Israel Lyons: a short but starry career. The life of an eighteenth-century Jewish botanist and astronomer' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 275-305</p>
      <p>M Crosland, 'Relationships between the Royal Society and the Academie des Sciences in the late eighteenth century' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 25-34</p>
      <p>C Anderson, 'Blagden Papers at the Royal Society' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 237-238</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician</term>
   </note>
</person>