<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8288">
   <persName>
      <forename>Joseph John</forename>
      <surname>Thomson</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1856 - 1940</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Cheetham Hill, near Manchester, Cheshire, England (18 December 1856)</p>
      <p>Death: Cambridge (30 August 1940)</p>
      <p>Burial: Nave, Westminster Abbey, London</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics</p>
      <p>Education: Owen's College, Manchester; Trinity College, Cambridge. BA (1880)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow and Lecturer of Trinity College, Cambridge; Professor of Natural Philosophy, Royal Institution, London; Cavendish Professor of Physics, Cambridge (1884-1918); Master of Trinity College, Cambridge (1918)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1908; OM 1912</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 12/06/1884</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Royal Medal 1894; Hughes Medal 1902; Copley Medal 1914; Nobel Prize (Physics) 1906</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1887, 1913</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1915-1920; VP 1911-1913</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Anniversary Address 1920 in Proceedings of the Royal Society A 98 1920-21 pp319-328</p>
      <p>AssocMaterial: CSAC 74/4/80; NCUACS 91/4/00; NCUACS 117/3/03. Papers deposited in Trinity College Library, Cambridge</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society 1939-1941 vol 3 pp 587-609, plate, by Rayleigh</p>
      <p>References: George and Joan Thomson, 'J J Thomson as We Remember Him' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 201-210, plate</p>
      <p>Derek J Price, 'The Cavendish Laboratory Archives' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 139-147</p>
      <p>C T R Wilson, 'Reminiscences of My Early Years' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 163-173</p>
      <p>Sir George Thomson, 'An Unfortunate Experiment: Hertz and the Nature of Cathode Rays' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 237-242</p>
      <p>John G Jenkin, 'The Appointment of W H Bragg, FRS, to the University of Adelaide' in NR 1985-86 vol 40 pp 75-99</p>
      <p>S Devons, 'Rutherford and the Science of His Day' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 221-242</p>
      <p>Gordon Squires, 'A History of the Electron', review of Per F. Dahl, Flash of the Cathode Rays: A History of J J Thomson's Electron in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 176-177</p>
      <p>Sir Brian Pippard, 'Stumbling Towards the Light', review of E A Davis and I J Falconer, J J Thomson and the Discovery of the Electron in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 375-376</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>P Harper, 'Preserving scientific archives: the work of NCUACS' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 227-232</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Knight Physicist</term>
   </note>
</person>