<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8202">
   <persName>
      <forename>Kenelm</forename>
      <surname>Digby</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1603 - 1665</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Gayhurst, Buckinghamshire, England, Europe (11 July 1603)</p>
      <p>Death: Covent Garden, London, England, Europe (11 June 1665)</p>
      <p>Burial: Christ Church, Newgate Street, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Author</p>
      <p>Diplomat</p>
      <p>Sailor</p>
      <p>Research Field: Natural philosophy; Chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: Gloucester Hall, Oxford (1618); Gray's Inn (1619); Peterhouse, Cambridge; MA (on the King's visit 1624)</p>
      <p>Career: Sailed to Spain with his relative, Sir John Digby (1617-1618); travelled in France, Italy and Spain (1620-1623); gave three addresses to the 'Accademia dei Filomati' in Siena; became gentleman of the privy chamber to Prince Charles (1623); commissioner of the 'Eage' and the 'George and Elizabeth'; appointed Junior Principal Officer of the Navy (1630); studied chemistry and became involved in alchemy (1633-1635); arrested by Parliament (7 August 1642; 12 November 1642-30 Julu 1643); wrote his treatises 'Two treatises, in the one of which the nature of bodies, in the other the nature of man's soul is looked into: in way of discovery of the immortality of reasonable souls' (1642-1643); banished to France (1643-1654); permitted to return to England (January 1654) and received a pension; published translation of 'Of Adhering to God' (1654); confidant and ambassador of Cromwell (1655-1658); Chancellor to Queen Henrietta</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 28 October 1623</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 22/04/1663</p>
      <p>Council: Sworn in 3 June 1663.</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Chemistry Committee</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Presented findings on plants and animals (1661).</p>
      <p>Brought in stones, called octulus mundi (1661)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn</p>
      <p>References: Jacqueline A Stedall, 'Catching Proteus: the collaborations of Wallis and Brouncker. II. Number problems' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 317-331</p>
      <p>Peter Brimblecombe, 'Interest in Air Pollution Among Early Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 123-129</p>
      <p>John F Fulton, 'Sir Kenelm Digby, FRS (1603-1665)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 199-210, plate</p>
      <p>G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>H W Robinson, 'Gleanings from the Library - I. A Note on the Early Minutes' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 92-95</p>
      <p>J Gribbin, 'The Fellowship', 2005, pp174-180</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Digby's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously elected on 12 December 1660.</p>
      <p>Aubrey (quoting Jonson) gives his date of birth as 11 June</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher and courtier</term>
   </note>
</person>