<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8259">
   <persName>
      <forename>James Clerk</forename>
      <surname>Maxwell</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1831 - 1879</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Edinburgh, Scotland (13 June 1831)</p>
      <p>Death: Cambridge (05 November 1879)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics</p>
      <p>Education: Edinburgh; Peterhouse, Cambridge; Trinity College, Cambridge. BA (1854), MA</p>
      <p>Career: Shared Smith's Prize (1854) with Edward John Routh (FRS 1872); Professor of Natural Philosophy, Marischal College, Aberdeen (1856); Professor of Natural Philosophy, King's College, London (1860-1865); Professor of Experimental Physics, Cambridge (1871); died of cancer</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 6/06/1861</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Rumford Medal 1860</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1866</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Authority: Birth date verified from the Parochial Records by Professor Bolton (Sep 1977), and confirmed by DSB entry.</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1881-1882 vol 33 pp i-xvi</p>
      <p>References: J S Rowlinson, 'Energy in the 19th Century', review of Crosbie Smith, The Science of Energy. A Cultural History of Energy Physics in Victorian Britain in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 281-282</p>
      <p>Sir Brian Pippard, 'Genius in Context', review of P M Harman, The Natural Philosophy of James Clerk Maxwell in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 279-281, plate</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, 'Maxwell's Early Career', review of P M Harman, The Scientific Letters and Papers of James Clerk Maxwell. Vol 1. 1846-1862 in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 266-270</p>
      <p>Gillian Beer, 'Translation or Transformation? The Relations of Literature and Science' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 81-99</p>
      <p>T M Charlton, 'An Extension of Maxwell's Theory of Pin-Jointed Frameworks by M W Crofton, FRS' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 53-56</p>
      <p>P M Harman, 'Newton to Maxwell: the Principia and British Physics' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 75-96</p>
      <p>C Domb, 'James Clerk Maxwell in London 1860-1865' in NR 1980 vol 35 pp 67-103</p>
      <p>H C Bolton and W C Price, 'The Date of Birth of James Clerk Maxwell' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 213-214</p>
      <p>J G O'Hara, 'George Johnstone Stoney, FRS, and the Concept of the Electron' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 265-276</p>
      <p>R V Jones, 'James Clerk Maxwell at Aberdeen 1856-1860' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 57-81, plate</p>
      <p>Otto Mayr, 'Victorian Physicists and Speed Regulation: An Encounter Between Science and Technology' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 205-228</p>
      <p>T M Charlton, 'Maxwell, Jenkin and Cotterill and the Theory of Statically-Indeterminate Structures' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 233-246</p>
      <p>William P D Wightman, 'Aberdeen University and the Royal Society' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 145-158</p>
      <p>Derek J Price, 'The Cavendish Laboratory Archives' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 139-147</p>
      <p>Graeme Gooday, 'A Victorian scientist and engineer', review of Gillian Cookson and Colin Hempstead, 'Fleeming Jenkin and the birth of electrical engineering' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 265-266</p>
      <p>K K Schwarz, 'Faraday and Babbage' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp367-381</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Le Sage's Essai de chymie mechanique' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 35-45</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'The work of Thomas Andrews and James Thomson on the liquefaction of gases' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 143-159</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Gases and liquids. How fluids unmix: discoveries by the school of Van der Waals and Kamerlingh Onnes, by J L Sengers' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 255-256</p>
      <p>B Pippard, 'A paragon of physics. &lt;i&gt;The man who changed everything - the life of James Clerk Maxwell&lt;/i&gt; by Basil Mahon' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 103-104</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Physicist</term>
   </note>
</person>