<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8278">
   <persName>
      <forename>Ernest</forename>
      <surname>Rutherford</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>Baron Rutherford of Nelson</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1871 - 1937</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Spring Grove (Brightwater), New Zealand (30 August 1871)</p>
      <p>Death: Cambridge, Cambridgeshire, England (19 October 1937)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey, London (ashes)</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics, chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: Nelson College, New Zealand (Marlborough Education Board Scholarship) (1887-1889); Canterbury College, Christchuch (1890-1894). BA, BSc, MA (Hons), DSc (University of New Zealand); BA (Cambridge); BSc (McGill, ad eudem)</p>
      <p>Career: Worked as a relieving teacher, Christchurch Boys High School (1894); won a scholarship as a research student in England and went to work with J J Thompson (FRS 1884), Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge; Professor, McGill University, Montreal, Canada (1898); worked on radioactivity with Frederick Soddy (FRS 1910); moved to Manchester University, England (1907); worked on acoustic detection of submarines (during World War 1); Director, Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge, where he split the atom (1919); helped to found, and was President of, the Academic Assistance Council to aid displaced academics (1933); received about 32 Honorary doctorates; his honours included 34 medals, and Honorary Fellowships of many societies; his picture appeared on $100 (NZ) note (went into circulation 1992) Had little patience with left wing politics or with theoretical speculation generally. His accent was said to be a combination of West Country and Cockney.</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1914; OM 1925; Baron 1931</p>
      <p>Memberships: Hon RSNZ (1904); FInstP (president 1931-1933)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 11/06/1903</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Rumford Medal 1904; Copley Medal 1922; Nobel Prize (Chemistry) 1908</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1904 and 1920</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1925-1930; VP 1922-1923</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; DNZB; www.rutherford.org.nz</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Obituary Notices of Fellows of the Royal Society 1936-1938 vol 2 pp 395-423, plate, by A S Eve and J Chadwick</p>
      <p>References: Sir Harold Hartley, 'The Ramsay Centenary' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 71-80</p>
      <p>Derek J Price, 'The Cavendish Laboratory Archives' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 139-147</p>
      <p>C T R Wilson, 'Reminiscences of My Early Years' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 163-173</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'Some Reminiscences of Ernest Marsden's Days with Rutherford at Manchester' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 247-250</p>
      <p>Sir Mark Oliphant, 'Some Personal Recollections of Rutherford, the Man' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 7-23</p>
      <p>Sir Harrie Massey, 'Nuclear Physics Today and in Rutherford's Day' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 25-44</p>
      <p>N Feather, 'Rutherford - Faraday - Newton' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 45-55</p>
      <p>Lord Blackett, 'Rutherford' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 57-59</p>
      <p>W Bennett Lewis, 'Some Recollections and Reflections on Rutherford' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 61-63</p>
      <p>Sir Nevill Mott, 'Rutherford and Theory' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 65-66</p>
      <p>P P O'Shea, 'Ernest Rutherford, his Honours and Distinctions' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 67-74</p>
      <p>J B Adams, 'Four Generations of Nuclear Physicists' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 75-94, plate</p>
      <p>Anon., 'Rutherford Centenary Celebrations' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 p 5, plate</p>
      <p>J W Boag and D Shoenberg (trans and eds), 'Letters from Kapitza to his Mother, 1921-27' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 205-228</p>
      <p>Sir Rudolf Peierls, 'Rutherford and Bohr' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 229-241</p>
      <p>S Devons, 'Rutherford and the Science of His Day' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 221-242, plate</p>
      <p>Robin J H Clark and Michael J Kelly, 'New Zealand, New Zealanders and the Royal Society' in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 263-281</p>
      <p>Allan R Mackintosh, 'The Crocodile and the Elephant: Rutherford, Bohr and Quantum Physics' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 309-316, plate</p>
      <p>G V R Born, FRS, 'The wide-ranging family history of Max Born' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 219-262</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 1. 1731-1847' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 307-332</p>
      <p>P Fara, ' Big bangs. Invisible rays: a history of radioactivity' by G I Brown</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>R Singh and F Riess, 'The nobel laureate Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman FRS and his contacts with the British Scientific community in a social and political context' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 47-64</p>
      <p>Neil Todd, 'A Brief History of Lord Rutherford's Radium' in NR 2014, vol 68, no3, pp 279-300</p>
      <p>E Marsden 'Rutherford, by those who knew him' in Physical Society, 1954. Report of Rutherford Memorial Lecture (1948)</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Notes: Mistakenly registered in the birth records in New Zealand as 'Earnest'</p>
   </note>
</person>