<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8218">
   <persName>
      <forename>Michael</forename>
      <surname>Faraday</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1791 - 1867</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Newington Butts, Surrey, England (22 September 1791)</p>
      <p>Death: Hampton Court, Middlesex (25 August 1867)</p>
      <p>Burial: Highgate Cemetery, London</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Chemistry, physics</p>
      <p>Education: DCL (1832)</p>
      <p>Career: Apprenticed to a bookbinder (c 1804); assistant to Sir Humphry Davy at the Royal Institution; visited the Continent with Davy; succeeded Davy at Royal Institution (1827); granted pension (1835); advisor to Trinity House (1836, for nearly 30 years) given house at Hampton Court (1858); discoveries included induced electricity (1831), electronic state of matter (1831) &amp; equivalents in electro-chemical decomposition (1834)</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Often called the first scientific celebrity in Britain, Faraday was the leading scientst of his generation. his work in the fields of electricity and magnetism led to the discovery of electromagnetic rotation - the theoretical basis of the electric motor. He started his career as an assistant to the famous chemist Humphry Davy, but had established himself as a great experimentalist by the time of his great discovery which changed scientific thought concerning electromagnetism. Public lectures were very important to Faraday, who commenced his work in science after attending chemistry lectures, so in 1826 he set up the Friday Evening Discourses and the Christmas Lectures for juveniles, institutions which continue to this day. In 1860 he published a series of children's lectures entitled 'The Chemical History of a Candle'.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>In 1858 a deputation from the Royal Society visited Faraday and asked him to be the next President of the Society, Faraday declined the offer. (Recorded in White's Diary 20 May 1858 pp 117-118, reference courtesy of Professor Frank James).</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 08/01/1824</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1832, 1838; Royal Medal 1835, 1846; Rumford Medal 1846</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1829, 1832, 1849, 1851, 1857</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1868-1869 vol 17 pp i-lxviii signed by H B J</p>
      <p>References: Sydney Ross, 'The Search for Electromagnetic Induction 1820-1831' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 184-219, plate</p>
      <p>Sir Harold Hartley, 'Richard Owen and William Clift' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 60-62</p>
      <p>Sir Harold Hartley, 'A Letter From Richard Phillips, FRS (1778-1857) to Michael Faraday, FRS (1791-1867)' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 220-223</p>
      <p>S Ross, 'Faraday Consults the Scholars: the Origins of the Terms of Electrochemistry' in NR 1961 vol 16 pp 187-220</p>
      <p>M L Wolbarsht and D S Sax, 'Charles II, a Royal Martyr' in NR 1961 vol 16 pp 154-157</p>
      <p>Brian Bowers and Keith Bowers, 'Michael Faraday's Geological Notes on the Isle of Wight' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 65-74</p>
      <p>Crosbie Smith, 'More Light on Faraday', review of Frank A J L James, ed, The Correspondence of Michael Faraday. Volume 2, 1832-1840 in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 170-172, plate</p>
      <p>Garry J Tee, 'Relics of Davy and Faraday in New Zealand' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 93-102, plate</p>
      <p>John Varley Jeffery, 'The Varley Family: Engineers and Artists' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 263-279</p>
      <p>Sir John Meurig Thomas, 'Sir Benjamin Thompson, Count Rumford and the Royal Institution' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 11-25</p>
      <p>Crosbie Smith, 'The Genius of Michael Faraday', essay review in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 317-323</p>
      <p>Gillian Beer, 'Translation or Transformation? The Relations of Literature and Science' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 81-99</p>
      <p>Ronald Anderson, 'The Referees' Assessment of Faraday's Electromagnetic Induction Paper of 1831' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 243-256</p>
      <p>David Gooding, '"He Who Proves, Discovers": John Herschel, William Pepys and the Faraday Effect' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 229-244</p>
      <p>David Gooding, 'A Convergence of Opinion on the Divergence of Lines: Faraday and Thomson's Discussion of Diamagnetism' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 243-259</p>
      <p>H R H The Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh, 'Research and Prediction. The Inaugural Hartley Lecture Delivered at the Royal Society, 21 May 1974' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 11-27</p>
      <p>Lise Wilkinson, 'Three Drawings of Fellows by William Brockedon, FRS' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 183-187, plate</p>
      <p>N Feather, 'Rutherford - Faraday - Newton' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 45-55</p>
      <p>Paul A Tunbridge, 'Faraday's Genevese Friends' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 263-298</p>
      <p>R V J, review of Gwendy Caroe, The Royal Institution: An Informal History in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 107-110</p>
      <p>Sydney Ross, 'John Herschel on Faraday and on Science' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 77-82, plate</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'A Roman tercentenary' by A Cook in NR 2002 vol 56 p273</p>
      <p>F A J L James, ' Editing Faraday' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 349-352</p>
      <p>K K Schwarz, 'Faraday and Babbage' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 367-381</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'The work of Thomas Andrews and James Thomson on the liquefaction of gases' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 143-159</p>
      <p>W P Griffith and P J T Morris, 'Charles Hatchett FRS (1765 - 1847), chemist and discoverer of niobium' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 299 - 316</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'A national treasure house. &lt;i&gt;'The common purposes of life': science and society at the Royal Institution of Great Britain&lt;/i&gt; ed Frank A J L James ' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 105-106</p>
      <p>Notes: At head of certificate: 'Balloted for &amp; Elected the 8 January 182[4]'; small sections of certificate missing;</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Natural Philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>