<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8238">
   <persName>
      <forename>John Frederick William</forename>
      <surname>Herschel</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1792 - 1871</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Slough, Buckinghamshire, England (07 March 1792)</p>
      <p>Death: His residence, named Collingwood, Hawkhurst, Kent (11 May 1871)</p>
      <p>Burial: Near the grave of Sir Isaac Newton, Westminster Abbey, London</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Astronomy, physics, chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: Eton; St John's College, Cambridge. BA (1813, Senior Wrangler and 1st Smith's prizeman), MA (1816)</p>
      <p>Career: Conducted astronomical observations at the observatory of Sir James South (FRS 1821), Blackman Street, Southwark; travelled in Italy and Switzerland with Charles Babbage (FRS 1816); set up observatory at Feldhausen, near Cape Town, South Africa (1833-1838); Master of the Mint (1850-1855)</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1831; Bt 1838</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 27/05/1813</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1821 and 1847; Royal Medal 1833, 1836, 1840</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1823</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1824-1827; VP 1827-1829, 1838-1840, 1847-1848, 1851-1852</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1871-1872 vol 20 pp xvii-xxiii signed by T R R</p>
      <p>References: W H Brock, 'The Selection of the Authors of the Bridgewater Treatises' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 162-179</p>
      <p>Sir John Craig, 'The Royal Society and the Royal Mint' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 156-167</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer, ed, 'Some Unpublished Letters of Charles Darwin' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 12-66</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'A Guide to the Archives of the Royal Society and to other Manuscripts in its Possession' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 21-39</p>
      <p>L F Gilbert, 'The Election to the Presidency of the Royal Society in 1820' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 256-279</p>
      <p>John R Levene, 'Sir George Biddell Airy, FRS (1801-1892) and the Discovery and Correction of Astigmatism' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 180-199</p>
      <p>Geoffrey Cantor, 'In Love With Light', review of Larry J Schaaf, Out of the Shadows. Herschel, Talbot and the Invention of Photography in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 147-149, plate</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Herschel, Peacock, Babbage and the Development of the Cambridge Curriculum' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 205-219</p>
      <p>Margaret Bullard, 'My Small Newtonian Sweeper - Where is it Now?' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 139-148</p>
      <p>Peter J Turvey, 'Sir John Herschel and the Abandonment of Charles Babbage's Difference Engine No. 1' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 165-176</p>
      <p>David Gooding, '"He Who Proves, Discovers": John Herschel, William Pepys and the Faraday Effect' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 229-244</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, 'Between Two Scientific Generations: John Herschel's Rejection of the Conservation of Energy in His 1864 Correspondence With William Thomson' in NR 1985-86 vol 40 pp 53-62</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, 'Of "Medals and Muddles". The Context of the Discovery of Thallium: William Crookes's Early Spectro-Chemical Work' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 65-90</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, 'The Conservation of Energy, Theories of Absorption and Resonating Molecules, 1851-1854: G G Stokes, A J Angstrom and W Thomson' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 79-107</p>
      <p>Maurice Crosland, 'Explicit Qualifications as a Criterion for Membership of the Royal Society: A Historical Review' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 167-187</p>
      <p>Sydney Ross, 'John Herschel on Faraday and on Science' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 77-82</p>
      <p>R Sharp, 'Some final thoughts of Sir John Herschel, FRS' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 183-186</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Charles Babbage and his world' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 353-365</p>
      <p>K K Schwarz, 'Faraday and Babbage' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp367-381</p>
      <p>J Corden, 'Web of Science History' project in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 383-388</p>
      <p>M Bolt, 'Colonizing the Heavens. John Herschel's Cape voyage: Private Science, Public Imagination and the Ambitions of Empire by S Ruskin', in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 333-334</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Astronomer</term>
   </note>
</person>