<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8219">
   <persName>
      <forename>John</forename>
      <surname>Flamsteed</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1646 - 1719</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Denby, Derbyshire, England (19 August 1646)</p>
      <p>Death: Greenwich, London (31 December 1719)</p>
      <p>Burial: The chancel of Burstow parish church, Surrey</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Astronomer</p>
      <p>Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Astronomy</p>
      <p>Education: Derby School; Jesus College, Cambridge; MA (Lit. Reg. 1674)</p>
      <p>Career: Left school because of an attack of rheumatism (1662); travelled to Ireland in search of a cure; went to London (1670) where he met Henry Oldenburg (FRS date) and Sir Jonas Moore (FRS date), who became his patron; ordained (1675); first Astronomer Royal (1675-1719), he used his own instruments, which were removed by his widow after his death; Vicar of Burstow, Surrey (1684); a perfectionist, he was reluctant to publish his observations unless they were perfect, which led to conflict with Newton and Halley. On 12 December 1709 Queen Anne appointed a Board of Visitors of the Royal Observatory made up of the president and council of the Royal Society, authorizing them to demand a copy of each year's observations, to direct what observations should be made, and to examine the observatory's instruments. Flamsteed's vigorous objections and refusal to co-operate further on the publication of his star catalogue and observations led to an incomplete version being published by Halley in 1712, which he condemned. After the accession of George I Flamsteed was able to buy up 300 of Halley's unsold copies, and after removing the sextant observations which he had previously approved and reserving some copies to display their errors, he burnt the rest. His observations were published to his very high standards posthumously in 1725 edited by his wife Margaret, and his 'Atlas Coelestis' in 1729, where the editor was again his wife with Crosthwait and Sharp responsible for the technical side</p>
      <p>Memberships: Oxford Philosophical Society</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 8/02/1677</p>
      <p>Council: 1681, 1683, 1685, 1692, 1694, 1699</p>
      <p>9/11/1709 Society ended his exemption from dues, and used non-payment as an excuse to expel him.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Hunter; Gunther</p>
      <p>References: Sir Harold Spencer Jones, 'Halley as an Astronomer' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 175-192</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>Eric G Forbes, 'The Library of the Rev. John Flamsteed, FRS, First Astronomer Royal' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 119-143</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society's Role in the Diffusion of Information in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 173-192</p>
      <p>Sir Bernard Lovell, 'Address at Westminster Abbey, on the Occasion of the Tercentenary of the Royal Greenwich Observatory' in NR 1975-6 vol 30 pp 127-132</p>
      <p>W H McCrea, 'The Royal Observatory and the Study of Gravitation' in NR 1975-6 vol 30 pp 133-140, plate</p>
      <p>D W Hughes, 'The Principia and Comets' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 53-74</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'The Prehistory of the Principia from 1664 to 1686' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 11-61</p>
      <p>A J Meadows, 'John Flamsteed, Our Astronomical Observator', review of The Correspondence of John Flamsteed, First Astronomer Royal. Volume I (1666-1682), ed. Eric G Forbes et al, in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 250-253, plate</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Greenwich Comes of Age', review of Eric G Forbes, Lesley Murdin and Frances Willmoth, The Correspondence of John Flamsteed, the First Astronomer Royal. Volume Two, 1682-1703 in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 191-193, plate</p>
      <p>Allan Chapman, 'Our Astronomical Observator', review of Frances Willmoth, ed., Flamsteed's Stars, New Perspectives on the Life and Work of the First Astronomer Royal (1646-1719)in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 170-171</p>
      <p>A Cook, '1703 and other anniversaries' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 1-2</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'The end of the affair. The correspondence of John Flamsteed, the first Astronomer Royal, vol 3 (1703-1719) by E G Forbes, L Murdin and F Willmoth' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 113-116</p>
      <p>J H Appleby, 'The founding of St Petersburg in the context of the Royal Society's relationship with Russia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 273-284</p>
      <p>M Croarken, 'Astronomical labourers: Maskelyne's assistants at the Royal Observatory, Greenwich, 1765 - 1811' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 285 - 298</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>astronomer</term>
   </note>
</person>