<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8242">
   <persName>
      <forename>Robert</forename>
      <surname>Hooke</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1635 - 1703</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Freshwater, Isle of Wight, England, Europe (18 July 1635)</p>
      <p>Death: Gresham College, London, England, Europe (3 March 1703)</p>
      <p>Burial: Church of St Helen, Bishopsgate Street, London, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Architect</p>
      <p>Research Field: Physics</p>
      <p>Education: Pupil of Samuel Cooper and Sir Peter Lely; Westminster School; Christ Church, Oxford; MA (1663); MD (Lambeth 1691)</p>
      <p>Career: Assisted Thomas Willis and Robert Boyle with their experiments; invented the pendulum watch; Curator of Experiments at the Royal Society (1662); Professor of Geometry at Gresham College, London (1664); Cutlerian Lecturer (1664); Philosophical assistant to John Wilkins and William Petty at Durdans, Epsom, Surrey (1665); Published 'Micrographia, or, Some physiological descriptions of minute bodies made by magnifying glasses, with observations and inquiries thereupon' (1665); City Surveyor for London (1667); Doctor of Physic at Doctors' Commons (1691)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Council: Curator of Experiments 1662-1688; Secretary 1677-1682; On Council 1677-1681; 1684; 1686; 1689-1690; 1692-1695; 1697-1699</p>
      <p>Editor Phil. Coll.: 1679-1682</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Mechanical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Astronomical and Optical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Anatomical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for the Histories of Trades (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for Collecting all the Phenomena of Nature hitherto observed (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee to audit Mr Colwall's accounts for the past year (1677)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: As Curator of Experiments, created a large variety of demonstrations and presentations for the meetings of the Society. These were mainly recorded in the Journal Book and the Register Book.</p>
      <p>Set up a 'select club' which met outside the Society's lodgings (1670s).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Foster; Aubrey; Hunter; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Charles H Cotter, 'The Mariner's Sextant and the Royal Society' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 23-36</p>
      <p>D R Oldroyd, 'Some "Philosophicall Scribbles" Attributed to Robert Hooke' in NR 1980 vol 35 pp 17-32</p>
      <p>D R Oldroyd, 'Some Writings of Robert Hooke on Procedures for the Prosecution of Scientific Inquiry, Including His "Lectures of Things Requisite to a Ntral History"' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 145-167</p>
      <p>Ian Adamson, 'The Royal Society and Gresham College 1660-1711' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 1-21</p>
      <p>J A Bennett, 'Robert Hooke as Mechanic and Natural Philosopher' in NR 1980 vol 35 pp 33-48</p>
      <p>J A Bennett, 'Wren's Last Building?' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 107-118</p>
      <p>J A Lohne, 'Experimentum Crucis' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 169-199</p>
      <p>J Buchanan-Brown, 'The Books Presented to the Royal Society by John Aubrey, FRS' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 167-193</p>
      <p>Jeanne Bolam, 'The Botanical Works of Nehemiah Grew, FRS (1641-1712)' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 219-231</p>
      <p>Kathleen H Ochs, 'The Royal Society of London's History of Trades Programme: An Early Episode in Applied Science' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 129-158</p>
      <p>Laurel Brodsley, Sir Charles Frank and John W Steeds, 'Prince Rupert's Drops' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 1-26</p>
      <p>Margaret J M Ezell, 'Richard Waller, SRS: "In the Pursuit of Nature"' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 215-233</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society's Role in the Diffusion of Information in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 173-192</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'A "College" for the Royal Society: The Abortive Plan of 1667-1668' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 159-186</p>
      <p>P D Lawrence and A G Molland, 'David Gregory's Inaugural Lecture at Oxford' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 143-178</p>
      <p>Penelope M Gouk, 'Acoustics in the Early Royal Society 1660-1680' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 155-175</p>
      <p>R Lewis, 'The publication of John Wilkins's Essay (1668): some contextual considerations' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp133-146</p>
      <p>S Mandelbrote, 'From Bremen to Pall Mall. Henry Oldenburg. Shaping The Royal Society, by M B Hall' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 389-390</p>
      <p>A Cook, '1703 and other anniversaries' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 1-2</p>
      <p>Robert Iliffe 'Material doubts: Hooke, artisan cultureand the exchange of information in 1670's London' in British Journal of the History of Science vol 28 pp 285-318</p>
      <p>J Heyman, 'The birth of the modern architect. On a grander scale: the outstanding career of Sir Christopher Wren, by L Jardine' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 243-244</p>
      <p>Stephen Inwood 'The Man Who Knew Too Much'. Macmillan 2002</p>
      <p>Lisa Jardine 'On a Grander Scale; the outstanding career of Sir Christopher Wren'. Harper Collins 2002</p>
      <p>Lisa Jardine 'The Curious Life of Robert Hooke; The Man Who Measured London' Harper Collins, 2003</p>
      <p>Michael Cooper 'A more beautiful city; Robert Hooke and the rebuilding of London after the Great Fire' Sutton Publishing 2003</p>
      <p>Cooper, Michael, ed; Hunter, Michael. ed. 'Hooke 2003: Papers presented at a conference to mark the tercentenary of the death of Robert Hooke 1635-1703'. Conference held at the Royal Society 7-8 July 2003.</p>
      <p>Jim Bennett; Michael Cooper; Lisa Jardine 'London's Leonardo: the Life and Work of Robert Hooke'. Oxford Uuniversity Press 2003</p>
      <p>P Breeze, 'The ancestry of Robert Hooke: John Hooke of Wroxhall' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 269-271</p>
      <p>M Hunter, 'Report. Robert Hooke revivified' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 89-91</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Report. Robert Hooke at Christ Church, Oxford' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 93-95</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>L Jardine, 'The 2003 Wilkins Lecture: Dr Wilkins's boy wonders' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 107-129</p>
      <p>H Gest, 'The Discovery of Microorganisms by Robert Hooke and Antoni von Leeuwenhoek, Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 187-201</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Theatrical Science. C Djerassi and D Pinner, Newton's darkness: two dramatic views' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 237-238</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'In this issue' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 245 - 247</p>
      <p>J Friesen, 'Essay review. Robert Hooke under the microscope' in in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 299 - 302</p>
      <p>J Friesen, 'Hooke and seventeenth century science. 'England's Leonardo. Robert Hooke and the seventeenth century Scientific Revolution' by Allan Chapman' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 205-206</p>
      <p>J Gribbin, 'The Fellowship', 2005, pp147-154, 183-225</p>
      <p>R M May, 'Address by Lord May PRS, given at the dedication of the memorial to Dr Robert Hooke at Westminster Abbey on 3 March 2005' in NR 2005 pp 321-324</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'The Palace of Westminster frescoes, Kelvin's secretary and the Calcutta School of Tropical Medicine', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 135-137</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'The Hooke folio', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 231-233</p>
      <p>R Adams and L Jardine, 'The return of the Hooke folio', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 235-239</p>
      <p>F Henderson, 'Unpublished material from the memorandum book of Robert Hooke, Guildhall Library MS 1758' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 129-175</p>
      <p>A Mills, 'Robert Hooke's 'Universal joint' and its application to sundials and the sundial-clock' in NR 2007 vol 61 pp 219-236</p>
      <p>W Poole 'Antoine Frqancois Payen, the 1666 "Selenelion" and a rediscovered letter to Robert Hooke' NR 2007 Vol 61 pp 251-264</p>
      <p>W Ramsey, P Daniels, E G Ramsey, 'The Limehouse Porcelain Factory - its output, antecedents, and the influence of the Royal Society of London on the evolution of English porcelain based on composition and technology. ' Published Inverscafgill, New Zealand, January 2013</p>
      <p>I Lawon 'Crafting the Microworld: how Robert Hooke constructed knowledge about small things' in N&amp;R Vo 70 Issue 1 March 2016, pp 23 - 44</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Hooke's election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was later elected on 3 June 1663.</p>
      <p>DSB gives death date as 3 March 1702.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>