<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8279">
   <persName>
      <forename>Edward</forename>
      <surname>Sabine</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1788 - 1883</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Great Britain Street, Dublin, Ireland (14 October 1788)</p>
      <p>Death: Richmond, Surrey (26 June 1883)</p>
      <p>Burial: Family vault at Tewin, Hertfordshire</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Research Field: Geophysics, terrestrial magnestism, astronomy</p>
      <p>Education: Entered the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich (1803); studied astronomy and terrestrial magnetism under Henry Browne (1816)</p>
      <p>Career: Served in Canada; astronomer to expeditions to discover the North West Passage under Sir John Ross (1818) and under Sir William Edward Parry (1819-1820); Colonel (by 1849); Major General (1856)</p>
      <p>Honours: KCB 1869</p>
      <p>Memberships: Athenaeum (Founder member 1824)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 16/04/1818</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1821; Royal Medal 1849</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1821 and 1853</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1861-1871; Treas 1850-1861; Sec 1827-1830; For Sec 1845-1850; VP 1839-1841, 1850-1856, 1871-1872</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1892 vol 51 pp xliii-li</p>
      <p>References: G E Fogg, 'The Royal Society and the Antarctic' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 85-98</p>
      <p>James Gabriel O'Hara, 'Gauss and the Royal Society: The Reception of His Ideas on Magnetism in Britain (1832-1842)' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 17-78</p>
      <p>Charles H Cotter, 'The Royal Society and the Deviation of the Compass' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 297-309</p>
      <p>M J Bartholomew, 'The Award of the Copley Medal to Charles Darwin' in NR 1975-6 vol 30 pp 209-218</p>
      <p>Sir Gavin de Beer, ed, 'Some Unpublished Letters of Charles Darwin' in NR 1959 vol 14 pp 12-66</p>
      <p>H G L, 'A Fragment of History' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 28-31</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 1. 1731-1847' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 307-332</p>
      <p>R W Home, 'The Royal Society and the Empire: the colonial and Commonwealth Fellowship. Part 2. After 1847' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 47-84</p>
      <p>D Carr Agnew, 'Robert Fitzroy and the myth of 'Marsden Square': Transatlantic rivalries in early marine meteorology' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 21-46</p>
      <p>E Murphy, 'A mad house transformed: the lives and work of Charles James Beverly FRS (1788-1868) and John Warburton MD FRS (1795-1847)' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 267 - 281</p>
      <p>G Ferrari and A McConnell, 'Robert Mallet and the 'Great Neapolitan earthquake' of 1857 in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 45-64</p>
      <p>Notes: Given the course of his life, probably better to describe him as British even though he was born in Ireland.</p>
   </note>
</person>