<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8239">
   <persName>
      <forename>Archibald Vivian</forename>
      <surname>Hill</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1886 - 1977</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 26 September 1886</p>
      <p>Death: 03 June 1977</p>
      
      <p>Education: MA</p>
      <p>Career: In 1914, at the outbreak of World War I, Hill joined the British army and assembled a team working on ballistics and operations research. The team included many notable physicists including Ralph H. Fowler, Douglas Hartree and Arthur Milne.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Hill returned to Cambridge in 1919 before taking the chair in physiology at the Victoria University of Manchester in 1920. Parallelling the work of German Otto Fritz Meyerhof he elucidated the processes whereby mechanical work is produced in muscles. The two shared the 1922 Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine for this work.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>In 1923 he succeeded Ernest Starling as professor of physiology at University College, London, a post he held until his retirement in 1951. He continued as an active researcher until 1966.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>World War II saw the beginning of Hill's extensive public service. Already in 1935 he was working with Patrick Blackett and Sir Henry Tizard on the committee that gave birth to Radar. In 1933, he became with Lord Beveridge and Lord Rutherford a founder member and vice-president of the Academic Assistance Council (which became the Society for the Protection of Science and Learning in 1936). By the start of the Second World War, the organization had saved 900 academics (18 of whom went on to win Nobel Prizes) from the Nazi persecution. He served as an independent Member of Parliament (MP) for Cambridge University from 1940 to 1945. He took part in many scientific missions to the U.S</p>
      <p>Honours: CBE 1946; Kt 1968</p>
      <p>Honours: OBE 1918; CH 1946</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 2/05/1918</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1948; Royal Medal 1926; Nobel Prize (Physiology or Medicine) 1922 with Otto Fritz Meyerhoff</p>
      <p>Royal Society Foulerton Research Professorship (1926 - 1951)</p>
      <p>Lectures: Croonian 1926</p>
      <p>Council: V-P 1943-1944, 1945-1946; For Sec 1945-1946; Sec 1935-1945</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; dates for Foulerton Research Professorship from Year Book, dates given by Record (1925-1951) incorrect</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1978 vol 24 pp 71-149, plate, by Sir Bernard Katz</p>
      <p>References: Robert S Anderson, 'Patrick Blackett in India: Military Consultant and Scientific Intervenor, 1947-72. Part One' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 253-273</p>
      <p>Meg Weston Smith, 'E A Milne and the Creation of Air Defence: Some Letters From an Unprincipled Brigand, 1916-1919' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 241-255</p>
      <p>William McGucken, 'The Royal Society and the Genesis of the Scientific Advisory Committee to Britain's War Cabinet, 1939-1940' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 87-115</p>
      <p>A V Hill, 'Jewels in My Acquaintance with C S Sherrington, FRS' in NR 1975-6 vol 30 pp 65-68</p>
      <p>R Singh and F Riess, 'The nobel laureate Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman FRS and his contacts with the British Scientific community in a social and political context' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 47-64</p>
   </note>
</person>