<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8289">
   <persName>
      <forename>William</forename>
      <surname>Thomson</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>Baron Kelvin of Largs</roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1824 - 1907</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: College Square East, Belfast (26 June 1824)</p>
      <p>Death: Netherhall, near Largs, Ayrshire (17 December 1907)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow, St Peter's College, Cambridge; Professor of Natural Philosophy, University of Glasgow.</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1866; Baron Kelvin 1892; GCVO 1896; OM 1902</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 5/06/1851</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Royal Medal 1856; Copley Medal 1883</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1856</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1890-1895</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc Series A 1908 vol 81 pp iii-lxxvi, three plates, signed by J L</p>
      <p>References: J S Rowlinson, 'Energy in the 19th Century', review of Crosbie Smith, The Science of Energy. A Cultural History of Energy Physics in Victorian Britain in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 281-282</p>
      <p>Sir Brian Pippard, 'Genius in Context', review of P M Harman, The Natural Philosophy of James Clerk Maxwell in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 279-281</p>
      <p>John Varley Jeffery, 'The Varley Family: Engineers and Artists' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 263-279</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, review of Crosbie Smith and M Norton Wise, Energy and Empire: a Biographical Study of Lord Kelvin in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 122-124</p>
      <p>Colin A Russell, review of Donald S L Cardwell, James Joule: A Biography in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 311-313</p>
      <p>P M Harman, 'Newton to Maxwell: the Principia and British Physics' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 75-96</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, 'Between Two Scientific Generations: John Herschel's Rejection of the Conservation of Energy in His 1864 Correspondence With William Thomson' in NR 1985-86 vol 40 pp 53-62</p>
      <p>Frank A J L James, 'The Conservation of Energy, Theories of Absorption and Resonating Molecules, 1851-1854: G G Stokes, A J Angstrom and W Thomson' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 79-107</p>
      <p>David Gooding, 'A Convergence of Opinion on the Divergence of Lines: Faraday and Thomson's Discussion of Diamagnetism' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 243-259</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'The Theory of Glaciers' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 189-204</p>
      <p>Otto Mayr, 'Victorian Physicists and Speed Regulation: An Encounter Between Science and Technology' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 205-228</p>
      <p>Paul A Tunbridge, 'A Letter by William Thomson, FRS, on the "Thomson Effect"' in NR 1971 vol 26 pp 229-232</p>
      <p>J T Lloyd, 'Background to the Joule-Mayer Controversy' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 211-225</p>
      <p>Vanity Fair 29 April 1897 - "Natural Philosophy" by 'Spy'</p>
      <p>Graeme Gooday, 'A Victorian scientist and engineer', review of Gillian Cookson and Colin Hempstead, 'Fleeming Jenkin and the birth of electrical engineering' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 265-266</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'The work of Thomas Andrews and James Thomson on the liquefaction of gases' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 143-159</p>
      <p>W Hayes, 'Physics as well as poetry. Physicists of Ireland, edited by M McCartney and A Whitaker' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 245-246</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson 'Which Kelvin? Degrees Kelvin: a tale of genius, invention, and tragedy, by D Lindley' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 339-342</p>
      <p>T Quinn, 'The Palace of Westminster frescoes, Kelvin's secretary and the Calcutta School of Tropical Medicine', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 135-137</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Dr Thomas Carver and Lord Kelvin', in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 161-170</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>Physicist</term>
   </note>
</person>