<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8253">
   <persName>
      <forename>Johannes</forename>
      <surname>Hevelius</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1611 - 1687</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Danzig [Gdańsk], Poland, Europe (28 January 1611)</p>
      <p>Death: Danzig [Gdańsk], Poland, Europe (28 January 1687)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Astronomer</p>
      <p>Research Field: Astronomy; instrument making</p>
      <p>Education: Danzig Gymnasium; School at Bydgoszcz; Leyden (admitted 1630)</p>
      <p>Career: Visited London (1631) and Paris (1632-1634); worked in his father's brewery for two years and ran it after his father's death (1649); Magistrate (1641); City Counsellor (1651); built an observatory in his house, which was destroyed by a fire (1679) along with his instruments, workshop, printing press and books and papers, and reconstructed, though with inferior instruments (1681)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 30/03/1664</p>
      <p>Proposer: Sir Robert Moray</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Astronomical and Optical Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Elected on the same day he was proposed.</p>
      <p>Acted as a frequent correspondent to the Society on astronomical matters, including the sending of star catalogues.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB; Hunter; Encyclopaedia Britannica</p>
      <p>References: G H Turnbull, 'Samuel Hartlib's Influence on the Early History of the Royal Society' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 101-130</p>
      <p>Sir Harold Spencer Jones, 'Halley as an Astronomer' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 175-192</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>Albert Van Helden, 'Christopher Wren's De Corpore Saturni' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 213-229</p>
      <p>N S Hetherington, 'The Hevelius-Auzout Controversy' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 103-106</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society's Role in the Diffusion of Information in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 173-192</p>
      <p>P B Wood, 'Hevelius's Business: An Unpublished Letter from Henry Oldenburg to the Earl of Tweeddale' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 25-29</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Ladies in the Scientific Revolution' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 1-12</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Our Foreign Correspondence' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 179-182</p>
      <p>Notes: Proposed by Sir Robert Moray. Alternative version of surname appears in R and BR, alternative version of Christian name in Hunter.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>astronomer</term>
   </note>
</person>