<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8283">
   <persName>
      <forename>George Gabriel</forename>
      <surname>Stokes</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1819 - 1903</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Skreen, County Sligo, Ireland (13 August 1819)</p>
      <p>Death: Cambridge (01 February 1903)</p>
      <p>Burial: Mill Road cemetery, Cambridge</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Physics</p>
      <p>Education: MA</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow, Pembroke College, Cambridge; Lucasian Professor of Mathematics, University of Cambridge.</p>
      <p>Honours: Bt 1889</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 5/06/1851</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Rumford Medal 1852; Copley Medal 1893</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1854-1885; PRS 1885-1890; VP 1890-1892</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Proc Roy Soc 1905 vol 75 pp 199-216, plate, signed by H</p>
      <p>References: Frank A J L James, 'The Conservation of Energy, Theories of Absorption and Resonating Molecules, 1851-1854: G G Stokes, A J Angstrom and W Thomson' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 79-107</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society in Thomas Henry Huxley's Time' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 153-158</p>
      <p>W V Farrar, 'Edward Schunck, FRS. A Pioneer of Natural Product Chemistry' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 273-296</p>
      <p>John R Levene, 'Sir George Biddell Airy, FRS (1801-1892) and the Discovery and Correction of Astigmatism' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 180-199</p>
      <p>Alex D D Craik, 'James Ivory's last papers on the 'Figure of the Earth' (with biographical additions) in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 187-204</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'The work of Thomas Andrews and James Thomson on the liquefaction of gases' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 143-159</p>
      <p>W Hayes, 'Physics as well as poetry. Physicists of Ireland, edited by M McCartney and A Whitaker' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 245-246</p>
      <p>R Iliffe and J Young, 'Report. Newton on the net: first and prospective fruits of a Royal Society grant' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 83-88</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Lucasian Professors. From Newton to Hawking: a history of Cambridge University's Lucasian professors of mathematics, ed K C Knox and R Noakes' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 312-313</p>
      <p>G Ferrari and A McConnell, 'Robert Mallet and the 'Great Neapolitan earthquake' of 1857 in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 45-64</p>
   </note>
</person>