<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8378">
   <persName>
      <forename>Martin</forename>
      <surname>Folkes</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1690 - 1754</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Westminster, London, England, United Kingdom, Europe (29 October 1690)</p>
      <p>Death: Ormond Street, London, England, United Kingdom, Europe (28 June 1754)</p>
      <p>Burial: The chancel of Hillington Church, Norfolk, England, United Kingdom, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Antiquarianism</p>
      <p>Education: Clare College, Cambridge (matriculated 1709); MA (Com. Reg. 1717); Saumur; Oxford DCL (1746); Incorporated at Cambridge (1747)</p>
      <p>Career: Travelled to Italy with his family (1733-1735) and to Paris (1739); died of a paralytic attack; he left £200 and his seal ring to the Royal Society; the sale of his library, prints, drawings, gems, pictures, coins, etc lasted 56 days; memorial in south aisle of the choir of Westminster Abbey</p>
      <p>Memberships: French Academy (1742); Fellow of the Society for Antiquaries (1720, President 1750-1754); Spalding Society; Académie Royale des Sciences, Paris (Foreign Fellow, 1742)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 29/07/1714</p>
      <p>Proposer: Fettisplace Bellers and Sir Hans Sloane</p>
      <p>Council: VP 1722/3, 1733-1741; Council 1716, 1718-1726, 1729-1730; PRS 1741-1752</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Presented a variety of papers, mostly on astronomy, to the Society and published in the 'Philosophical Transactions'.</p>
      <p>Proposed to convert Sir Godfrey Copley's donation for an annual experiment into an honorary prize, the Copley Medal (10 November 1736).</p>
      <p>Member and later Preisdent of the Club of Royal Philosophers [later: Royal Society Club].</p>
      <p>Bequeathed £100 to the Royal Society after his death, along with a seal and a portrait of Francis Bacon.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Thomas; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: Richard Sorrenson, 'Towards a History of the Royal Society in the Eighteenth Century' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 29-46, plate</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'Edmond Halley and the Clubs of the Royal Society' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 195-205</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'The Diaries of John Byrom, MA, FRS, and their Relation to the Pre-history of the Royal Society Club' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 162-183</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'A Note on the Correspondence of Martin Folkes' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 100-109</p>
      <p>A N L Munby, 'The Distribution of the First Edition of Newton's Principia' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 28-39</p>
      <p>'Gentleman's Magazine' 1754, p292</p>
      <p>Sir John Hill 'Review of the Works of the Royal Society' 1761</p>
      <p>Notes: DSB gives death date as 29 June 1754</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>antiquary and natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>