<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8374">
   <persName>
      <forename>Francis</forename>
      <surname>Willughby</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1635 - 1672</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Middleton, Warwickshire, England, Europe (22 November 1635)</p>
      <p>Death: Middleton Hall, Warwickshire, England, Europe (3 July 1672)</p>
      <p>Burial: Middleton Church, Warwickshire, England, Europe</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: zoology; natural history</p>
      <p>Education: Sutton Coldfield School; Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1655/6; MA 1659); studied at the Bodleian Library, Oxford (1660)</p>
      <p>Career: Accompanied John Ray (FRS 1667) on botanical research trips through Warwickshire and Nottinghamshire (1660-1662); travelled extensively in Europe (1663-1666) and to the south-west of England with Ray (1667); his work 'Ornithology' published posthumously by Ray (1676; 1678)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Proposers: John Wilkins (20 November 1661)</p>
      <p>Admitted 4 December 1661 and 1 October 1662</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee for the Histories of Trade (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Involved in experiments and demonstrations of botanical and zoological nature (1662).</p>
      <p>Pledged £80 in support of the Royal Society College at Arundel House (1667-1668).</p>
      <p>Frequent correspondent to the Society and sent independent reseach in natural history.</p>
      <p>'Historia piscium' published posthumously by the Royal Society (1686).</p>
      <p>'Historia insectorum' published posthumously by the Royal Society (1710), having been edited by William Derham (FRS 1703).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster; ODNB</p>
      <p>References: R K Bluhm, 'Remarks on the Royal Society's Finances, 1660-1768' in NR 1958 vol 13 pp 82-103</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>Charles A Rivington, 'Early Printers to the Royal Society 1663-1708' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 1-27</p>
      <p>William T Stearn, 'The Wilkins Lecture, 1985. John Wilkins, John Ray and Carl Linnaeus' in NR 1985-86 vol 40 pp 101-123</p>
      <p>Sachiko Kusukawa, 'The Historia Piscium (1686)' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 179-197</p>
      <p>Susan McMahon, 'John Ray (1627-1705) and the Act of Uniformity 1662' in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 153-178</p>
      <p>R Lewis, 'The publication of John Wilkins's Essay (1668): some contextual considerations' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp133-146</p>
      <p>N J W Thrower, 'Samuel Pepys FRS (1633-1733) and The Royal Society' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 3-13</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Willughby's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 4 December 1661 and 1 October 1662 .The double admission dates are taken from the Journal Book.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>naturalist</term>
   </note>
</person>