<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8406">
   <persName>
      <forename>Hans</forename>
      <surname>Sloane</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1660 - 1753</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Killyleagh or White's Castle, County Down, Ireland, Europe (16 April 1660)</p>
      <p>Death: Chelsea, London, England, Europe (11 January 1753)</p>
      <p>Burial: Chelsea Old Church, London, England, Europe (18 January 1753)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Physician</p>
      <p>Research Field: Medicine; natural history; botany</p>
      <p>Education: Killyleagh school; when removed from school due to poor health continued education supported by the Hamilton Family of Killyleagh Castle; studied medicine at Apothecaries Hall, London (1679-1883); Pupil of Joseph Pitton de Tournefort, at the Jardin Royal, Paris and Montpellier (1683-1684); University of Orange (MD 1683); University of Oxford (DMed, by diploma 1701)</p>
      <p>Career: Went to Jamaica as personal physician to the 2nd Duke of Albemarle, Governor of Jamaica, where he worked as a doctor on slave plantations whilst collecting over 800 botanical specimens and other items of natural history with the assistance of planters and enslaved Africans (1687-1689); practised medicine in Bloomsbury, Middlesex (1689-1741); published multiple papers on his observations in Jamaica (1680s); Physician, Christ's Hospital (1694-1730); carried out the autopsy of Samuel Pepys PRS (1703); purchased the manor of Chelsea, Middlesex (1712); physician to Queen Anne and George I (1712-1727); Physician to the Army (1714); first British physician to receive a baronetcy (1716); founded the Botanic Garden at Chelsea on behalf of the Society of Apothecaries (1721); First Physician to George II (1727); experimented with inoculation of smallpox inoculating the children of the Princess of Wales; also advocated the use of quinine in treatment of malaria and eye ailments; one of the promoters of the colony of Georgia (1732); a founding governor of London's Foundling Hospital (1739), retired from general practice (1741); benefactor to Christ's Hospital and the Bodleian Library and to many other individuals and institutions; bequeathed his collection to King and Parliament in return for a payment of £20,000 to his heirs (his collection was estimated to have cost him £100,000). The bequest was accepted and on 7 June 1753 the British Museum act became law, establishing the first national museum freely open to the public, the Sloane collections forming the nucleus of the British Museum (around 200,000 specimens)</p>
      <p>Honours: Bt 1716</p>
      <p>Memberships: Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians (1687, President 1719-1735)</p>
      <p>Foreign Member of the Royal Prussian Academy of Sciences (1712)</p>
      <p>Member of the Academy of Science of St Petersburg and of Madrid (1735)</p>
      <p>Member of the Academy of Sciences of Göttingen (1752)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 21/01/1685</p>
      <p>Proposers: Martin Lister (29 November 1684)</p>
      <p>Council: 1690-1699; Secretary 1693-1713; PRS 1727-1741; VP 1703-1704, 1704-?, 1715-?, 1722-?</p>
      <p>Editor Phil. Trans.: 1696-1713</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Committee to inspect the Books and Papers of the Society (1692)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Commissioned a variety of experiments and observations, e.g. in the field of natural history</p>
      <p>Presented papers and collected specimens to the Society, e.g. Jamaican pepper tree</p>
      <p>Listed as a principal benefactor with donation of £100 (1710)</p>
      <p>As secretary and subsequent editor of the 'Philosophical Transactions', Sloane was instrumental in revitalising the publication and his wide network of correspondents contributed to communication published in the 'Transactions'. During this time, he was also involved in a somewhat public feud with John Woodward (FRS 1693), who disagreed with Sloane's administrative style and qualification and insulted him during a presentation of a paper before the Society in 1710. Woodward refused to apologise for the insult and was soon after expelled.</p>
      <p>As president, Sloane proposed multiple chnages in 1728. In part, these aimed at securing subscriptions from Fellows who were in arrears under the threat of potential legal action. Additionally, under Sloane a new procedure and documentation for the election of new Fellows was introduced, which aimed at limiting the number of Fellows admitted annually.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; GEC Baronetage; Hunter; Foster; Irish Innovators; ODNB</p>
      <p>Delbourgo, J. 2017. 'Collecting the World: The Life and Curiosity of Hans Sloane' (Allen Lane)</p>
      <p>References: W H G Armytage, 'The Royal Society and the Apothecaries' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 22-37</p>
      <p>W H G Armytage, 'Sir Godfrey Copley, FRS (1653-1709). Some Tercentenary Glimpses through Letters to his Friends' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 54-74</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'The Diaries of John Byrom, MA, FRS, and their Relation to the Pre-history of the Royal Society Club' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 162-183</p>
      <p>John Thomas, 'Josiah Wedgwood's Portrait Medallions of Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 45-53, plate</p>
      <p>Jessie M Sweet, 'Sir Hans Sloane's Metalline Cubes' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 99-100</p>
      <p>Jessie M Sweet, 'Benjamin Franklin's Purse' in NR 1952 vol 9 pp 308-309</p>
      <p>Jean Jacquot, 'Sir Hans Sloane and French Men of Science' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 85-98</p>
      <p>G R de Beer, 'The Relations between Fellows of the Royal Society and French Men of Science when France and Britain were at War' in NR 1952 vol 9 pp 244-299</p>
      <p>G R de Beer, 'Sir Hans Sloane, FRS, 1660-1753' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 81-84, plate</p>
      <p>H G Lyons, 'Two Hundred Years Ago: 1739' in NR 1939 vol 2 pp 34-42</p>
      <p>Geoffrey Cantor, 'Quakers in the Royal Society, 1660-1750' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 175-193</p>
      <p>Harold B Carter, 'The Royal Society and the Voyage of HMS Endeavour 1768-71' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 245-260</p>
      <p>John H Appleby, 'The Royal Society and the Tartar Lamb' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 23-34</p>
      <p>L Taub, 'Collecting Curiosities', review of Jan Bondeson, A Cabinet of Medical Curiosities in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 371-372</p>
      <p>Richard Sorrenson, 'Towards a History of the Royal Society in the Eighteenth Century' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 29-46, plate</p>
      <p>M Yakup Bektas and Maurice Crosland, 'The Copley Medal: the Establishment of a Reward System in the Royal Society, 1731-1839' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 43-76</p>
      <p>Ruth Stungo, 'The Royal Society Specimens from the Chelsea Physic Garden 1722-1799' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 213-224</p>
      <p>T E Allibone, 'Philately and the Royal Society' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 129-154</p>
      <p>A E Gunther, 'The Royal Society and the Foundation of the British Museum, 1753-1781' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 207-216</p>
      <p>Frank N Egerton, 'Richard Bradley's Relationship with Sir Hans Sloane' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 59-77</p>
      <p>John H Appleby, 'Ginseng and the Royal Society' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 121-145</p>
      <p>John R Millburn, 'Benjamin Martin and the Royal Society' in NR 1973-4 vol 28 pp 15-23</p>
      <p>P Fontes da Costa, 'The Culture of Curiosity at The Royal Society in the first half of the eighteenth century', NR 2002 vo l56 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>J H Appleby, 'The founding of St Petersburg in the context of the Royal Society's relationship with Russia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 273-284</p>
      <p>W P Griffith and P J T Morris, 'Charles Hatchett FRS (1765 - 1847), chemist and discoverer of niobium' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 299 - 316</p>
      <p>W Ramsey, P Daniels, E G Ramsey, 'The Limehouse Porcelain Factory - its output, antecedents, and the influence of the Royal Society of London on the evolution of English porcelain based on composition and technology. ' Published Inverscafgill, New Zealand, January 2013</p>
      <p>Notes: A large part of Sloane's correspondence is held at the British Library, with letters being transcribed and described by the Sloane Letters Project [https://sloaneletters.com/; last accessed 23/02/2022]</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physician and collector</term>
   </note>
</person>