<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8411">
   <persName>
      <forename>Nehemiah</forename>
      <surname>Grew</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1641 - 1712</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Mancetter, Warwickshire, England</p>
      <p>Baptism: (26 September 1641)</p>
      <p>Death: 25 March 1712</p>
      <p>Burial: The Dodson family vault, Cheshunt parish church, Hertfordshire</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Plant morphology, plant anatomy; Chemistry</p>
      <p>Education: Pembroke College, Cambridge; BA (1649/50); Leyden; probably MD (c1671)</p>
      <p>Career: Practised in Coventry (1671) and then in London; Editor of 'Philosophical Transactions' (1678-1679); compiled a catalogue of the Royal Society's repository; died suddenly while going on his rounds</p>
      <p>Memberships: Hon FRCP (1680)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 2/11/1671</p>
      <p>Proposers: Robert Hooke</p>
      <p>Council: Sec 1677-1679; Council 1675, 1677-83, 1690, 1692; Plant Anatomy Curator 1672-1673</p>
      <p>Editor Phil. Trans.:1677-1679</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Hunter; Innes Smith</p>
      <p>References: Janet Browne, review of William LeFanu, Nehemiah Grew, MD, FRS: A Study and Bibliography of His Writings in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 115-116</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Early Years of the Royal Society', review of Michael Hunter, Establishing the New Science: the Experience of the Early Royal Society in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 265-268</p>
      <p>Charles A Rivington, 'Addendum. Early Printers to the Royal Society, 1663-1708' in NR 1985-86 vol 40 pp 219-220</p>
      <p>A D C Simpson, 'Newton's Telescope and the Cataloguing of the Royal Society's Repository' in NR 1983-84 vol 38 pp 187-214</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'Early Problems in Professionalizing Scientific Research: Nehemiah Grew (1641-1712) and the Royal Society, With an Unpublished Letter to Henry Oldenburg' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 189-209</p>
      <p>Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>Jeanne Bolam, 'The Botanical Works of Nehemiah Grew, FRS (1641-1712)' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 219-231</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>botanist and physiologist</term>
   </note>
</person>