<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8450">
   <persName>
      <forename>Gottfried Wilhelm von</forename>
      <surname>Leibniz</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1646 - 1716</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Leipzig, Germany (? 21 June 1646)</p>
      <p>Death: Hanover, Germany (14 November 1716)</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Civil servant</p>
      <p>Research field: Mathematics, philosophy, metaphysics</p>
      <p>Education: Nicolai School; Leipzig (admitted 1661); Jena (admitted 1663); Altdorf; LLD (1666)</p>
      <p>Career: Employed by the Elector Johann Philipp von Schonborn of Mainz as an adviser on legal matters (1667); began work on his calculating machine (1671); went on a diplomatic missions to Paris (1672) and London (1673); on the death of the Elector, went to Paris, hoping for a post at the Academie des Sciences, but was disappointed; visited Antoni van Leeuwenhoek (FRS 1680); Adviser and Librarian to the Duke of Hannover (1676); Councillor at the Court of Hannover (1679); travelled through Germany and Italy in order to prepare a genealogy of the house of Brunswick and visited Vincenzo Viviani (FRS 1696) in Florence and Marcello Malpighi (FRS 1665) in Bologna (1687-1689); Privy Councillor in Hannover; in the service of Sophia Charlotte, Electress of Brandenburg (1700); involved in a dispute about calculus with Isaac Newton (FRS 1672), in which he was accused of plagiarism, a charge which was upheld by a commission of the Royal Society (1712); Privy Councillor to Peter the Great of Russia (1712); Imperial Privy Councillor at Vienna (1712-1714); returned to Hannover and unsuccessfully petitioned the Elector, now George I of Great Britain, for a post (1714)</p>
      <p>Memberships: Accademia Fisico-matematica, Rome; Berlin Academy (1700, Founder and President for life)</p>
      
      <p>Fellowship: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election date: 9/04/1673</p>
      <p>Proposers: Sir Robert Moray</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DSB</p>
      <p>References: Sir Alan Cook, 'The 350th Anniversary of the Birth of G W Leibniz, FRS' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 153-163, plate</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Personality of Isaac Newton' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 1-56</p>
      <p>Derek Massarella, 'Philip Henry Zollman, the Royal Society's First Assistant Secretary for Foreign Correspondence' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 219-234</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'The Prehistory of the Principia from 1664 to 1686' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 11-61</p>
      <p>G J Whitrow, 'Newton's Role in the History of Mathematics' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 71-92</p>
      <p>E A Fellmann, 'The Principia and Continental Mathematicians' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 13-34</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'The Royal Society's Role in the Diffusion of Information in the Seventeenth Century' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 173-192</p>
      <p>Joan L Hawes, 'Newton's Revival of the Aether Hypothesis and the Explanation of Gravitational Attraction' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 200-212</p>
      <p>R E W Maddison, 'Studies in the Life of Robert Boyle, FRS. Part IV. Robert Boyle and Some of his Foreign Visitors' in NR 1954-55 vol 11 pp 38-53</p>
      <p>M Greenwood, 'The First Life Table' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 70-72</p>
      <p>R Lewis, 'The publication of John Wilkins's Essay (1668): some contextual considerations' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp133-146</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Charles Babbage and his world' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 353-365</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Le Sage's Essai de chymie mechanique' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 35-45</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Rome and the Royal Society, 1660-1740' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 3-19</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Theatrical Science. C Djerassi and D Pinner, Newton's darkness: two dramatic views' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 237-238</p>
      <p>M Bailey Ogilvie, 'In her place. Pandora's breeches: women, science and power in the enlightenment, by P Fara' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 314-315</p>
   </note>
</person>