<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8428">
   <persName>
      <forename>Peter</forename>
      <surname>Collinson</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1694 - 1768</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 94 Lombard Street, London, England (January 1694)</p>
      <p>Death: Thorndon Hall, Brentwood, Essex (11 August 1768)</p>
      <p>Burial: Long Lane burial-ground, Bermondsey, London</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Mercer</p>
      <p>Research Field: Natural history, dissemination of science</p>
      <p>Education: Quaker school at Wandsworth, Surrey</p>
      <p>Career: Took over the family business with his brother James and improved it by extensive trading with the American colonies; helped Mark Catesby (FRS 1733) to find patrons in America; Sir Hans Sloane (FRS 1685) encouraged his interest in the metamorphosis of insects, much of his collection was deposited in Sloane's museum and he later contributed to the British Museum; his gardens at Peckham and Mill Hill were known for their exotics and he is credited with introducing or reintroducing 180 species into England; encouraged the cultivation of silk, flax, hemp and wines in America; London agent for the Library Company of Philadelphia (1732); corresponded with Benjamin Franklin (FRS 1756) and other scientists in America, Europe and elsewhere;</p>
      <p>Memberships: FSA; Berlin Academy; Uppsala Academy</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 5/12/1728</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; DQB</p>
      <p>References: H G Lyons, 'Two Hundred Years Ago: 1739' in NR 1939 vol 2 pp 34-42</p>
      <p>R V Jones, 'Benjamin Franklin' in NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 201-225</p>
      <p>John H Appleby, 'Ginseng and the Royal Society' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 121-145</p>
      <p>Geoffrey Cantor, 'Quakers in the Royal Society, 1660-1750' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 175-193</p>
      <p>Obituary, Gentleman's Magazine (1768) p 398</p>
      <p>Notes: DNB gives birth date of 14 January 1694 and birth place near Windermere. DSB agrees with DQB date of 28 January and is corroborated by Quaker Register of births. DNB gives father-in-law as Mr Bushell of Mill Hill, Hendon, Middlesex. Proposed by Sylvanus Bevan; Sir Hans Sloane; John Gaspar Scheuchzer</p>
   </note>
</person>