<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8424">
   <persName>
      <forename>Charles</forename>
      <surname>Howard</surname>
   </persName>
   <persName type="additional" subtype="title">
      <roleName>1st Earl of Carlisle </roleName>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1629 - 1685</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 04 February 1628</p>
      <p>Death: Henderskelfe House [present site Castle Howard], Bulmer, North Yorkshire, England, United Kingdom (24 Februay 1685)</p>
      <p>Burial: York Minster</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Soldier; politician; government official; diplomat; colonial governor</p>
      <p>Career: Charged with bearing arms for King Charles I during the English Civil War, and fined (1646); travelled in Holland (1646-1647); High Sheriff of Cumberland (1650); Governor of Carlisle (1650-1660, 1678-1685; fought on the Parliamentary side at the Battle of Worcester, with the rank of Captain, and wounded (1651); MP for Westmoreland (1653), Cumberland (1654, 1656, 1660); Member of the Council of State (1653, 1655-1658); Captain of the Lord Protector's Bodyguard (1654); Colonel of a regiment of horse (1655, 1660); Councillor of State for Scotland (1655); Deputy Major-General of Cumberland, Northumberland and Westmoreland (1655); created Lord Gilsland and Viscount Howard of Morpeth by Oliver Cromwell (1657); imprisoned, paroled, and re-arrested to the Tower of London, for high treason, but released (1659); Privy Councillor (1660); Custos Rotulorum for Essex (1660); Lord Lieutenant of Cumberland and Westmoreland (1660); after the Restoration created Baron Dacre of Gillesland, Viscount Howard of Morpeth, and earl of Carlisle by King Charles II (20 April 1661) Vice-Admiral of Northumberland, Cumberland and Durham (1661); Member of the Royal Adventurers into Africa (1661-1672); Joint-Commissioner for the office of Earl Marshal (1662); Ambassador extraordinary to Russia, Poland, Sweden and Denmark (1663-1664); Commissioner for Prizes (1664-1667); Captain of a troop of horse (1666); Captain in Prince Rupert's regiment of horse (1667); Member of Society of Mines Royal (1667); Ambassador extraordinary to Sweden (1668); Lord Lieutenant of Durham (1672); Colonel of a regiment of foot (1673); Deputy Earl Marshal of England (1673); Member, Company of the Royal Fishery of England (1677); Governor of Jamaica (1677-1681) in which capacity he unsuccesfully attempted to assert greater British legislative control over the Jamaican Assembly (made up of plantation and slave owners); retired to Cumberland (1680)</p>
      <p>Honours: Baron Gilsland and Viscount Howard of Morpeth 1657; Baron Dacre of Gillesland, Viscount Howard of Morpeth, and Earl of Carlisle 1661</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 14/06/1665</p>
      <p>Proposers: Sir Paul Neile</p>
      <p>Expelled (1682)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; ODNB; GEC; Hunter; Henning</p>
      <p>References: H. Cary (ed.), 'Memorials of the great civil war in England from 1646 to 1652...' (London, 1842)</p>
      <p>Frank Cundall, 'The governors of Jamaica in the seventeenth century' (London, 1936)</p>
      <p>B. D. Henning (ed.), 'The history of Parliament: the House of Commons 1660-1690' (London, 1983)</p>
      <p>Mark Govier, 'The Royal Society, Slavery and the Island of Jamaica: 1660-1700' in NR 1999 vol 53 pp 203-217</p>
      <p>Christopher Durston, 'Cromwell's Major-Generals: godly government during the English Revolution' (Manchester UP, 2001)</p>
      <p>Steve Murdoch and Alexia Grosjean, SSNE Database, individual entry SSNE 1877 [records of British and Irish activity in Scandinavia and the Baltic States], Institute of Historical Research, University of St. Andrews (1995-2021).</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>army officer and politician</term>
   </note>
</person>