<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8442">
   <persName>
      <forename>Jonas</forename>
      <surname>Moore</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1617 - 1679</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Whitelee or Whittle, Lancashire, England (08 February 1617)</p>
      <p>Death: Godalming, Surrey (25 August 1679)</p>
      <p>Burial: Tower Chapel, London</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Mathematics</p>
      <p>Education: Pupil of William Oughtred</p>
      <p>Career: Clerk under Dr Burghill, Chancellor of Durham; Mathematical Tutor to the Duke of York (1647); set up as a teacher of mathematics in London but failed to get pupils; under the patronage of Giles Strangeways (FRS 1673), became Surveyor for the draining of the Fens (1649); Surveyor of Tangier (1663); Surveyor-General of the Ordnance; invited John Flamsteed (FRS 1677) to London; Governor of Christ's Hospital; instrumental in the foundation of the Royal Greenwich Observatory and the Mathematical School at Christ's Hospital; died suddenly while travelling from Portsmouth to London; buried with a 62-gun salute; collected a splendid library of scientific works in many languages which was sold at auction after his death</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1663</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 3/12/1674</p>
      <p>Proposers: William, Viscount Brouncker</p>
      <p>Council: VP 1676-; Council 1675-1678</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; Hunter; Aubrey</p>
      <p>References: A J Meadows, 'John Flamsteed, Our Astronomical Observator', review of The Correspondence of John Flamsteed, First Astronomer Royal. Volume I (1666-1682), ed. Eric G Forbes et al, in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 250-253</p>
      <p>Marie Boas Hall, 'Surveyor of the Restoration', review of Frances Willmoth, Sir Jonas Moore: Practical Mathematics and Restoration Science in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 153-154</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Halley the Londoner' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 163-177</p>
   </note>
</person>