<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8419">
   <persName>
      <forename>John Theophilus</forename>
      <surname>Desaguliers</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1683 - 1744</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: La Rochelle, France (10 or 13 March 1683)</p>
      <p>Death: His lodgings at the Bedford Coffee House, Covent Garden (29 February 1744)</p>
      <p>Burial: The Savoy Chapel, Strand, Westminster</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Natural Philosopher and Engineer</p>
      <p>Research Field: Experimental natural philosophy</p>
      <p>Education: Christ Church, Oxford); Hart Hall, Oxford. BA (1709), MA (1712), DCL (1719). Incorporated LLD at Cambridge (1726)</p>
      <p>Career: Brought to England by his parents after the Revocation of the Edict of Nantes, he was rumoured to have been smuggled on board ship in a barrel (1685); Assistant in his father's school at Islington, Middlesex; ordained deacon (1710); Lecturer on Experimental Philosophy at Hart Hall (1710); Demonstrator and Curator to the Royal Society (1714); Chaplain to James Brydges, Duke of Chandos (FRS 1694) (1714); Rector of Little Stanmore, Middlesex (1715-1744); Rector of Bridgham, Norfolk (1717-1726); Chaplain to Frederick, Prince of Wales (c1717); Rector of Little Warley, Essex (1727-1744); lectured and performed experiments before a wide audience at his London house and later in Holland (1730), where he drew the interest of Herman Boerhaave (FRS 1730)</p>
      <p>Memberships: Freemason, Member, Lodge no 3 at Horn Tavern Westminster, London, subsequently Royal Somerset House and Inverness Lodge No 4; Grand Master of the Premier Grand Lodge, nicknamed the 'Moderns' 1719;</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 29/07/1714</p>
      <p>Proposers: Sir Hans Sloane; Sir Isaac Newton.</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1734, 1736 and 1741</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster</p>
      <p>References: Henry Guerlac, 'Newton's Optical Aether: his Draft of a Proposed Addition to his Opticks' in NR 1967 vol 22 pp 45-57</p>
      <p>J A Lohne, 'Experimentum Crucis' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 169-199</p>
      <p>Stephen F Mason, 'The Spring-Tide of Experimental Philosophy', review of Marie Boas Hall, Promoting Experimental Learning: Experiment and the Royal Society, 1660-1727 in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 313-316</p>
      <p>Alan Q Morton, 'Previous Public Perceptions of Science', review of Larry Stewart, The Rise of Public Science: Rhetoric, Technology and Natural Philosophy in Newtonian Britain, 1660-1750 and Jan Golinski, Science as Public Culture: Chemistry and Enlightenment in Britain, 1760-1820 in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 157-159</p>
      <p>John H Appleby, 'Human Curiosities and the Royal Society, 1699-1751' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 13-27</p>
      <p>Marta Cavazza, 'The Institute of Science of Bologna and the Royal Society in the eighteenth century' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 3-25, plate</p>
      <p>'Gentleman's Magazine' 1744, p168</p>
      <p>P Fontes da Costa, 'The Culture of Curiosity at The Royal Society in the first half of the eighteenth century', NR 2002 vo l56 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>J P Zinsser, 'The ultimate commentary: a consideration of I Bernhard Cohen's Guide to Newton's Principia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 231-238</p>
      <p>The Library and Museum of Freemasonry 'Freemasons and the Royal Society; Alphabetical List of Fellows of the Royal Society who were Freemasons' 2010, page 26</p>
      <p>Notes: DSB provides birth and death dates, 12 March 1683 and 10 March 1744 respectively. Venn gives death date as 29 February 1744</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher</term>
   </note>
</person>