<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8414">
   <persName>
      <forename>Isaac</forename>
      <surname>Newton</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1642 - 1727</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Woolsthorpe manor-house, Colsterworth, near Grantham, Lincolnshire, England (25 December 1642)</p>
      <p>Death: Kensington, London, England (20 March 1727)</p>
      <p>Burial: Westminster Abbey, London, England</p>
      
      <p>Research Field: Mathematics, dynamics, mechanics, celestial mechanics, astronomy, optics, natural philosophy</p>
      <p>Education: Grantham Grammar School; Trinity College, Cambridge, BA (1665), MA (1668)</p>
      <p>Career: Left Cambridge because of the plague and spent two years at Woolsthorpe, where he did most of the work on colours and mechanics, including gravity, later published in the 'Principia Mathematica' and 'Opticks' (1665-1667); Fellow of Trinity (1667-death); Lucasian Professor of Mathematics, Cambridge (1669-1701); MP for Cambridge University (1689, 1701); Warden of the Mint (1696); Master of the Mint (1699-death); Commissioner for Assessment for Cambridge, Cambridge University and Lincolnshire (1689-1690); acknowledged throughout Europe as a great scientist, philosopher and mathematician, he was involved in bitter controversies with Robert Hooke (FRS 1663), with Gottfried Wilhelm von Leibniz (FRS 1673) over the calculus and with John Flamsteed (FRS 1677) over the publication of his astronomical observations; his body lay in state in the Jerusalem Chamber, Westminster; Benefactor to the chapels of Christ's and Trinity Colleges, Cambridge and to Addenbrooke's Hospital</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1705</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 11/01/1672</p>
      <p>Proposers: Seth Ward</p>
      <p>Council: PRS 1703-1727; Council 1697, 1699</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Hunter; Venn; Henning</p>
      <p>AssocMaterial: Newton papers are available online, at (1) Newton Project, Sussex University - http://www.newtonproject.sussex.ac.uk/prism.php?id=1</p>
      <p>(2) Also at National Library of Israel - http://dlib.nli.org.il/R/?func=collections&amp;collection_id=7856</p>
      <p>Papers deposited at King's College Cambridge;</p>
      <p>References: John Hedley Brooke, 'Isaac's faith', review of James E Force and Richard H Popkin (eds) Newton and religion: context, nature and influence in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 113-115</p>
      <p>William Shea, 'Evolution not revolution', review of Margaret J Osler (ed) Rethinking the scientific revolution in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 106-107</p>
      <p>Marta Cavazza, 'The Institute of Science of Bologna and the Royal Society in the eighteenth century' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 3-25, plate</p>
      <p>Sir John Craig, 'The Royal Society and the Royal Mint' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 156-167</p>
      <p>Sir John Craig, 'Isaac Newton and the Counterfeiters' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 136-145</p>
      <p>S Chapman, 'Edmond Halley, FRS, 1656-1742' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 168-174</p>
      <p>Richard S Westfall, 'Short-writing and the State of Newton's Conscience, 1662' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 10-16</p>
      <p>R K Bluhm, 'Henry Oldenburg, FRS (c. 1615-1677)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 183-197</p>
      <p>Margaret Deacon, 'Founders of Marine Science in Britain: the Work of the Early Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 28-50</p>
      <p>Lord Adrian, 'Newton's Rooms in Trinity' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 17-24</p>
      <p>John Thomas, 'Josiah Wedgwood's Portrait Medallions of Fellows of the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 45-53, plate</p>
      <p>James L Axtell, 'Locke's Review of the Principia' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 152-161</p>
      <p>J F Scott, 'The Reverend John Wallis, FRS (1616-1703)' in NR 1960 vol 15 pp 57-67</p>
      <p>J E McGuire and P M Rattansi, 'Newton and the "Pipes of Pan"' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 108-143</p>
      <p>J A Lohne, 'Isaac Newton: the Rise of a Scientist 1661-1671' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 125-139</p>
      <p>I Bernard Cohen, '"Quantum in se est": Newton's Concept of Inertia in Relation to Descartes and Lucretius' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 131-155</p>
      <p>Henry Guerlac, 'Newton's Optical Aether: his Draft of a Proposed Addition to his Opticks' in NR 1967 vol 22 pp 45-57</p>
      <p>H A Feisenberger, 'The Libraries of Newton, Hooke and Boyle' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 42-55</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'The Birth and Early Days of the Philosophical Transactions' in NR 1965 vol 20 pp 9-27</p>
      <p>E N da C Andrade, 'Samuel Pepys and the Royal Society' in NR 1963 vol 18 pp 82-93</p>
      <p>Douglas McKie, 'Bernard le Bovier de Fontenelle, FRS, 1657-1757' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 193-200</p>
      <p>D McKie and G R de Beer, 'Newton's Apple - an Addendum' in NR 1952 vol 9 pp 333-335</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'Newton's Marvellous Year: 1666 and All That' in NR 1966 vol 21 pp 32-41</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'Isaac Newton: Birth of a Mathematician' in NR 1964 vol 19 pp 53-62</p>
      <p>A N L Munby, 'The Keynes Collection of the Works of Sir Isaac Newton at King's College, Cambridge' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 40-50</p>
      <p>A N L Munby, 'The Distribution of the First Edition of Newton's Principia' in NR 1953 vol 10 pp 28-39</p>
      <p>A D Atkinson, 'The Royal Society and English Vocabulary' in NR 1956-57 vol 12 pp 40-43</p>
      <p>C S S, 'The Society's Library' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 21-27</p>
      <p>H W Robinson, 'Gleanings from the Library - I. A Note on the Early Minutes' in NR 1938 vol 1 pp 92-95</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'Cambridge: Newton's legacy' in NR 2001 vol 55 pp 205-226</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall and A D C Simpson, 'An Account of the Royal Society's Newton Telescope' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 1-11</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'Isaac Newton and the Aerial Nitre' in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 51-61</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'John Collins on Newton's Telescope' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 71-78</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'The Francis Affair Reconsidered' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 179-184</p>
      <p>A W F Edwards, 'Is the Frontispiece of Gulliver's Travels a Likeness of Newton?' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 191-194, plate</p>
      <p>D Lynden-Bell and R M Lynden-Bell, 'On the Shapes of Newton's Revolving Orbits' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 195-198</p>
      <p>D Lynden-Bell, 'The Wonderful Geometry of Dynamics', review of S Chandrasekhar, Newton's Principia for the Common Reader in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 253-255</p>
      <p>Milo Keynes, 'The Personality of Isaac Newton' in NR 1995 vol 49 pp 1-56, plate</p>
      <p>R Willach, 'New Light on the Invention of the Achromatic Telescope Objective' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 195-210</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Ladies in the Scientific Revolution' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 1-12</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Seeds of the Scientific Revolution', review of Edward Grant, The Foundations of Modern Science in the Middle Ages, Their Religious, Institutional and Intellectual Contexts and Benedino Gemelli, Aspetti dell'Atomismo classico nella Filosofia di Francis Bacon e nel Seicento, Accademia toscana di Scienze e Lettere "La Colombaria", 'Studi' CLII in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 327-334</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'The 350th Anniversary of the Birth of G W Leibniz, FRS' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 153-163</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'The Gatekeeper of the Modern World', review of Niccolo Guicciardini, Reading the Principia; The Debate on Newton's Mathematical Methods for Natural Philosophy from 1687 to 1736 in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 109-113</p>
      <p>Walter Munk, 'Solving the Tidal Problem', review of David E Cartwright, Tides: A Scientific History in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 116-119</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'A Practical Natural Philosopher', review of Alan Cook, Edmond Halley: Charting the Heavens and the Seas in NR 1998 vol 52 pp 369-371</p>
      <p>A E Shapiro, 'Huygens' Traite de la Lumiere and Newton's Opticks: Pursuing and Eschewing Hypotheses' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 223-247</p>
      <p>A R Hall, 'Newtonianism After 300 Years' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 5-9</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'Beyond the Fringe: Diffraction as Seen by Grimaldi, Fabri, Hooke and Newton' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 13-23</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, review of The Preliminary Manuscripts for Isaac Newton's 1687 Principia 1684-1685. Facsimiles of the Original Autographs, Now in Cambridge University Library in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 307-309</p>
      <p>Anita McConnell, 'L F Marsigli's Visit to London in 1721, and his Report on the Royal Society' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 179-204</p>
      <p>D G King-Hele, 'Introductory Remarks' in NR 1988 vol 42 p 3, plate</p>
      <p>D L Simms and P L Hinkley, 'Brighter Than How Many Suns? Sir Isaac Newton's Burning Mirror' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 31-51</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'The Evolution of the Principia from 1665 to 1686' in NR 1988 vol 42 p 11</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'The Latest on Newton…', essay review in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 111-117</p>
      <p>D T Whiteside, 'The Prehistory of the Principia from 1664 to 1686' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 11-61</p>
      <p>D W Hughes, 'The Principia and Comets' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 53-74</p>
      <p>David J Thomas, 'Joseph Raphson, FRS' in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 151-167</p>
      <p>E A Fellmann, 'The Principia and Continental Mathematicians' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 13-34</p>
      <p>Frank Smithies, review of Stuart Hollingdale, Makers of Mathematics in NR 1990 vol 44 pp 309-311</p>
      <p>G J Whitrow, 'Newton's Role in the History of Mathematics' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 71-92</p>
      <p>H A M Snelders, 'Christiaan Huygens and Newton's Theory of Gravitation' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 209-222</p>
      <p>I Bernard Cohen, 'Newton's Description of the Reflecting Telescope' in NR 1993 vol 47 pp 1-9</p>
      <p>J M T Thompson, 'The Principia and Contemporary Mechanics: Chaotic Dynamics and the New Unpredictability' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 97-122</p>
      <p>M C W Hunter, 'The Crown, the Public and the New Science, 1689-1702' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 99-116</p>
      <p>Mary Fellgett, 'Some Influences on the Young Isaac Newton' in NR 1988 vol 42 p 243</p>
      <p>P Casini, 'Newton's Principia and the Philosophers of the Enlightenment' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 35-52</p>
      <p>P M Harman, 'Newton to Maxwell: the Principia and British Physics' in NR 1988 vol 42 pp 75-96</p>
      <p>Simon Schaffer, 'The Glorious Revolution and Medicine in Britain and the Netherlands' in NR 1989 vol 43 pp 167-190</p>
      <p>Sir Alan Cook, 'Edmond Halley and Newton's Principia' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 129-138</p>
      <p>Stuart Hollingdale, '"Voyaging Through Strange Seas of Thought, Alone"', review of A Rupert Hall, Isaac Newton: Adventurer in Thought in NR 1994 vol 48 pp 154-156, plate</p>
      <p>V S Kirsanov, 'The Earliest Copy in Russia of Newton's Principia: Is it David Gregory's Annotated Copy?' in NR 1992 vol 46 pp 203-218</p>
      <p>A A Mills and P J Turvey, 'Newton's Telescope: An Examination of the Reflecting Telescope Attributed to Sir Isaac Newton in the Possession of the Royal Society' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 133-155</p>
      <p>A A Mills and R Hall, 'The Production of a Plane Surface. As Illustrated by Specula From Some Early Newtonian Telescopes' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>A A Mills, 'Newton's Prisms and His Experiments on the Spectrum' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 13-36, plate</p>
      <p>A A Mills, 'Newton's Water Clocks and the Fluid Mechanics of Clepsydrae' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 35-61</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'Further Newton Correspondence' in NR 1982-83 vol 37 pp 7-34</p>
      <p>A Rupert Hall, 'Newton and His Editors. The Wilkins Lecture, 1973' in NR 1974-5 vol 29 pp 29-52</p>
      <p>Charles H Cotter, 'The Mariner's Sextant and the Royal Society' in NR 1978-9 vol 33 pp 23-36</p>
      <p>G L'E Turner, 'James Short, FRS, and his Contribution to the Construction of Reflecting Telescopes' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 91-108</p>
      <p>J A Chaldecott, 'Cromwell Mortimer, FRS (c. 1698-1752) and the Invention of the Metalline Thermometer for Measuring High Temperatures' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 113-135</p>
      <p>J A Lohne, 'Experimentum Crucis' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 169-199</p>
      <p>Joan L Hawes, 'Newton's Revival of the Aether Hypothesis and the Explanation of Gravitational Attraction' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 200-212</p>
      <p>K A Baird, 'Some Influences Upon the Young Isaac Newton' in NR 1986-87 vol 41 pp 169-179</p>
      <p>L W Johnson and M L Wolbarsht, 'Mercury Poisoning: A Probable Cause of Isaac Newton's Physical and Mental Ills' in NR 1979-80 vol 34 pp 1-9</p>
      <p>N Feather, 'Rutherford - Faraday - Newton' in NR 1972-3 vol 27 pp 45-55</p>
      <p>P D Lawrence and A G Molland, 'David Gregory's Inaugural Lecture at Oxford' in NR 1970 vol 25 pp 143-178</p>
      <p>P E Spargo and C A Pounds, 'Newton's "Derangement of the Intellect": New Light on an Old Problem' in NR 1979-80 vol 34 pp 11-32</p>
      <p>P M Rattansi, 'The Intellectual Origins of the Royal Society' in NR 1968 vol 23 pp 129-143</p>
      <p>R W Ditchburn, 'Newton's Illness of 1692-3' in NR 1980 vol 35 pp 1-16</p>
      <p>Roy L Bishop, 'Rainbow Over Woolsthorpe Manor' in NR 1981-82 vol 36 pp 3-11</p>
      <p>'Image of Newton re0opens historic divide; article in 'Nature' 18/9/1997, p221 [re Sir Edward Paolozzo statue in courtyard of British Library</p>
      <p>P Fontes da Costa, 'The Culture of Curiosity at The Royal Society in the first half of the eighteenth century', NR 2002 vo l56 pp 147-166</p>
      <p>M Marotta 'Sir Isaac Newton; Warden and Master of the Mint' in 'The Numismatist' Vol 114, Number 11, November 2001</p>
      <p>M V Wilkes, 'Charles Babbage and his world' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 353-365</p>
      <p>W R Shea, 'The shifting image of Newton. Newton: the making of a genius, by P Fara' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 391-392</p>
      <p>A Cook, '1703 and other anniversaries' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 1-2</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Le Sage's Essai de chymie mechanique' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 35-45</p>
      <p>B Heap, 'From the dust of the Earth? Things come to life: spontaneous generation revisited by Henry Harris' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 107-108</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'The end of the affair. The correspondence of John Flamsteed, the first Astronomer Royal, vol 3 (1703-1719) by E G Forbes, L Murdin and F Willmoth' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 113-116</p>
      <p>A Cook, 'Two Anniversaries' in NR 2003 vol 57 p 133</p>
      <p>D E Cartwright, 'The Tonkin tides revisited' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 135-142</p>
      <p>J P Zinsser, 'The ultimate commentary: a consideration of I Bernhard Cohen's Guide to Newton's Principia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 231-238</p>
      <p>J Henry, 'Newton for philosophers. The Cambridge Companion to Newton, edited by I Bernard Cohen and G E Smith' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 246-247</p>
      <p>M Hesse, 'An eighteenth-century polymath. William Stukeley: science, religion and archaeology in eighteenth century England, by D B Haycock' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 248-249</p>
      <p>J H Appleby, 'The founding of St Petersburg in the context of the Royal Society's relationship with Russia' in NR 2003 vol 57 pp 273-284</p>
      <p>R Iliffe and J Young, 'Report. Newton on the net: first and prospective fruits of a Royal Society grant' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 83-88</p>
      <p>M Hunter, 'Report. Robert Hooke revivified' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 89-91</p>
      <p>J Gray, 'Harriot Restored. &lt;i&gt;The greate invention of algebra: Thomas Harriot's treatise on equations&lt;/i&gt;, by Jacqueline A Stedall' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 101-102</p>
      <p>L Jardine, 'The 2003 Wilkins Lecture: Dr Wilkins's boy wonders' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 107-129</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Theatrical Science. C Djerassi and D Pinner, Newton's darkness: two dramatic views' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 237-238</p>
      <p>P Fara, 'Lucasian Professors. From Newton to Hawking: a history of Cambridge University's Lucasian professors of mathematics, ed K C Knox and R Noakes' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 312-313</p>
      <p>M Bailey Ogilvie, 'In her place. Pandora's breeches: women, science and power in the enlightenment, by P Fara' in NR 2004 vol 58 pp 314-315</p>
      <p>J S Rowlinson, 'Mixed mathematics. 'Masters of theory: Cambridge and the rise of mathematical physics' by A Warwick' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 94-96</p>
      <p>R Higgett, 'President, patron, friend and lover: Charles Montagu's significance to the history of science' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 155-170</p>
      <p>A Belenkiy &amp; E V Echague, 'History of one defeat: reform of the Julian calendar as envisaged by Isaac Newton' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 223-254</p>
      <p>R MacFarlane, 'Royal Society Miscellaneous Manuscripts' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 309-312</p>
      <p>J T Young, 'Newton on the Net: an update' in NR 2005 vol 59 pp 313-316</p>
      <p>J T Young, 'Isaac Newton's alchemical notes in the Royal Society' in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 25-35</p>
      <p>P Quarrie 'The Scientific library of the earls of Macclesfield' in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 5-25</p>
      <p>D King-Hele, 'The many images of Isaac Newton. 'The iconography of Sir Isaac Newton, to 1800' by M Keynes' in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 215 - 216</p>
      <p>M J Osler, 'A hero for their times: early biographies of Newton' in NR 2006 vol 60 pp 291-305</p>
      <p>M Keynes 'Balancing Newton's mind: his singular behaviour and his madness on 1692-3' in NR 2008 vol 62 pp 289-300</p>
      <p>Imagen Clarke 'How to manage a revolution: Isaac Newton in the early twentieth century.' N&amp;R 2014 vol 68 pp 323-327</p>
      <p>M Joalland and S Mandelbrote 'Isaac Newton l earns Hebrew: Samuel Johnson's 'Nova cubi Hebraei tabella'' in N&amp;R Vol 70 Issue 1 March 2016 pp9-22</p>
      <p/>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>natural philosopher and mathematician</term>
   </note>
</person>