<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8441">
   <persName>
      <forename>Stephen</forename>
      <surname>Hales</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1677 - 1761</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Bekesbourne, Kent, England (07 or 17 September 1677)</p>
      <p>Death: Teddington, Middlesex (04 January 1761)</p>
      <p>Burial: Beneath the tower, Teddington Church</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Clergyman, Church of England</p>
      <p>Research Field: Physiology, public health</p>
      <p>Education: Revd Richard Johnson's school, Orpington, Kent; Corpus Christi College, Cambridge. MA (1703); BD (1711). Oxford. DD (by diploma 1733)</p>
      <p>Career: Fellow of Corpus Christi (1703-1719); ordained priest (1709); Perpetual curate, Teddington, Middlesex (1709-1761); had a laboratory, where he performed experiments relating to physiology, physics, chemistry, botany; published "Vegetable statics" (1727) and "Statical essays" (1733); was an active parish priest and helped his parishioners to a decent water supply; invented artificial ventilators and other things; one of the FRS who petitioned Parliament for Johanna Stephens to be paid for her method for dissolving stones in the bladder (1739); restored the tower of Teddington Church; Rector of Porlock, Somerset (1717-1723); Vicar of Farringdon, Hampshire (1722); Clerk of the Closet to the Princess Dowager Augusta (1751); Chaplain to Prince George, afterwards George III; one of the Trustees for the Colony of Georgia</p>
      <p>Memberships: French Academy; FRSA (Founder)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 13/03/1718</p>
      <p>Proposers: William Stukeley; (a candidate)</p>
      <p>Medals/Prizes: Copley Medal 1739</p>
      <p>Council: 1727</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Venn; Foster</p>
      <p>Authority: Date of birth from DSB</p>
      <p>References: Marta Cavazza, 'The Institute of Science of Bologna and the Royal Society in the eighteenth century' in NR 2002 vol 56 pp 3-25, plate</p>
      <p>John H Appleby, 'Robert Dingley, FRS (1710-1781), Merchant, Architect and Pioneering Philanthropist' in NR 1991 vol 45 pp 139-154</p>
      <p>Ernest Heberden, 'Correspondence of William Heberden, FRS With the Reverend Stephen Hales and Sir Charles Blagden' in NR 1984-85 vol 39 pp 179-189</p>
      <p>Jeffrey M N Boss, 'A Collection of Some Observations on Bills of Mortality &amp; Parish Registers: An Unpublished Manuscript by Stephen Hales, FRS (1677-1761)' in NR 1977-8 vol 32 pp 131-147</p>
      <p>J A Chaldecott, 'Cromwell Mortimer, FRS (c. 1698-1752) and the Invention of the Metalline Thermometer for Measuring High Temperatures' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 113-135</p>
      <p>H G Lyons, 'Two Hundred Years Ago: 1739' in NR 1939 vol 2 pp 34-42</p>
      <p>'Gentleman's Magazine' 1761, p32, 44; 1764, p273-278 (Account of Hales's life by Peter Collinson FRS)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>physiologist and inventor</term>
   </note>
</person>