<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8401">
   <persName>
      <forename>Alexander</forename>
      <surname>Cuming</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>c 1690 - 1775</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Edinburgh (18 December 1691)</p>
      <p>Death: Charterhouse hospital, London (20 August 1775)</p>
      <p>Burial: The church of East Barnet, Hertfordshire</p>
      
      <p>Education: Middle Temple (admitted 1716)</p>
      <p>Career: Captain in the Earl of Mar's Regiment of Foot (1703-1713); called to the Scottish Bar (1714); in the secret service of the Crown (1718-1721); rumoured to have been a Captain in the Russian Army; went to America to visit the Cherokee Mountains because of a dream of his wife's (1729); made a Chief of the Cherokee Nation (1730); returned to England with five Cherokee chiefs, whom he presented to George II (1730); signed a peace treaty with the Cherokees on behalf of the British nation; Captain of an Independent Company in Jamaica (1734); accused of defrauding settlers while in South Carolina, he lost all his money and was imprisoned for debt in the Fleet Prison (1737-1765); his plans for settling 300,000 Jewish families in the Cherokee Mountains, for paying off the National Debt and for relieving the American colonies of taxation came to nothing; a Poor Brother of the Charterhouse (1766-death)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 30/06/1720</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; MT; Dalton</p>
      <p>Notes: Birth date given as 18 December 1691 in his manuscript autobiography at British Library, BL Add. MS 39855</p>
      <p>Proposed by John Theophilus Desaguliers. Ejected for non-payment of arrears (Journal Book 9 Jun 1757). Alternative spelling of name from DNB. Buried 28 Aug 1775 - his death date has been extrapolated from that.</p>
   </note>
</person>