<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8405">
   <persName>
      <forename>George</forename>
      <surname>Graham</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1673 - 1751</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Horsgill, in the parish of Kirklinton, Cumberland, England (07 July 1673)</p>
      <p>Death: His house in Fleet Street, London (16 or 20 November 1751)</p>
      <p>Burial: The same grave as Tompion, Westminster Abbey, London</p>
      
      <p>Profession: Scientific instrument maker</p>
      <p>Watchmaker</p>
      <p>Education: Apprenticed to Henry Aske, a watchmaker in London</p>
      <p>Career: Assistant, partner and then successor to Thomas Tompion; made instruments for the astronomers royal Edmund Halley (FRS 1678) and James Bradley (FRS 1718), for Samuel Molyneux's (FRS 1712) private observatory at Kew, and the apparatus used by the French Academy for measuring the meridian, as well as an orrery, named after Charles Boyle, 4th Earl of Orrery (FRS 1706); a Quaker, he disliked banks and kept his money in a strong box, lending large sums to his friends at no interest; one of those whom he thus encouraged was the instrument maker, James Harrison</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 9/03/1721</p>
      <p>Council: 1722, 1724, 1726, 1728, 1730</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DNB; DSB; Clifton</p>
      <p>References: H G Lyons, 'Two Hundred Years Ago: 1739' in NR 1939 vol 2 pp 34-42</p>
      <p>G L'E Turner, 'James Short, FRS, and his Contribution to the Construction of Reflecting Telescopes' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 91-108</p>
      <p>J A Chaldecott, 'Cromwell Mortimer, FRS (c. 1698-1752) and the Invention of the Metalline Thermometer for Measuring High Temperatures' in NR 1969 vol 24 pp 113-135</p>
      <p>Richard Sorrenson, 'Towards a History of the Royal Society in the Eighteenth Century' in NR 1996 vol 50 pp 29-46</p>
      <p>Geoffrey Cantor, 'Quakers in the Royal Society, 1660-1750' in NR 1997 vol 51 pp 175-193</p>
      <p>Desmond King-Hele, 'Not So Dumb, After All?', review of R Sorrenson, ed., 'Did the Royal Society Matter in the Eighteenth Century?', British Journal for the History of Science, 32 (June 1999), 130-221, in NR 2000 vol 54 pp 120-122</p>
      <p>'Gentleman's Magazine' 1751, p523</p>
      <p>Notes: Birth date supplied by the Clockmakers' Company. Proposed by Martin Folkes. DSB gives death date as 16 November 1751.</p>
   </note>
</person>