<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA8408">
   <persName>
      <forename>Joseph</forename>
      <surname>Williamson</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1633 - 1701</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Bridekirk, near Cockermouth, Cumberland, England, Europe (25 July 1633 )</p>
      <p>Baptism: Parish church of Bridekirk, Cumberland, England, Europe (4 August 1633)</p>
      <p>Death: Cobham Hall, Kent, England, Europe (3 October 1701)</p>
      <p>Burial: Duke of Richmond's vault in King Henry VII's chapel, Westminster Abbey, London, England, Europe (14 October 1701)</p>
      
      <p>Occupation: Government official, diplomat, politician</p>
      <p>Research field: Antiquities</p>
      <p>Education: St Bees free grammar school, Cumberland; Westminster School (1648); Queen's College, Oxford; BA (1654), MA (1657); tutored in natural philosophy and chemistry by Peter Stael at Oxford; Incorporated at Cambridge (1659); Middle Temple, honorary call to bar (1664); Lincoln's Inn, honorary member (1672); DCL (1674)</p>
      <p>Career: Clerk to Richard Tolson, MP for Cockermouth; travelled in France and the Low Countries as tutor to young gentlemen (1655-1658); Fellow of Queen's College, Oxford (1658-1679); called to the Bar (1664); Founded the 'London Gazette' (1665); Under-secretary to the Secretary of State for the South, Sir Edward Nicholas then Sir Henry Bennett 'Lord Arlington' (1660-1674) imposing strict order on the administrative running of the office and exerting influence through this position; known to have gathered domestic and international intelligence especially on political plots, using a network of spies and infomers and has been described as de facto head of the restoration government's intelligence system (see DNB); Keeper of the King's Library at Whitehall and of the state paper office (1661); Assistant, Royal Adventurers into Africa (1664-1668), Royal African Company (1673, 1675-1677); Commissioner for Lotteries (1665); Commissioner for Assessment for Cumberland and Thetford (1673-1680), for Middlesex (1673-1679), for Westminster (1673-1674, 1679-1680), for Norfolk (1677-1680), and for Kent and Westminster (1689); Commissioner for seizing prohibited goods (1663); Contractor for the Royal Oak Lottery (1664); Editor of the Oxford Gazette, a newsletter which he used to disseminate offical news and government rhetoric (1665); MP for Thetford, Norfolk (1669, 1679, 1681, 1685), for Rochester (1690, 1701), for County Clare (1692), and for Limerick (1695); Clerk of the Council (1672-1674); played a prominant role in The Royal Declaration of Indulgence (1672) which briefly allowed greater religious freedoms in England before being repealed; Joint Plenipotentiary at the Congress at Cologne (1673-1674); Secretary of State (North) (1674-1679); briefly imprisoned in the Tower during the 'Popish plot' for having supposedly excused Catholics from taking oaths of allegiance whilst Secretary of State (1678); released from the Tower by order of Charles II but was soon after replaced as Secretary of State; Lord of the Admiralty (1674-1679); Privy Councillor (1674-1679, 1696-death); Assistant, Royal Fisheries (1677); Irish Privy Council (1680-1685, 1692-1696); Recorder of Thetford (1682); Joint Plenipotentiary at the peace conference in Rijswijk (Ryswick, 1697); Ambassador at the Hague (1697-1699); held antiquarian interests including in the ages of bibilical figures; a lover of music; benefactor of Queen's College, Oxford to which he bequeathed his library as well as funding buildings, including one designed by Christopher Wren FRS; bequeathed money to build a free school for boys at Rochester which is still called 'Sir Joseph Williamson's Mathematical School' .</p>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1672</p>
      <p>Memberships: Clothworkers' Company (Master 1675-1677)</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Original Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 20/05/1663</p>
      <p>Proposers: Thomas Povey (29 January 1662)</p>
      <p>Council: 1666</p>
      <p>Secretary 1676; PRS 1677-1680; VP: 1686-?</p>
      <p>Committee appointments include: Correspondence Committee (1664)</p>
      <p>Committee for the Improving the English language (1664)</p>
      <p>Other RSActivity: Placed diplomatic channels at the Society's disposal for the transmission of foreign letters.</p>
      <p>Involved in attempts to procure His Majesty's grant for Chelsea College and pledged £50; this project never came to fruition.</p>
      <p>Involved in the possible press to print books after a certain number of subscribers to the Society (1676).</p>
      <p>The Society's shares in the East India Company were transferred to Williamson, along with Herbert, Pitfield, and Creed.</p>
      <p>Left a legacy of £200 to the Royal Society.</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; ODNB; Venn; Foster; Davies; Henning</p>
      <p>References: Michael Hunter, 'The Social Bias and Changing Fortunes of an Early Scientific Institution: An Analysis of the Membership of the Royal Society, 1660-1685', NR 1976-7 vol 31 pp 9-114</p>
      <p>A. Marshall, 'Sir Joseph Williamson and the conduct of administration in Restoration England', Historical Research, 1996 vol 69 pp 18-41</p>
      <p>Mark Govier, 'The Royal Society, Slavery and the Island of Jamaica: 1660-1700', NR 1999 vol 53 pp 203-217</p>
      <p>Notes: The election date is Williamson's re-election date into the Society after the grant of the second charter in April 1663. All Fellows admitted in a two-month window after this charter, until 22 June 1663, are considered Original Fellows. He was previously admitted into the Society on 5 February 1662.</p>
      <p>Associated material: Correspondence of Joseph Williamson from various repositories is listed in the Early Modern Letters Online catalogue http://emlo.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/forms/advanced?people=williamson%2C+joseph</p>
      <p>'Sir Joseph Williamson 1633-1701: the loyal Queensman and great benefactor' online version of a 2011 exhbition by the Queen's College, Oxford (https://www.queens.ox.ac.uk/joseph-williamson, accessed 19 May 2021)</p>
   </note>
   <note type="keywords">
      <term>government official</term>
   </note>
</person>