<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA912">
   <persName>
      <forename>Richard Vynne</forename>
      <surname>Southwell</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1888 - 1970</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: 02 July 1888</p>
      <p>Death: 09 December 1970</p>
      
      <p>Education;</p>
      <p>King Edward VII School Norwich 1898-1907; Trinity College Cambridge 1907-1910, B.Sc Class I; Fellow of Trinity College Cambidge 1912;</p>
      <p>Career: Superintendent of the Aerodynamics Department of the National Physical Laboratory 1920-1925</p>
      <p>Fellow and Faculty Lecturer in Mathematics at Trinity College Cambridge 1925</p>
      <p>Professor of Engineering Science, Oxford 1929</p>
      <p>Rector of Imperial College London 1942-1948</p>
      <p>President of International Union for Theoretical and Applied Mechanics 1946-1948; President of International Congressof Applied Mechanics 1948-1952, and Treasurer 1952-1956</p>
      <p>General Secretary of the British Association1948-1956</p>
      <p>Hon. Ll.D by University of St Andrews 1939, Glasgow 1957; Hon. D.Sc. by Universities of Bristol, Brussels in 1949, and Queen's University Belfast in 1952; Hon. D.Eng. by University of Sheffield 1958.</p>
      <p>Hon. Fellow of Brasenose College Oxford in 1943, and Imperial College London and Trinity College Cambridge in 1950.</p>
      <p>Medals;</p>
      <p>Telford Premium 1932 by Institution of Civil Engineers</p>
      <p>James Alfred Ewing Medal 1946 by Institution of Civil Engineeers</p>
      <p>Clayton Prize 1947 by Institution of Mechanical Engineers</p>
      <p>Worcester Reed Warner Medal 1941 by , and Timoshenko Medal in 1959, by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers</p>
      <p>Lectures: James Forest Lecture 1930 and 1948, Institution of Civil Engineeers</p>
      <p>Wright Brothers Lecture, 1941, Institution of Aeronautical Sciences</p>
      <p>Hinchley Lecture, 1950, University of Toronto</p>
      <p>Trueman Wood Lecture, 1953, RoyalSociety of Arts</p>
      <p>Thomas Hawksley Lecture, 1954, Institution of Mechanical Engineers</p>
      <p>W J Rankin Memorial Lecture, 1955, University of Glasgow</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Honours: Kt 1948</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 7/05/1925</p>
      <p>Offices: Council, 1930-1831</p>
      <p>Lectures: Bakerian 1943</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll</p>
      <p>Obituaries: Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society 1972 vol 18 pp 549-565, plate, by D G Christopherson</p>
   </note>
</person>