<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/identified-entities.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<person xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="NA981">
   <persName>
      <forename>Robert</forename>
      <surname>Erskine</surname>
   </persName>
   <note type="dates">
      <date>1735 - 1780</date>
   </note>
   <sex value="M"/>
   <note type="biography">
      <p>Birth: Dunfermline, Fife, Scotland (07 September 1735)</p>
      <p>Death: 02 October 1780.</p>
      <p>Buried at Ringwood Manor in Ringwood State Park in New Jersey.</p>
      
      <p>Education: Career: Ringwood Company ironworks was established in 1742 by five members of Newark's Ogden family. Located in Passaic County, the ironworks were operated until 1764 by the Ringwood Company, and later by Peter Hasenclever (1716-1793) as an agent for the company until he was replaced first by John Jacob Faesch (1729-1799) in 1769, and then by Robert Erskine (1735-1780) who came to America in 1771 to manage the iron ore mines at Ringwood and Charlottesburgh in Upper Passaic Co., New Jersey. Erskine immediately set about trying to make the operation profitable. His efforts were cut short by the Revolutionary War. Erskine was sympathetic to the American cause, but worried that he might lose his workers to the army, he organized them into a militia and was appointed a militia captain in August of 1775.</p>
      <p/>
      <p>Because of its remoteness from the enemy, Ringwood was the only permanent barracks for revolutionary troops in New Jersey, and its forges supplied much needed ammunition and weapons. Once the war broke out in earnest there was concern among the rebels that the British warships would use the Hudson river to attack northern forts and separate New England from the rest of the colonies. Erskine, ever the engineer, designed a tetrahedron-shaped marine Chevaux-de-Frise; esentially a barrier that would keep warships from moving upriver.</p>
      <p>General Washington commissioned him as geographer and surveyor-general of the United Colonies on 27 July 1777. Following his appointment, Erskine drew upwards of 275 maps covering the northern sector of the war. His maps of the region, showing roads, buildings, and other details, were of much use to Gen. Washington and remain historically valuable.</p>
      
      <p>Membership: Fellow</p>
      <p>Election Date: 31/01/1771</p>
   </note>
   <note type="sources">
      <p>Sources: Bulloch's Roll; DAB</p>
      <p>References: Albert H Heusser edited with introductin by Hubert G Schmidt ' George Washington's Mapmaker, a Biography of Robert Erskine' Rutgers University Press, New Brunswick, New Herseym USA 1966</p>
   </note>
</person>