<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1095">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Sir Thomas Frankland, Thirkleby, [Yorkshire], to Sir James Edward Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63035/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/15/59, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Frankland, Sir Thomas">Sir Thomas Frankland</persName>
                    <placeName>Thirkleby, Yorkshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1820-08-30">30 Aug 1820</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Pleased Smith had such an agreeable tour. His wife died 19 May; "a bitter affliction" to be separated from his companion of 45 years but considering the complaint in her breast, paralysis of left side, and digestion and appetite gone it was a "desireable blessing".</p><p>Attended Horticultural Society anniversary meeting and invited by Sir Joseph Banks to visit Spring Grove [Isleworth, Middlesex]. Bank's successor at Royal Society: not canvassed by any candidate; initially objected to Prince Leopold as he lived too far away to be easily consulted and though convinced by his promises to keep a librarian at Marlborough House, to have dinners and evening meetings, and to dedicate £4000 a year to the Society it is said that enmity from "a certain quarter" has induced Leopold to give up his campaign. In London received ten air plants from his nephew, Commodore Bowles, but neglected them and only three are alive, two are 'Epidendrum cochleatum' and other a 'Tillandsia'; saw many at Leddiges but they have no great beauty. Raised several plants from Buenos Aires, [Argentina], but [James] Lee says they are not new having been collected by [Aimé Jacques Alexandre] Bonpland [(1773-1858)] travelling with [Alexander von] Humboldt.</p><p>A "profusion of peaches" and his favourite green fleshed Egyptian melon, which he exhibited at Horticultural Society and were so admired that he is saving seed for members. Immediately looked at 'Hypnum resognitum' in [James] Sowerby, the name a good one from singular circumstance of Smith's "refinding it". Dwarf apple trees 4 feet high with fruit brances supported by stakes, chiefly Hemick codlings and Hawthorn clean.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>