<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1092">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Sir Thomas Frankland, Thirkleby, [Yorkshire], to Sir James Edward Smith, Norwich, [Norfolk]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63032/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/15/56, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Frankland, Sir Thomas">Sir Thomas Frankland</persName>
                    <placeName>Thirkleby, Yorkshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1818-03-11">11 Mar 1818</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Norwich, Norfolk</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Discussion of melons: should not have dismissed Great Mogul before Smith tried it, and read of a fine variety brought from Persia by Sir Gore Ouseley [1st baronet (1770-1844)] but till he tastes it will stick with the Green Egyptian. Will determine whether the plant he sent Smith is 'Sonchus arvensis var' with seeds he saved. Low barometer readings during recent storm: 28.17 on Wedneday at Thirkleby and 27.95 at Gordon Castle, [Moray], their wind "trifling compared to its fury in the South" and no damage to his house built on hill but skylight and tiles on his son's house in Curzon Street, [London], were damaged and trees uprooted in Chesterfield Gardens.</p><p>Trying to find plants unattractive to rabbits and hares after having to cradle 'Pyrus japonica' sent by [James] Lee: has not ascertained whether it is true that they only interfere with transplants and not those sown directly; 'Rhododendron ponticum' grown in the wood, box and privet safe but American bird cherry, 'Hippophae', 'Aucuba japonica' and juniper destroyed. Convinced a neighbouring nurseryman to write his labels in the more durable Indian ink. Surprised to receive letter of thanks from Horticultural Society for the Newton pippin apples he sent to [James] Dickson. Intends to search for ferns and mosses by side of Hambleton, [Yorkshire], believes no botanist has been there before.</p><p>Gathering evidence on power of crossbills to kill young rooks; Norfolk Eton boys used to speak of them being shot with bolts. Mentions his son's growing interest in natural history, especially geology, and encloses specimen as example [undisclosed]. His health good but Lady Frankland gradually failing from complaint of several years standing from which none have ever recovered, she is frequently attended by Sir Everard Home and Atkinson of York.</p><p>Small sketch in ink of plant detail "'Aspidium thelypteris (from Mr Teesdale) confirms you descrip[tio]ns in "English Botany" by the length of lower leaves, very ill figured by [James] Sowerby".</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>