<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN867">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Sir James Edward Smith, Norwich, [Norfolk], to Sir Thomas Gery Cullum</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62825/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/13/61, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Norwich, Norfolk</placeName>
                    <date when="1818-10-31">31 Oct 1818</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Cullum, Sir Thomas Gery">Sir Thomas Gery Cullum</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Has been busy with Sessions week, a visit from his brother-in-law, James Reeve, and wife, and a feverish cold. On his way to Liverpool stayed at Dunston Hall, Derbyshire, Reeve's new home. Gave twelve lectures in Liverpool supported with abundant specimens from the "fine" botanic garden, they were enthusiastically received with about three hundred in attendance, mainly women, including Lady Crewe. Pleased to see [William] Roscoe so well respected. Some Cambridge men in the audience were "abundantly flattering" and indignant "at the behaviour of the Johnians" to him [College of St John had been obstructive in Smith's campaign for Cambridge botany professorship].</p><p>Believes Dean [of Norwich, Joseph Turner (1747-1828)] correct to say that the Cambridge establishment only objects to Smith on grounds that they do not want to see the £200 a year for the botany professorship go to one who is not a member of the university. Bishop of Winchester [Brownlow North] recently blind but enthusiasm for botany still active and he was pleased with Smith's pamphlet ["Considerations respecting Cambridge..."]. Collected rare ferns from high rocks of Cromford Moor, near Matlock, [Derbyshire], will raise them from seed by following instructions of the Liverpool gardener who has raised 'Acrostichum calomelanos' from a fifty year old specimen of Forster's. Has deferred a visit to Holkham, [Norfolk, home of Thomas William Coke] but glad Cullum enjoyed his time there.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>