<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1089">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Sir Thomas Frankland, Thirkleby, York, to Sir James Edward Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63029/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/15/53, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Frankland, Sir Thomas">Sir Thomas Frankland</persName>
                    <placeName>Thirkleby, Yorkshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1816-07-31">31 Jul 1816</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Received Smith's letter from Woburn [Abbey, Bedfordshire]. His health good but Lady Frankland weakened by summer weather, gave up London trip to care for her. His son in Geneva avoiding the 400 English there, but returning to act as his uncle's executor and so Lady Frankland can meet her new daughter-in-law for first time. Grew successful crop of Great Mogul melons from the seeds Smith sent from Lord [Thomas, 1st Viscount] Anson's [(1769-1818)] and will compare with the green Egyptian and scarlet-fleshed melons, though thinks melons too troublesome to be worth raising.</p><p>Strawberry propagation: laid straw in two beds of alpine and pine strawberries, in the latter half of ripe fruit was daily found scooped out, the gardeners think it was slugs but he suspects beetles concealed in the straw during the day, encloses specimen. Strawberry plants given him by [Edward Lascelles, 1st Earl of] Harewood's [(1740-1820)] gardener in January 1815 not pines; they have a uniform shape, a higher colour, blood red inside, and firmer than pines, detailed ink sketch of fruit. Unable to succeed with hautboys even when raising from seed of very fine fruit of Mr [Christopher] Dundas' in Berkshire.</p><p>Two beetles in small blue envelope labelled "Beetles 'Carabus striatus' Kirby mss. near 'vulgaris'".</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>