<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN643">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Samuel Goodenough, Carlisle, [Cumberland], to James Edward Smith, Surry Street, Norwich, Norfolk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62612/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/11/68, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Goodenough, Samuel">Samuel Goodenough</persName>
                    <placeName>Carlisle, Cumberland</placeName>
                    <date when="1808-10-01">1 Oct 1808</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Norwich, Norfolk</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Forwarded Smith's letter to [George] Don, did not know that 'Limosella' cannot be found in Scotland but remembers it growing on Hounslow Heath and cultivating it in his Ealing garden. There are no naturalists in the Carlisle area or anyone to collect plants. Lists plants he has observed in the area: the variety of 'Plantago maritima' called 'Loeflingii' by [William] Hudson, in elevated moist positions, smaller and with untoothed leaves, does Smith know of it growing in such conditions away from the sea; 'Salix pentandria' in all the moist hedges; 'Campanula latifolia' in shady lanes by Rose Castle; 'Fumaria capreolata' in cornfields amongst turnips, contrary to Smith's statement that it is a southern plant; 'Senecio sarracenicus', possibly escaped from a garden; 'Sanguisorba officinalis', a favourite Oxfordshire plant; 'Serapias latifolia'; 'Salix repens'; a tree called bird-cherry or heckberry, possibly 'Prunus padus'; 'Rubus corylifolius' is common. The hills and wastes are in a wild state and covered with 'Erica vulgaris', 'Juncus squarrosus', 'Tormentilla reptans', 'Lichen rangiferinus' and similar.</p><p>Received letter from Hugh Davies complaining that [Edward] Donovan [(1768-1837), zoologist] has attacked him and [Thomas] Pennant over the Beaumaris shark and trifurcated hake in Pennant's "British Zoology", claiming that Pennant did not refer to Davies' figure but instead fabricated his own, and that Pennant makes Davies guilty of gross misrepresentation over the trifurcated hake; Donovan concludes that these fabricated figures left Goodenough wrongly informed in his "Linnean Transactions" paper on the Porbeagle shark, and Donovan is convinced that the Beaumaris and Porbeagle sharks are the same. Goodenough convinced that both his and Pennant's figures are exact and the sharks are different. Exasperated by those, like [Richard] Salisbury, "thinking to raise themselves at other people's expense" and "carping jealousies" engendered by learned societies.</p><p>Rose Castle prettily situated but six miles from the nearest badly supplied market town and the house thermometer is already halfway between temperate and freezing.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>