<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1097">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Sir Thomas Frankland, Thirkleby, [Yorkshire], to Sir James Edward Smith, Norwich, [Norfolk]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63036/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/15/60, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Frankland, Sir Thomas">Sir Thomas Frankland</persName>
                    <placeName>Thirkleby, Yorkshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1820-11-05">5 Nov 1820</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Norwich, Norfolk</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Received Smith's letter from Holkham, [Norfolk, home of Sir Thomas William Coke]. Supposes Smith occupied "by the business which has so long disgraced the house of Lords, but more so everyone of those who have brought such foul matters before them" [probably "trial" of Queen Caroline], his opinion same as Lord Harewood's speech in today's paper and regardless of whatever party is more in the wrong the business in hand is "insanity &amp; is more likely to shake the government than the attempts of the Radicals". Prince Leopold seems to have had "some tiff" with the King [George III (1738-1820)] lately.</p><p>His son and daughter-in-law have been placing single trees and shrubs on the lawn "so zealously that the Lady carries various articles, &amp; even digs". His son has renounced foxhunting. His own health generally good but debility and rheumatism leave him helpless at hedges and when shooting has to be pulled through.</p><p>His garden thriving: had asparagus on the 3rd and peas today, the former raised in a "pigeon holed frame" invented by McPhail which prevents manure vapours affecting the bed so the produce is sweeter. Disapproves of [Thomas] A[ndrew] Knight's "filthy practice of drenching [his] fig, &amp; his pines, with a mixture of piegons' dung &amp; water the colour of Porter" to guarantee multiple crops from his fig tree, received a letter reporting nine crops in fifteen months. Too few woodcocks this season to prove his theory that only males come over in first flight; encloses exterior quill feathers [not extant] of the male as example, females have a white line running most of the way from the quill to the extremity, small ink sketch illustrating this.</p><p>Copying and "tearing out likenesses in paper"; there is much chance in tracing them, encloses example of "old Mrs Warburton, well known in the society at York 30 or 40 years ago", requests its return. Just requested specimen of 'Menziesia caerulea' from Scotland and will attempt to procure 'Menziesia polifolia' through his sister, Lady Roche, in Dublin.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>