<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN925">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Edmund Davall, Orbe, Canton de Berne, [Switzerland], to James Edward Smith, 12 Great Marlborough Street, London</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62907/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/14/23, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Davall, Edmund">Edmund Davall</persName>
                    <placeName>Orbe, Switzerland</placeName>
                    <date when="1790-09-14">14 Sep 1790</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>His wife gave birth to a daughter. He suffered from diarrhea for last three weeks. Collected 'Schoenus ferrugineus' and 'Satyrium repens' for Smith. Will send Smith 'Bartsia alpina' every year. Frustrated that out of paternal concern Mr Mandrot refused to pay more than 10 guineas for [James] Sowerby's work on his plates. Work on his book very slow and does not feel capable of producing a second and in future will send his notes to Smith or publish them through Linnean Society; feels he would be more useful to Smith botanising in his garden and in the wild. [Werner de] Lachenal is not jealous of the book and encourages him as it will be useful for his own intended "Flora Helo. Linnaeus ordine". [Jacob] Wyttenbach and young [Albrecht von] Haller [(1758-1823)] have offended himself and Lachenal in pursuit of their work [new edition of elder Haller's "Icones plantarum Helvetiae"] and transcribes, in French, long extract from offensive letter sent by Wyttenbach who wishes to use Davall's plates in the new edition.</p><p>Observations on various Alpine plants: 'Arenaria striata', 'Arenaria liniflora', 'Hypericum babatum', particular observations on 'Hypericum richeri', 'Saxifraga ajugifolia', 'Arenaria grandiflora' and 'Arenaria triflora', 'Arenaria laricifolia' and 'Arenaria liniflora' of Bauhin, now thinks what he thought were two plants of 'Chenopodium polyspermum' are the same plant in different stages of growth. Discusses in detail 'Cerinthe' from one of his previous packets. No longer thinks Haller is correct to name 'Alium angulosum' the same as 'Alium senescens'; compares with plants of [Nikolaus von] Jacquin's "Flora Austriaca" t423 and Gmelin's ["Flora Sibirica"] t11 f3. Discussion of Haller's plants 30 and 31. Anecdote relating to sale of Haller's library: in the same year it was sold to the Emperor there was a fireworks display costing £1500, when a smaller sum would have kept the library. Developing an area in his aunt's garden for shelter and a different exposure for about 800 plants in pots. Convinced Haller's plant number 30, in his parcel of 27 February 1790, is 'Salsola prostrata' of Jacquin's "Flora Austriacta". Plant 59 'Euphorbia gerardiana'.</p><p>In postscript down left-hand margin of recto of first folio Davall has written that he has been very ill since writing this letter, and hopes Smith received a letter from Mrs [Henriette] Davall [letter is dated "by post of 14 Sept 1790" but was evidently written before].</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>