<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN966">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">James Edward Smith, London, to Edmund Davall, Orbe, Canton de Berne, [Switzerland]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62944/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/14/60, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                    <date when="1793-07-02">2 Jul 1793</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Davall, Edmund">Edmund Davall</persName>
                    <placeName>Orbe, Switzerland</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Responds to Davall's letters of 11 May 1793 and 4 June 1793 [the latter is not extant in this collection]: answers Davall's rich packet on another paper [not extant], but will say no.12 is 'Triticum tenellum' HL and no.26 is 'Myagrum hispanicum' HL [HL is probably Herbarium Linnaeus]; thanks for plants and Mrs Davall's puzzling netted purse, his sister will try to copy it and piece of work of different kind for Mrs Davall. Sending Mrs Davall two spar eggs for netting from Matlock, [Derbyshire]._x000D_</p><p>Does not comprehend Davall's illness; his own health well but overcome with heat of town. Has a project to live in Kensington. Apologises for not sending Davall for his herbarium everything he could from England. Mandrot is taking parcel of 50 Botany Bay specimens for Davall, and numbers 16 to 31 of "English Botany", and another parcel containing [James] Sowerby's "Florists Delight" 2 and 3 and 80 more Botany Bay specimens sent another way. Comments on how rare these specimens are, considering how close Sir Jospeh Banks kept his voyage specimens, and half what he sends Davall are new to Banks also. Smith receives them from White, surgeon of the colony, has not had time to settle the names yet. Has asked [John] Fairbairn for Davall's seeds. 'Mornia' in Davall's garden, is in none here. [Adam] Afzelius happy to correspond with Davall, the colony in Sierra Leone "thrives admirably". Sending [James] Dickson's "Hortus siccus Britannicus" nos.1, 2 and 3. First volume of his "Sketch of a Tour of the Continent" published. Congratulates Davall on his son having had the smallpox. Encloses packet and letter to be forwarded to Montpellier, and has asked Broussonet to send letters via Davall as no post goes to France now on account of war. Asks if Davall's aunt remember Miss Butterworth from her school in Marlborough Street, now married to his cousin Kindersley, just returned from fourteen years in India. Updates Davall's account for books._x000D_</p><p>Various notes in Davall's hand on verso of second folio: wrote 11 October by Mrs Simpson with seed of 'Lavatera puncata', 'Minuartia campestris', and 'Androsace lactea'; forwarded letter from Victor Broussonet 2 August; note that when mentioning Jacquin's repetition of caps of 'Alstroemeria pelegrina' to see Colls vol 4 p.220; to mention parcel by Dorthes, done in letter of 6 Dec 1793; when writing again 'Hypochaeris uniflora' preferable to 'Helactica', 'Ranunculus [belliflorus], the print of dissertation.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>