<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN667">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Samuel Goodenough to James Edward Smith, a Mr Broussonet, 57 Rue des Blanes Monteaux, Paris, [France]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62553/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/11/9, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Goodenough, Samuel">Samuel Goodenough</persName>
                    
                    <date when="1787-08-13">13 Aug 1787</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Paris, France</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Critices the Society for the Promotion of Natural History for "dron[ing] on in its usual course" and particularly for a shambolic lecture by Dr Pitcairn on a new arrangement of shells. [Emanuel Mendez] da Costa [(1717-1791), naturalist] was at the meeting and "enjoyed everything said against Linnaeus", he had a paper on the fossil and living 'Asteria' which he would not deliver to the Society as intends to publish it himself.</p><p>Found a 'Cicada aurita', said to be a German insect, 'Silpha germanica', and many previously undescribed insects, further activity hindered by multiple attacks of gout in the summer. Travelling to Hastings, Sussex, on Saturday to collect new insects. Filling his insect cabinet with [Thomas] Marsham and [William] Jones' assistance, latter acquiring 200 lepidoptera for him. Purchased [Carlo] Allioni's "Stirpes Piedmontana". Has set his writing-master to copy the defect in second volume of De Geer, a work he loves. Advises Smith to study closely [Joseph Pitton de] Tournefort's [(1656-1708)] herbarium and not to bother smuggling any French wine home as their is now an over-supply. Anxiety over the issue of affairs in Holland, many positive that there will be war, it is said [William] Pitt approves it but a "Great Personage" is against it, a few months ago they were of contrary opinions.</p><p>Envies Smith for the sights he has seen, and to have 'Orchis abortiva' and 'Orchis coriophora'. Has heard that the Oxford Botanical Garden is in a "terrible condition". Glad Smith left Pavia before publication of his translation of Linnaeus' "Dissertation on the sexes of plants" as [Lazzaro] Spallanzani [(1729-1799), physiologist] would "assassinate" him.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>