<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1229">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Thomas Johnes, Hafod, [Cardiganshire], to James Edward Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63190/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/16/75, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Johnes, Thomas">Thomas Johnes</persName>
                    <placeName>Hafod, Cardiganshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1803-09-22">22 Sep 1803</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Responds to Smith's letters of 26 and 31 August: Smith should have received Dr Ford's letter with [William] Roscoe's certificate. Has always intended to visit Burleigh, having heard the pictures highly spoken of, and recalls when at Loretto, [Austria ?], story told by the monks of the late Lord Exeter offering buy a Raphael for as many guineas it took to cover it, but they refused; comments that this would be "a cheap way of buying his pictures, compared with present prices". Will inform Smith of details of the Chancery suit next time he sees him, and he owes it entirely to Symmons.</p><p>Advises Smith to advertise his "Tour [to Hafod]" this winter and believes another 15 subscribers could be added to the 35 existing. Possible rival works: never answered Bowyer's letter, but "he is enterprising, and his things are in general tawdry &amp; badly done", in reference to his "Views of Egypt, &amp; the Levant"; Loutherbowey was in Wales 12 or 15 years ago and carried away many sketches; Mr Malkin of Hackney, [Middlesex], intends publishing a "Tour thro' South Wales" in one or more volumes with well engraved prints, and though Johnes believes it will not be very enlightening urges Smith that he has no time to lose.</p><p>Viganoni leaving on Monday: his improvement of Mariamne's playing and singing is "wonderful" but her drawing skills are equally good. Todd [his gardener] "cannot be trusted again" after his neglect of the kitchen garden and destruction of seeds, though he will take care of him [Todd sustained head injuries after falling from his horse, see RelatedMatieral below]. Requests any new Botany Bay seeds.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>