<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN2896">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">David Hosack, New York, to Sir James Edward Smith, Surrey Street, Norwich, [Norfolk]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/61933/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/5/83, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Hosack, David">David Hosack</persName>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>
                    <date when="1817-07-25">25 Jul 1817</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Norwich, Norfolk</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Received Smith's letter of 24 March and "Compendium [florae Britannicae]". [American] Philosphical Society to publish their second volume within the next six months, invites Smith to send a paper. Intending to send his son to Oxford or Cambridge. The books he is sending to Sir Joseph Banks and Horticultural Society, under care of his fellow former student [Joseph] Sabine, may differ from those he sends to Smith. Sending various unnamed magazines and publications, including book on "Life of Mr Fullar, inventor of steamboats", asks Smith to present it to the Royal Society after he has read it.</p><p>Sends papers on contemplated canal between Lake Erie and the Hudson river, work of which has begun under direction of DeWitt Clinton. Clinton has just been elected governor of New York, believes he will be the next President of the United States, nominates him to be a member of the Linnean and Royal Societies, lists his commendments including extensive botanical collections, referring Smith to second volume of "the Repository" for biographical information, shall write to Banks' on same subject.</p><p>Often sees [José Francisco] Corrêa de Serra who is enjoying a good income as the Portugeuse Minister to American government. Requests copy of third edition of Smith's "Elements"[?] and last edition of "Tour on the Continent"; "there is no book in our city library that has been more read". Bust of Smith placed in New York Institution. In reference to a conversation had in 1794 asks after the minerals in the Linnaean collections and whether the Institution would be able to purchase them.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>