<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN951">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">James Edward Smith, London, to Edmund Davall, Orbe, Canton de Berne, [Switzerland]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62931/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/14/47, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                    <date when="1792-02-21">21 Feb 1792</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Davall, Edmund">Edmund Davall</persName>
                    <placeName>Orbe, Switzerland</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>His street was not affected by the fire at the Pantheon, although [Robert] Batty's shop was destroyed and he and his family took refuge with Smith.</p><p>Responds to Davall's letters of 31 January and 3 February 1792: promises to visit Davall soon but wants to publish his "Sketch of a Tour on the Continent" and "Systema vegetabilum" first; François [Borone] to be [Adam] Afzelius' assistant in Sierra Leone, commissioned by the new Company to collect plants for at least a year, advantageous situation for Borone, and Smith will receive a share of the plants, roots, and seeds collected; when François returns Smith intends to tour to Genoa to visit Davall and Mount Cenis again; impatient to hear from [Dominique] Villars; applauds Davall's comments on naming of plants after botanists, shall give Davall's name to 'Trichomanes canariense' but requests a paper from him for second volume of "Linnean Transactions"; has no duplicate of 'Smithia sensitivia', it flowered and seeded at Turin in 1790; admires Davall's manner of drying plants.</p><p>[Carl Peter] Thunberg compared specimen of his [Smith's] 'Festuca' with [Joachim] Burser's [(1583-1639)] original specimen at Upsala, so there is now no doubt, but [Martin] Vahl [(1749-1804)] has published discovery as his own in second volume of "Symbolae botanicae" but made mistake of saying he learned what 'Anthoxanthum paniculatum' was from the Linnaean herbarium.</p><p>Has been introduced to the Royal Family as this summer he is to arrange the Queen's herbarium, previously [John] Lightfoot's, give the Queen and princesses a course of botany; comments on the Queen's behaviour and dignity. Has not taken any salary for the job for the sake of dignity and future influence and interest.</p><p>Prescribes a tablespoon of melted butter with the salt skimmed off before bed for Davall's costiveness; excellent for bowel complaints but "neglected for nasty drugs &amp; irritating oils". Eager to see vegetable part of [Johann Friedrich] Gmelin's [(1748-1804)] "Systema naturae". Glad Davall found [Johann] Hermann agreeable, "an excell[ent] &amp; pleasant man". Pleased Davall likes his figure of 'Festuca spadicea'. Waiting for lichens before sending parcel of plants, will also send second edition of "Flora Lapponica".</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>