<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN2184">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">William Jackson Hooker, Glasgow, to Sir James Edward Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/64017/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/23/11, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Hooker, Sir William Jackson">Sir William Jackson Hooker</persName>
                    <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>
                    <date when="1824-11-30">30 Nov 1824</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Thanks for botanical information in Smith's last letter, and for Smith's "friendly &amp; affectionate manners". Unsure of [Joseph] Sabine's intentions in erroneously reporting John Lindley's [(1799-1865)] involvement in "Flora Scotia".</p><p>Discusses his proposed "Species plantarum" in English, which will neither be a translation of Candolle's "Prodromus" nor an entirely original work; details; will be able to profit from consulting Smith's "English Flora"; queries on terminology; encloses a specimen of the work; will not commence printing until his return from London and Paris in March.</p><p>Has not received Nepalese plants from [Nathaniel] Wallich except one collection sent 5 years ago, and now understands that the East India Company requires that they have the distribution of all the specimens, but he continues to receive mosses from Wallich. Pleased the Company sent Smith "so fine a parcel of ferns", thanks the 'Darea' from it, which he wishes to figure in his "Exotic flora". Encloses a "fern-like plant"; observations; wishes to name the genus after its discoverer, Mr Parker; asks if 'Pteris thalictroides' or 'Pteris cornuta' belong to same genus. He has established botanical correspondence with Demerara and St Vincent's; has mosses to send Smith; wishes to consult him about 'Orchideae', of which every new species forms a new genus.</p><p>Lists plants for his "Exotic flora", including 'Marcgravia umbellata', 'Cassytha filiformis', 'Cytinus hypocistus'; has two plates engraved of the nutmeg and two new 'Tillandsiae'; about to figure 'Artocarpus incisa' and 'A. integrifolia'. Discusses 'Lepraria iolithos'. Expects "great things" from the unexplored parts of North America, having sent two botanists to the north-west coast; one is to join Captain Franklin and return overland with him, and the other to explore the vicinity of the Columbia [River]; appointing a third to go with Captain Franklin and Dr Richardson on their expedition as far as Saskatchewan and to remain their two years; further details. [Francis] Hamilton and [Francis] Boott both enquired after Smith.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>