<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN955">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">James Edward Smith, Matlock Bath, [Derbyshire], to Edmund Davall, Orbe, Canton de Berne, [Switzerland]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/62934/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/14/50, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Matlock Bath, Derbyshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1792-06-27">27 Jun 1792</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Davall, Edmund">Edmund Davall</persName>
                    <placeName>Orbe, Switzerland</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Following pleuritic attacks in spring and summer has come to Matlock Bath for air and waters. Sending locally gathered mosses and lichens with this letter. Responds to Davall's letter of 18 May 1792: has not yet received Davall's two packets; recommends he take the Bath waters or similar for his stomach; condolences on death of his baby; entreats him not to overexert himself in the garden or fields, to avoid damp and evening air, and wet feet; thanks for seeds of 'Carduus crispus'; spending two or three weeks at Windsor soon [teaching Royal Family botany]; [Dominique] Villars correct in what he says, he [Smith] will write preface for his paper on 'Arenaria' for second volume of "Linnean Transactions" in which he will fully explain his method of ascertaining the Linnaean species from original numbered and marked specimens, and show in what cases synonyms are to be greater authority than the herbarium, citing example of 'Carex pilulifera'; thanks for quotation from Schreber, pleased with his praise and has written to him on the strength of it.</p><p>[Joseph] Gaertner has died but finished his book in second volume ["De fructibus et seminibus plantarum" (1788-1805)], he is very severe on Linnaeus "but a good author may be pardoned for a few prejudices'. Surprised at the attention his "introductory discourse" has received; Father Gregorio Fontana, mathematical professor at Pavia, has translated it into Italian.</p><p>Received parcel of plants from Botany Bay, many unknown to [Sir Joseph] Banks and others, with coloured drawings of most, and if Banks will not publish his work sees no reason not to publish these. Paper on 'Filices' not quite finished. Considers it settled that 'Trichomanes canariense' is to be 'Davallia'. Sending Davall a "choice copy" of second part of "Icones pictae", a present from Lady Rockingham, and second part of "Spicilegium Botanicum"; hopes he approves of 'Ligusticum cornubiense'. Encloses part of 'Byssus aurea'. Also encloses for Mrs Davall a small smelling bottle made of the "beautiful spar of this place".</p><p>Note at end of letter: "to remark that 'Poa salina' of Pollich is = distans as well as the retroflexa of Curtis".</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>