<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1079">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">Sir Thomas Frankland, Thirkleby, York, to James Edward Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63020/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/15/44, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Frankland, Sir Thomas">Sir Thomas Frankland</persName>
                    <placeName>Thirkleby, Yorkshire</placeName>
                    <date when="1812-04-08">8 Apr 1812</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Experienced a mild winter with primroses in full flower on 30 January, though March was severe. His apricot trees which he protected with copper plate printers' canvas, recommended by Sir Joseph Banks, [Thomas] A[ndew] Knight [(1759-1838)], and [James] Dickson as being superior to Buntine, have many flowers.</p><p>Unconvinced by some authors claims that ivy is injurious to trees as it dies if separated from the root; plants of his cut three months ago are showing no sign of decay and neglect of ivy in his gardens has caused much injury but they are now attacking it on trees and transferring it to walls. Mr Knight's peas are not worth cultivating, they produced inferior quantity of seed over two seasons which is now all saved for a third crop. Knight's method for obtaining large onions failed twice as they always run to seed in second year.</p><p>Smith's 'Conferva urceolata' is [William] Hudson's 'nigrescens' but could not find it in his drawings as [Lewis Weston] Dillwyn [(1778-1855)] still has them, complains he has had them too long and requests Smith's assistance in recovering them.</p><p>Encloses note [extant] from Mr [James] Hoy dated Gordon Castle, [Scotland], 18 Dec 1811, thanking Frankland for specimen of 'Scheuzeria' and detailing the extent of the [Alexander Gordon, 4th] Duke of Gordon's [(1743-1827)] estates.</p><p>Recently "whip grafted" 'Ilex' on common oak, having been unsuccessful in the common way, and has one 14 feet high plant cleft-grafted on common oak in uncommon health. They were taken from 100 year old wild trees which are much more hardy than his native trees of beech, lime, sycamore, and horse chestnut, which have graudually died since an unmerciful thinning in 1785, though the 'Ilex' seems uninjured.</p><p>Smith's 'Glaucium' was in flower last November, and some raised from seed had yellow flowers. Packed 'Nuphar' seeds received from [James] Brodie in earth, paper, and matting, and sunk with stone in a hard water stewpond secreted by planatation.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>