<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN1370">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">James Edward Smith, Norwich, [Norfolk], to William Roscoe</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/63292/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance" sameAs="../../website-pages/repo/EP-REPO-238.xml">GB-110/JES/COR/17/61, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    <placeName>Norwich, Norfolk</placeName>
                    <date when="1808-08-14">14 Aug 1808</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Roscoe, William">William Roscoe</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Replies to Roscoe's letter of 1 May. Thanks for Roscoe's notes on 'Canna', though there is not much new information; asks native country of Roscoe's 'Canna latifolia' and any authority used. Doubts whether [James] Sowerby will continue "Exotic botany" as it does not sell enough for a profit, though if he went on slowly it would pay. His work for [Abraham] Rees' "Cyclopedia" has increased and now includes the whole botanical part and biographies of botanists following death of [William] Wood; he has accepted as it sells 5000 copies and will help advance botany; he puts an "S" to articles he wishes to be responsible for.</p><p>New edition of his "Introduction to Botany" printing but has only made corrections. Intends to produce a new work called "Illustrations of Botany" with figures of new and interesting plants and genera, with possible chapter illustrating and criticising Jussieu's system. Second part of "Florae Graecae prodromus" printing and will finish "Flora Britannica" this winter. As usual will spend September in Lowestoft, [Suffolk]. His health is good but has been anxious for Roscoe's sons' health. Forced to to give up his visit to Lancashire but hopeful for next year. Thanks for Roscoe's second pamphlet, admires the introduction but observes that recent events in Spain are unfavourable for Roscoe's ideas of peace, and "sickens at the old story of subsidising Austria &amp; Co again!".</p><p>Discussion of toads: asks after Roscoe's tale of a "toad in a hole in a wall" having just read a similar account in Roesel [von Rosenhof's (1705-1759)] "Historia naturalis rariarum"; his own observations of three live natterjack toads in his possession, 'Bufo terrestius foetidus' of Roesel t24; [Thomas] Pennant's "British Zoology" quotes Sir Joseph Banks on natterjacks but not Roesel.</p><p>[Letter probably incomplete: text interrupted, no signature or valediction]</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>