<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LINNEAN2392">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:id="main_title">William Roxburgh, Cape of Good Hope, [South Africa], to James Edward Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="James Edward Smith">The James Edward Smith Collection</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Linnean Society of London</authority>
                <ptr type="projectItem" target="http://linnean-online.org/64226/"/>
                <date when="2021-07-20">2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <ab type="p"><hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Sir James Edward Smith</hi>, The Linnean Society's Archive Catalogue</ab>
                <ab type="url">http://www2.calmview.co.uk/Linnean/record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=GB-110/JES</ab>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="provenance">GB-110/JES/COR/25/14, The Linnean Society of London</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="Roxburgh, William">William Roxburgh</persName>
                    <placeName>Cape of Good Hope, South Africa</placeName>
                    <date when="1798-04-23">23 Apr 1798</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="Smith, Sir James Edward">Sir James Edward Smith</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <abstract><p>Last wrote by Mr Brown, surgeon of the Albion, in December; hopes Smith received the seeds, specimens, and insects. Arrived at the Cape a few days ago; sending his son, George, to England under care of a surgeon from Bengal Establishment. Requests Smith's assistance in getting his son, William [(fl 1780s-1810)], who has been studying in Edinburgh, a place as a writer in Bengal Establishment, otherwise to have him appointed his botanical assistant; would write to [Aylmer Bourke] Lambert on subject but does not have an introduction.</p><p>His health suffered during the voyage but now feels recovered; intends to remain 6 or 8 months, or until William and his sister arrive. Sends box of insects, including many 'Phalena paphia', which yields a large quantity of strong silk, as Smith will see by the cocoons he has sent Sir Joseph Banks, and another species of 'Phalena', the caterpillars of which live on leaves of 'Palma christi', observations on its silk; has written an account on both but yet to publish. Also sends specimens of nutmeg in spirits.</p></abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div/></body>
    </text>
</TEI>